<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A view of the whole controversy between the representer and the answerer, with an answer to the representer's last reply in which are laid open some of the methods by which Protestants are misrepresented by papists.</title>
            <author>Clagett, William, 1646-1688.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1687</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 241 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 64 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A33225</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C4402</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R10868</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12387023</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12387023</idno>
            <idno type="VID">60861</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A33225)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 60861)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 656:1)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A view of the whole controversy between the representer and the answerer, with an answer to the representer's last reply in which are laid open some of the methods by which Protestants are misrepresented by papists.</title>
                  <author>Clagett, William, 1646-1688.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[3], 123, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for William Rogers ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1687.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Errata: prelim. p. [1].</note>
                  <note>Includes bibliographical references.</note>
                  <note>Advertisement: p. [1] at end.</note>
                  <note>By William Clagett. Cf. Halkett &amp; Laing.</note>
                  <note>Occasioned by John Gother's "A papist misrepresented and represented" and the replies thereto written by Edward Stillingfleet and  William Sherlock.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Gother, John, d. 1704. --  Papist misrepresented and represented.</term>
               <term>Stillingfleet, Edward, 1635-1699. --  Doctrines and practices of the Church of Rome truly represented.</term>
               <term>Sherlock, William, 1641?-1707. --  Papist not misrepresented by Protestants.</term>
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature.</term>
               <term>Church of England --  Doctrines.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>Corinne Vieracker</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>Corinne Vieracker</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:60861:1"/>
            <p>Imprimatur,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Jan.</hi> 7, 1686.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>JO. BATTELY.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <p>PAge 104. line 11. for <hi>the Jews</hi> r. their Perſons. P. 119. line 9. for <hi>Cockles</hi> r. <hi>Cocleus.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:60861:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A VIEW OF THE <hi>Whole Controverſy</hi> BETWEEN THE REPRESENTER AND THE ANSWERER, WITH AN <hi>Anſwer to the</hi> Repreſenter<hi>'s laſt Reply:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In which are laid open ſome of the Methods by which <hi>Proteſtants</hi> are Miſrepreſented by <hi>Papiſts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>William Rogers,</hi> at the <hi>Sun,</hi> againſt St. <hi>Dun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtan</hi>'s Church in <hi>Fleetſtreet,</hi> MDCLXXXVII.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:60861:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:60861:2"/>
            <head>A VIEW Of the Whole CONTROVERSY BETWEEN THE Repreſenter <hi>and the</hi> Anſwerer.</head>
            <p>THE <hi>Repreſenter</hi> was loth to part with his <hi>Anſwerer</hi> without <hi>asking him in civi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity how he did:</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reply, </seg>
               </label> 
               <note place="margin">p. 1.</note> Now from ſo civil a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, I may, for ought I know, have the courteſy of a turn or two, for asking; which if he will allow me, I ſhall at laſt deſire <hi>a word or two with him before we part, and that chiefly, in civi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity to ask him</hi> How <hi>He</hi> does? I would intreat him to go back with me as far as to <hi>a Papiſt Miſrepreſented and Repreſented,</hi> that we may ſee how matters have been carried all along, ſince that Book gave occaſion to this Controverſy. How I ſhall ſpeed in this Requeſt,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. to Pap. </seg>
               </label> 
               <note place="margin">Prot. &amp;c. p. 125.</note> is hard to ſay, for 'tis a favour that his Second Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary did not obtain, who fairly led the way, when the Walk was not quite ſo long as it is grown ſince. But with, or without his Company, this is the way I muſt needs go; and becauſe I will not do it, without giving the <hi>Repreſenter</hi> a Reaſon, 'tis this: I hope to ſatisfy
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:60861:3"/>thoſe who will go along with me, That he has but jeſted all this while; and (to make his words ſpeak truth for once) has <hi>paſſed over all his</hi> Adverſaries Anſwers <hi>with a light touch</hi> (moſt of them with none at all) <hi>and the moſt Artificial way of</hi> replying, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reply, </seg>
               </label> 
               <note place="margin">p. 2.</note> 
               <hi>with ſaying nothing to 'em, as can poſſibly be met with.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It was well done of him to tell the Reader in the Title Page of his laſt <hi>Reply,</hi> That it was a <hi>Fourth Vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dication of a Papiſt Miſrepreſented,</hi> &amp;c. for if he had not ſaid ſo, really men could not have believed it. There were <hi>Thirty ſeven</hi> double Characters of a <hi>Papiſt</hi> laid down with ſolemn order in the firſt Book, to tell the World what he is by us falſly ſaid to be, and what he is truly in himſelf: And this later <hi>Character</hi> was fortified with ſuch Arguments to juſtify his Faith and Practiſe, as could be had. What now is become of all this? What ſaies the <hi>Fourth Vindication</hi> in defence of any one particular Complaint, Repreſentation, or Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument? Why not a word that I can find, unleſs it be where he barely asks,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>P.</hi> 11.</note> What we think of <hi>Praying to Images,</hi> and of ſome few other things, and of more than he would ſpeak of, <hi>which ſtand charged upon the Character of a Papiſt Miſrepreſented.</hi> He puts theſe Queſtions ſhortly and confidently, as if nothing had been yet ſaid to any of them. And his behaviour would almoſt perſwade a man, that his double Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racters were yet to be conſidered, and his Reaſons yet to be Anſwered. So one would think indeed by comparing his firſt and laſt Books together, without obſerving what has come between them; or, at leaſt, that the Cauſe is dropt by one Side, or the other: And let him that thinks ſo, think ſo ſtill; for that is the plain Truth of the Caſe, which I ſhall make out by an Argument that will do the buſineſs to the ſatisfaction
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:60861:3"/>of all men but the <hi>Repreſenter;</hi> and that is, That <hi>He</hi> hath dropt it.</p>
            <p>This I ſhall do in the <hi>Firſt</hi> place, if it be but to try whether he will take notice of it in the beginning of this Anſwer, tho he would not beſtow a word upon it,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. to Pap. </seg>
               </label> 
               <note place="margin">Prot, P. 125.</note> when he found it at the end of another.</p>
            <p>And perhaps, now that the length of this Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſy, together with the windings and turnings of the <hi>Repreſenter,</hi> has made it ſomething, uneaſy to be comprehended; it may not be ungrateful to thoſe that have concerned themſelves in it, to have ſome gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral proſpect of it, all at once before them; which I ſhall make as ſhort and as eaſy as I can, in going through the ſeveral Books that have been written in this Cauſe, ſince the firſt.</p>
            <div type="answer">
               <head>
                  <hi>The Firſt Anſwer to the</hi> Repreſenter.</head>
               <p>THE firſt Book that called him to account, was <hi>The Doctrines and Practices of the Church of</hi> Rome <hi>truly Repreſented;</hi>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwer to In∣troduction. </seg>
                  </label> in which, the Learned Author, having firſt made ſome Exceptions againſt the <hi>Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenter</hi>'s way of proceeding in his double Characters, went on to examine his Characters Point by Point. Every Queſtion was particularly and exactly ſtated, and the ſenſe of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> about it was ſhewn, by the Decrees of the <hi>Trent</hi>-Council, or their <hi>Roman</hi> Catechiſm, or their Publick Offices, and their moſt approved Divines and Caſuiſts, as the matter required. This was done very diſtinctly throughout the whole <hi>Anſwer,</hi> where he ſaw cauſe to correct the ſtate of the Queſtion; that the Reader might ſee the grounds of every particular charge, that we and our
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:60861:4"/>Fathers have laid againſt the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> And thus, by the way, all the falſe colours of the <hi>Repreſenter</hi> were taken off, where he thought it for his purpoſe to lay them on too Foul on his <hi>Miſrepreſenting,</hi> or too Fair on his <hi>Repreſenting</hi> ſide.</p>
               <p>But this was not all; for whereas the <hi>Repreſenter,</hi> not altogether truſting to his Arts of Repreſentation, thought fit ſometimes to urge, never fail'd to inſinuate, Arguments in favour of his ſide of the Queſtion; The <hi>Anſwerer,</hi> without omitting any ſhadow of Reaſon offered by the <hi>Repreſenter,</hi> took all his Argumentations, and every pretence from Scripture, into particular exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation: I ſay, he took them one by one in their place and order, and made it appear, that they were very faulty; as we at leaſt thought, and as we may think ſtill, for any thing that we have heard to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary.</p>
               <p>Nay, to give occaſion to a more perfect under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of theſe matters, He took <hi>Popery as Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented by the Repreſenter</hi> himſelf in one Colume, and gave him <hi>Our Reaſons againſt it,</hi> in another.</p>
               <p>And becauſe, to gain the greater opinion of ſincerity, the <hi>Repreſenter</hi> had with <hi>Anathema</hi>'s diſclaimed ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral points, which, as he ſaid, are imputed to <hi>Papiſts</hi> by <hi>Proteſtants;</hi> the <hi>Anſwerer</hi> conſidered him here too, very particularly, and ſeemed to diſcover inſincerity in the <hi>Repreſenter,</hi> even where one would be moſt apt to believe him to be in good earneſt.</p>
               <p>To all which I muſt add, That this was done through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out with that Calmneſs and Moderation, that his Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſary did not think fit to diſſemble it. So that this Book wanted nothing to make it deſerve a fair and full Reply, or at leaſt ſome honourable ſort of Conceſſion, That the Subject would not bear it.</p>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:60861:4"/>
               <p>For ſurely no Method of Anſwering the <hi>Repreſenter</hi> could be more Compleat, Honeſt, and Manly, than this was; nor ſerve better to put all thoſe, for whoſe ſake Books are written, into a way of judging what Popery indeed is, and whether we have rightly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned it or no, if they were not already ſatisfied in theſe things; eſpecially becauſe all was done with that plainneſs and perſpicuity, that if the Diſcourſe was in any particular greatly defective, it could not but be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vious to an Adverſary, that was, it ſeems, thought a fit Perſon by his Superiors, to Repreſent Popery to this Kingdom, and to defend it againſt this Church.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="reply">
               <head>
                  <hi>The Firſt Reply of the</hi> Repreſenter.</head>
               <p>TO this Anſwer the <hi>Repreſenter</hi> publiſhed a <hi>Reply</hi> under the Title of <hi>Reflections</hi> upon it. Now did he in theſe <hi>Reflections</hi> undertake to ſhew from Point to Point, That the <hi>Anſwerer</hi> had without cauſe correct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed either the <hi>Miſrepreſenting</hi> or the <hi>Repreſenting</hi> Side, where he undertook to correct them? Did he, as the <hi>Anſwerer</hi> has done before him, take the Queſtions in their Order, to examine how they were ſtated, and where need was, did he pretend to ſtate them better? Nay, Did he bear up fairly to any one point of Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentation that his Adverſary thought fit to alter, and try by the force of his Learning to reduce it to what it was when he left it? No truly, his mind did not ſerve him, for ſtating of Queſtions.</p>
               <p>But did he not ſtand up in defence of his <hi>Anathema</hi>'s which his <hi>Anſwerer</hi> charged, not without giving Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons for it, with <hi>Art</hi> and <hi>Sophiſtry?</hi> No, he did not ſo much as offer at it.</p>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:60861:5"/>
               <p>What then was the buſineſs of his <hi>Reflections?</hi> Did they turn upon <hi>our Reaſons againſt Popery as Repreſented</hi> by the <hi>Repreſenter?</hi> No ſure; Nor was it likely that he ſhould be forward to anſwer our Arguments, that had no Fancy to defend his own.</p>
               <p>What? Did he not betake himſelf to make good his own particular Arguments in behalf of Popery, againſt his Adverſaries Anſwers? Nothing leſs, I aſſure you; he did not take care ſo much as of one Argument be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to any one point, but fairly left them all to take their Fortune: Is it not enough for a man to bring Arguments, but he muſt be troubled to defend them? Well; From this time forward, the <hi>Repreſenters</hi> buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs was not to <hi>Diſpute,</hi> but to <hi>Repreſent.</hi> But was it ſo from the beginning? The <hi>Repreſenter</hi> indeed has ever ſince ſo vehemently diſclaimed <hi>Diſputing,</hi> that per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps he only <hi>Repreſented</hi> at firſt. Let us therefore try that a little.</p>
               <p>Were there not three Arguments for <hi>Veneration of Images,</hi> and for <hi>Praying to Saints?</hi> Were not <hi>Moſes, Job, Stephen,</hi> the <hi>Romans,</hi> the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> the <hi>Epheſians,</hi> and <hi>almoſt every ſick Perſon that deſires the Prayers of the Congregation,</hi> engaged one way or other? Did he not argue for <hi>Tranſubſtantiation</hi> from our Saviours <hi>Words,</hi> from the <hi>Power</hi> of God, from the incompe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tency of <hi>Senſe</hi> and <hi>Reaſon</hi> to judg in this, no leſs than in ſome other caſes? I think this is <hi>Diſputing.</hi> There were three Texts of Scripture to juſtifie the <hi>Reſtrain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> of <hi>Chriſtian</hi> people <hi>from reading the Scripture.</hi> And if they are not vaniſhed out of the Book, there are about ſeven Reaſons for <hi>Communion in one Kind:</hi> The 12th Chapter of the 2d Book of <hi>Maccab.</hi> was once thought one good Authority for the Doctrine of <hi>Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatoy;</hi> and St. <hi>Matth.</hi> 12.32, another; And a little
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:60861:5"/>pretence of Antiquity there was beſide, and three or four more Reaſons for it; and in this ſtrain the Book went all along: Now this I ſay, Thoſe Arguments were not made by the <hi>Anſwerer,</hi> but they were anſwered by him, and ſo were all the reſt, and now they may go ſhift for themſelves.</p>
               <p>And yet this is the Gentleman, who with no ſmall opinion of himſelf, takes his Adverſary to task for <hi>let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting his Arguments drop,</hi> nay, <hi>for not ſaying one word to all his own Reaſons preſſed againſt himſelf;</hi> 
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Reply, </seg>
                  </label> 
                  <note place="margin">p. 2, 3, 4, &amp;c.</note> but <hi>letting the matter fall very cautiouſly, when it comes to his own turn of Diſputing and Defending his own Reaſonings,</hi> and that too <hi>in a Caſe directly appertaining to our main point of Repreſenting,</hi> &amp;c. Now this is a biting Accuſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, if it be a <hi>True</hi> one; and before we part, I hope we ſhall have a word or two about <hi>that.</hi> But if it were as true, as I am well aſſured 'tis falſe, the <hi>Repreſenter,</hi> of all men living, ſhould have made no words on't; and that not only becauſe himſelf is a moſt notorious exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of forſaking his own Arguments in their diſtreſs, but becauſe his Adverſary was ſo generous to wink at <hi>him</hi> when <hi>he</hi> ſtole off from his Diſputing poſt, upon the very firſt attack that was made upon <hi>him.</hi> For I do not remember that he charges him with this, in ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the progreſs of the Controverſie; and indeed, conſidering all his other Advantages, there was no need of it. So that if the <hi>Repreſenter</hi> had been con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, this might have been forgotten ſtill; but if a man ows himſelf a ſhame, he does well to pay it.</p>
               <p>Well, but what went the <hi>Reflections</hi> upon, all this while? By this time I think a ſtranger may gueſs the Truth, and that is, that the <hi>Reflections</hi> were to flut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter up and down between the Anſwer to the <hi>Intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction,</hi> and the Anſwer to the <hi>Book;</hi> and to ſettle
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:60861:6"/>no where. And now I ſhall give as ſhort and faithful an abſtract of them, as I can. In the Anſwer to the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troduction, the <hi>Anſwerer</hi> declared himſelf unſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied with the <hi>Repreſenters method to clear his Party from Miſrepreſentations;</hi> and particularly, that he ſhould make his own <hi>ignorant, childiſh,</hi> or <hi>wilful mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtakes,</hi> the Proteſtant Repreſentations of Popery, as that <hi>the Papiſts are never permitted to hear Sermons which they are able to underſtand,</hi> and the like. Now from hence the Repreſenter deſires leave to aſſure his Friends, that the Proteſtant Repreſentations of Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery are <hi>ignorant, <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Reply, </seg>
                     </label> 
                     <note place="margin">p. 4.</note> childiſh,</hi> or <hi>wilful miſtakes.</hi> One would not have expected ſo mean a Cavil, ſo ſoon after he had promiſed <hi>moſt material Points;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>p.</hi> 1.</note> But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I find in his <hi>Proteſting Reply,</hi> that he is aſhamed to own it, I ſhall take no further notice of this, than to tell him, He ought to have been more aſhamed to deny it; it being ſo manifeſt, that what the Anſwerer ſaid of <hi>ſome</hi> of his Miſrepreſentations, he applied to <hi>all</hi> that himſelf calls <hi>Miſrepreſentations,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>An. p.</hi> 10. <hi>Rep. p.</hi> 3, 4.</note> that his utmoſt Art will never be able to diſguiſe it to any man that will take ſo much fruitleſs pains, as to compare the places. But to proceed,</p>
               <p n="1">1. Whereas the Anſwerer juſtly expoſed him for pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending to <hi>draw his Miſrepreſentantions exactly accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to his own Apprehenſions,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pag. 2, 3.</note> when himſelf was a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant; he now affirms, that he can juſtifie his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Characters of Papiſts, by Proteſtant Books, which he names, and out of one of them [<hi>Sutcliffs Survey</hi>) he produces ſome ſharp ſayings concerning Popery. Nay, he thinks to defend his Complaints of Miſrepreſentation, by thoſe very words of the <hi>Anſwerer</hi> concerning <hi>that Popery which the Repreſenter allows.
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:60861:6"/>we can never yield to it without betraying the Truth, renouncing our Senſes and our Reaſon, wounding our Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Whereas the <hi>Anſwerer</hi> excepted againſt his <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſenting Part,</hi> wherein he pretends to keep to a Rule, That the <hi>Repreſenter</hi> ſhewed no Authority that he, a private Man, had to interpret the Rule in his own Senſe, againſt the Judgment of Great Divines, as in the Queſtion of the <hi>Popes Perſonal Infallibility;</hi> and againſt the Determinations of Popes and Councils, as in the Queſtion concerning the <hi>Depoſing Power.</hi> The <hi>Repreſenter</hi> replies, That he followed the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil of <hi>Trent,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">P. 5, 6.</note> which he does not interpret, but takes in the Senſe of the <hi>Catechiſm:</hi> That he alſo kept to <hi>Veron</hi>'s Rule of Faith, and to the Biſhop of <hi>Condom</hi>'s Expoſition, ſo highly approved by Pope and Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> As to the Inſtances, having firſt ran to the Book for two more, he comes back with them to the two that were mentioned, and replies, 1. That where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as he <hi>limited</hi> the power of the Saints to help us <hi>to their prayers,</hi> he followed the Council, and the Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſm,<note place="margin">P. 7, 8.</note> 2. and the Biſhop of <hi>Condom.</hi> That he did not qualifie the Doctrine of <hi>Merit,</hi> without Authority, ſince it is ſo qualified by <hi>Trid. Seſſ.</hi> 6. <hi>Can.</hi> 26. 3. That the <hi>Popes Perſonal Infallibility</hi> is not determined by a General Council. 4 That the <hi>Deposing Power</hi> was never eſtabliſhed under an <hi>Anathema,</hi> as a Doctrinal Point;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>P.</hi> 9, 10.</note> and thoſe two are therefore no Articles of Faith.</p>
               <p n="3">3. He makes theſe <hi>Reflections</hi> upon the <hi>Anſwerers</hi> proceeding in the <hi>Book,</hi> That he either 1. owns part of the <hi>Repreſenters</hi> Doctrine to be the eſtabliſhed Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief of the Church of <hi>England:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>P.</hi> 11.</note> Or, 2. Does without
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:60861:7"/>good Reaſon deny part of it to be the Doctrine of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church, <hi>appealing from the Definitions of their Councils, and ſenſe of their Church,</hi> either to <hi>ſome Expreſſions found in old Maſs-Books and Rituals,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Or to ſome external Actions, in caſe of Reſpect ſhewn to Images and Saints,</hi> as <hi>Bowing, Kneeling,</hi> &amp;c. Or finally,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>P.</hi> 12.</note> to <hi>private Authors.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">P. 13, 14.</note> Upon which follows a grievous Complaint of Miſrepreſenting upon the laſt account.</p>
               <p n="4">4. From hence he goes back to the <hi>Anſwer to the Introduction,</hi> where he was charged for ſaying, That the Popes <hi>Orders are to be obeyed, whether he be infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible or not:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">P. 15, 16.</note> From whence it follows, That Papiſts <hi>are bound to Act, when the Pope ſhall require it, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Depoſing Power.</hi> He replies, That he gives no more to the Pope, than to Civil Soveraigns, whoſe Authority is not ſo <hi>abſolute and unconfined,</hi> but to <hi>ſome of their Decrees, there may be juſt exception.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. From hence he flings again into the middle of the Book, <note place="margin">P. 16.</note> and blames the <hi>Answerer</hi> for <hi>ſcouting amongſt the School-men,</hi> till the <hi>Queſtion about Diſpenſations to Lye or Forſwear, was loſt;</hi> and that he offered no proof, That the <hi>Diſpenſing Power was to be kept up as a Myſtery, and not uſed, but upon weighty Cauſes.</hi> Then he leaps into the Chapter of <hi>Purgatory,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">P. 17.</note> and affirms, That St. <hi>Perpetua's Viſion</hi> is not the Foundation of Purgatory,<note place="margin">P. 18.</note> but only uſed by him as a <hi>Marginal Citation amongſt many others.</hi> Then a Complaint of Miſrepre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentation again; and becauſe Complaints are not likely to convince us, <hi>Let us,</hi> ſays he, <hi>depend upon an Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience;<note place="margin">P. 19.</note> Do but give your Aſſent to thoſe Articles of Faith in the very Form and Manner, as I have ſtated them in the Character of a Papiſt Repreſented, and if you
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:60861:7"/>are not admitted into our Communion, I'le confeſs that I have abuſed the World.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus far the <hi>Reflections:</hi> It is now time to compare Things, and to ſee how much of the Cauſe is left ſtanding.</p>
               <p>I paſs it by, that the Anſwer to the <hi>Introduction,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>See for this Anſw. to Pap. Proteſt. p.</hi> 128.</note> upon which the <hi>Repreſenter</hi> ſpent his main Strength, is in many <hi>moſt material Points</hi> untouch'd by the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flections:</hi> But this is a ſmall Matter: For,</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>He has dropt the defence of his Double Characters, his Repreſentations and Miſrepreſentations.</hi> For in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of going on with his Adverſary in thoſe <hi>Thirty Seven</hi> Points, with which himſelf led the way, he does nothing but nibble about Three or Four of them, and that without taking notice of the tenth part of what was ſaid by his Adverſary to fix the true ſtate of the Controverſie even about them: He has indeed thrown about four Looſe, General Exceptions amongſt the Thirty Seven Chapters in which the <hi>Anſwerer</hi> Repreſented the ſeveral Doctrines and Practiſes of the Church of <hi>Rome;</hi> but he has not with any one of theſe Exceptions come up fairly to what the Anſwerer has ſaid upon any one particular Point; And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I add,</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>That for any thing our Repreſenter has done to ſhew the contrary, the Anſwerer has truly Repreſented the Doctrines and Practices of the Church of</hi> Rome. And then we have great Encouragement to turn Papiſts, ſince the <hi>Repreſenter</hi> tells us, That if the <hi>Anſwerer has truly Repreſented the Doctrines of the Church of Rome;</hi> He, the <hi>Repreſenter, would as ſoon be a Turk as a Papiſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:60861:8"/>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>He has abſolutely dropt the defence of all his own Arguments,</hi> not ſo much as pretending to ſhew where the Anſwers went upon a wrong State of the Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion; no, nor trying to reinforce his Arguments, where the State of the Controverſie was agreed upon on both ſides: So that for ought I can ſee, the <hi>Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenter</hi> fell ſick of his <hi>Thirty Seven</hi> Chapters all at once, both as to matter of <hi>Repreſentation</hi> and <hi>Diſpute:</hi> And this I think was pretty well for the <hi>Firſt Reply.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="answer">
               <head>The Second Anſwer to the Repreſenter, being a Reply to His Reflections.</head>
               <p>BUT we are to thank the <hi>Reflections</hi> for one good Thing, and that is for the Anſwer which they drew from another Learned Hand, under the Title of a <hi>Papiſt not Miſrepreſented by Proteſtants:</hi> In which I ſhall make bold to leave out ſeveral Material Points, which the <hi>Anſwerer</hi> offered too Conſideration, and take notice of no more, than what I think may ſerve to ſhew with what Sincerity on the One Side, and Inſincerity on the Other, this Controverſie has been managed. Wherefore,</p>
               <p n="1">1. Whereas the <hi>Repreſenter</hi> choſe to juſtify his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints of Miſrepreſentation, not by taking the firſt Anſwerers Repreſentations into examination, but by referring us to other Books, and to <hi>Sutcliff</hi>'s ſharp cenſures of Popery; The ſecond <hi>Anſwerer</hi> conſider'd that the <hi>Repreſenter</hi> called the <hi>Cenſures</hi> which Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:60861:8"/>puts upon the Avowed Doctrines and Practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the Church of <hi>Rome, Miſrepreſentations:</hi> which was in the firſt Book diſcernible enough, and ſpoken of in the Anſwer to it; but was ſo groſly owned in his ſecond Book, that no man could now doubt of it: For he made his <hi>Anſwerer</hi> guilty of Miſrepreſentation for ſaying, That <hi>we cannot yield to that Popery which the</hi> Repreſenter <hi>himſelf allows, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out betraying the Truth,</hi> &amp;c.<note place="margin">A Papiſt not Miſrepr. p. 4.</note> This Anſwer therefore blames him for putting into the <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentations of <hi>Popery,</hi> thoſe faults which we find, and thoſe ill conſequences which we charge upon <hi>Popery,</hi> as if we would make the World believe, that <hi>Papiſts</hi> think as ill of what themſelves <hi>profeſs</hi> and <hi>practice,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">P. 5.</note> as we do: And much more for putting theſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequences, as owned by <hi>Papiſts,</hi> in the Front of the <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Characters of them, as if we pretended, they were the <hi>Firſt Principles</hi> of <hi>Popery.</hi> As for the Doctrines and Practiſes of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church, which we charge them with, the <hi>Repreſenter gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally owned them;</hi> but he diſowned, <hi>as he eaſily might,</hi> the belief of thoſe Conſequences and Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretations which we charge upon them. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his putting them into the <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Characters of a <hi>Papiſt,</hi> was <hi>his own</hi> Artifice of laying the fouler colours upon <hi>Popery</hi> on the one ſide, that it might look the fairer, when he took them off, on the other. Now to prevent theſe Deceits for the future, this Anſwer goes through the Thirty ſeven Articles again,<note place="margin">P. 6. to p. 40.</note> to ſhew under each Head, what we charge <hi>upon them</hi> as their Doctrines and Practiſes; which is properly matter of <hi>Repreſentation:</hi> And likewiſe, what we charge <hi>upon ſuch Doctrines and
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:60861:9"/>Practiſes,</hi> which is properly matter of <hi>Diſpute:</hi> By the confounding of which two things, the <hi>Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenter</hi> had made a colour for his unjuſt complaints of <hi>Miſrepreſentation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. Whereas he pretended that he never delivered his own private ſense and opinion in Repreſenting a <hi>Papist;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">P. 44, 45.</note> the <hi>Anſwerer</hi> replies, that he certainly does ſo, when he determines concerning Queſtions which are diſputed among themſelves, whether they be Articles of Faith, or not; and that the <hi>Catechiſm</hi> may be interpreted by a private ſpirit as well as the <hi>Council.</hi> That <hi>Veron</hi>'s Rule, had no more Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority than the <hi>Repreſenter</hi>'s <hi>Characters.</hi> That <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larmines</hi> Controverſies had atteſtation from the Pope, as well as the Biſhop of <hi>Condom</hi>'s Expoſition; And that <hi>Canus</hi> himſelf, who is referred to by the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſenter,</hi> acknowledges that the Popes approbation is not always to <hi>be accounted the judgment of the Apoſtolick See.</hi> As to the Inſtances, The <hi>Anſwerer</hi> ſhews,<note place="margin">P. 45, 46.</note> I. <hi>Of his limitting the Power of the Saints to their Prayers;</hi> That no ſuch limitation of their Aid and Aſſiſtance, is to be found in the Council; That the <hi>Repreſenter</hi> would take no notice of what his firſt <hi>Anſwerer</hi> had ſaid, to ſhew that no ſuch limi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation was intended in the <hi>Council</hi> or the <hi>Catechiſm;</hi> And that he did not find this limitation in the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>Condom.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">P. 12, 13.</note> 2. Of <hi>Merit;</hi> That the Twenty ſixth Canon of the ſixth Seſſion, mentions nothing of it; and that it is clear from Chap. 16. of that Seſſion, That they make Good works truly and properly meritorious of Eternal Life, tho they grant the Grace of God, and the Merits of Chriſt, to be the cauſe of their own Merits. Finally, That the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:60861:9"/>
                  <hi>Anſwerer</hi> did not Appeal to the Thirty ſecond Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non to oppoſe the <hi>Repreſenter</hi>'s Qualification of the Doctrine of Merit,<note place="margin">P. 46. P. 47, 48.</note> and was therefore unconcern'd in his defence of it. 3. As to the <hi>Pope's Perſonal In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallibility;</hi> That he denies it to be of Faith, and makes it but a School point; whileſt there are as many who deny it to be a School point, and make it a matter of their Faith. That the want of <hi>poſitive Determination</hi> by a General Council, does not prove it to be no matter of Faith, becauſe neither the Infallibility of a General Council, nor of the Church, is poſitively determined by a General Council. That if Infallibility muſt be ſomewhere amongſt them, they have the beſt Reaſon that place it in the Pope. 4. As to the <hi>depoſing Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">P. 49.</note> the <hi>Anſwerer</hi> ſhewed largely and clearly, That Articles of Faith may be, and have been decreed without <hi>Anathema's;</hi> That the depoſing Decree in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes a Doctrinal point;<note place="margin">P. 54. P. 56.</note> That if it were meerly a point of Diſcipline and Government, they muſt either acknowledg it Lawful for the Church to depoſe Heretical Princes, or conſent that the Church is not ſecured from making wicked Decrees, in things that concern the whole Chriſtian World. That when the <hi>Repreſenter</hi> ſays, That ſome Decrees of <hi>Trent</hi> are not <hi>univerſally received,</hi> he does not tell us that the Council had no Authority to make them, and to oblige Princes to receive them. And laſtly, That the Pope's letting ſo many aſſerters of the <hi>No-de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing Power</hi> to paſs without any cenſure of Hereſy,<note place="margin">P. 57.</note> does not argue a change of their Doctrine, but only of the <hi>Times.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. To the <hi>Repreſenter</hi>'s Reflections upon the <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerer</hi>'s way of proceeding, as that 1. <hi>He owns in
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:60861:10"/>ſome part the Repreſenter's Doctrine to be the eſtabliſhed Doctrine of the Church of</hi> England; The ſecond <hi>Anſwerer</hi> charges him with foul Miſrepreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation upon this account, in as much as the firſt <hi>Anſwerer owned nothing which is peculiar to the Faith of a Papiſt, as diſtinguiſhed from thr common Faith of Chriſtians;</hi> and that the <hi>Repreſenter</hi> might as well have ſaid,<note place="margin">P. 59, 60, 61.</note> That <hi>becauſe Proteſtants own that Chriſt is to be worſhipped, therefore they</hi> in part <hi>own the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the Church of</hi> Rome, <hi>That Chriſt is to be worſhipped by Images.</hi> And this he ſhewed to be the very caſe in every one of thoſe ſix or ſeven Points, which the <hi>Repreſenter</hi> only named, but did not think fit to inſiſt upon, to ſhew how his Reflection was applicable to them. 2. And that the firſt <hi>Anſwerer appealed from the definitions of their Church,</hi> &amp;c. 1. <hi>To ſome Expoſitions found in old Maſs-Books and Rituals.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">P. 62.</note> This <hi>Anſwerer</hi> ſays, that he could find but one Inſtance of this, relating to the Worſhip of the Virgin <hi>Mary; viz.</hi> that ſcandalous Hymn, <hi>O Felix Puerpera,</hi> &amp;c. But that their Church is accountable for her old Miſſals, which were the allowed and eſtabliſhed Offices of Worſhip; That even this has never been condemned; but that Monſieur <hi>Widen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>felts</hi> Book was condemned at <hi>Rome,</hi> which was <hi>writ to bring the people to a bare</hi> Ora pro Nobis,<note place="margin">P. 63.</note> 
                  <hi>to the Bleſſed Virgin,</hi> 2. <hi>To ſome external Action as in caſe of reſpect ſhewn to Images and Saints.</hi> To this the <hi>Anſwerer</hi> ſays, That the <hi>Repreſenter</hi> brings in this Exception, without taking the leaſt notice of what his firſt Adverſary ſaid concerning external Adoration,<note place="margin">P. 63, 64.</note> That <hi>it is a part of Divine Worſhip;</hi> and that the Council of <hi>Trent</hi> requires it ſhould be
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:60861:10"/>given to Images. He ſhews further, That ſince there is ſuch a thing as external and viſible Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry; an Idolatrous action is nevertheleſs ſuch,<note place="margin">P. 65.</note> for the intention of him that is guilty of it, not to commit Idolatry;<note place="margin">P. 66.</note> That the worſhip of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſible Inhabitants of the other World, tho with ſuch external acts as may be paid to creatures, has always been accounted Religious Worſhip; That as the <hi>Degrees</hi> of Civil honour are diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh'd by the <hi>ſight of the Object;</hi> So one certain diſtinction between Civil and Religious is,<note place="margin">P. 67.</note> that the worſhip of an Inviſible Object is always <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious;</hi> and that to Worſhip the Image of an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſible Being, muſt therefore be Religious Worſhip alſo; becauſe 'tis referred to the <hi>Prototype.</hi> 3. <hi>To the ſentiments of private Authors.</hi> And here the preſent <hi>Anſwerer challenges him to give one inſtance wherein the Judgment of private Authors was,</hi> as he pretended, <hi>ſet up againſt the declared ſenſe of their Councils and Church:</hi> And moreover ſhews what uſe was made of private Authors, by particular Inſtances;<note place="margin">P. 68, 69.</note> and that ſometimes recourſe is neceſſary to be had to them, and to the general practice of their Church, to know the ſenſe of their Church.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Whereas the <hi>Repreſenter</hi> avoided the charge of their being obliged by his Doctrine to obey the Pope, when he commands them to act in purſuance of the Depoſing Power; by pretending that the Decrees of Popes may be excepted againſt no leſs than the commands of Civil Soveraigns, as the caſe may be. The <hi>Anſwerer</hi> does <hi>acknowledg this</hi> Reply <hi>to be good,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">P. 58.</note> if the <hi>Repreſenter</hi> be ſincere in the Application, and will <hi>grant the Depoſing De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:60861:11"/>to command a Sin;</hi> and that <hi>Bellarmin</hi> and <hi>Canus</hi> were miſtaken in aſſerting, That <hi>Popes and General Councils can make no ſinful Decrees relating to the whole Church.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. To the complaint of diſcourſing upon <hi>Diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſations</hi> out of the <hi>Schoolmen,</hi> and bearing the Read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er into a belief, that the <hi>Diſpenſing Power was kept as a Myſtery, to be uſed upon weighty occaſions,</hi> &amp;c. the preſent Anſwer ſaies, That there was reaſon for the former, this being one of the Inſtances wherein the whole ſenſe of their Church is not to be had, but from the Practices of Popes, and the Opinions of their Great men. To the latter, That their own <hi>Doctors</hi> had declared it, as the <hi>Anſwerer</hi> had ſhewn, before he ſaid it himſelf. Then as to St. <hi>Perpetua</hi>'s Viſion, That if <hi>he did not think it gave ſome cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit to the Doctrine of Purgatory,</hi> it was <hi>mentioned</hi> by him to no purpoſe. Finally, to the <hi>Repreſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er</hi>'s Invitation of us to come over to their Church upon his Terms, with promiſe of Acceptance; the <hi>Anſwerer</hi> returns, That he muſt <hi>like their Faith bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter firſt.</hi> And certainly the Invitation was ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing unſeaſonable, before the <hi>Repreſenter</hi> had an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer'd <hi>our Reaſons againſt that Popery, which</hi> himſelf <hi>allows.</hi> And this for the ſecond Anſwer.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="reply">
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:60861:11"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>The Second Reply of the</hi> Repreſenter, <hi>being an Anſwer, to</hi> a Papiſt not Miſrepreſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by Proteſtants.</head>
               <p>THE ſecond <hi>Reply</hi> comes forth under the Title of <hi>Papiſts Proteſting againſt Proteſtant Popery.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pap. Prot. p.4.</note> In which the <hi>Repreſenter</hi> beginning with a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of himſelf as to his conſtruction of the <hi>wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful miſtakes,</hi> (ſee before, <hi>p.</hi> 8.) which if he pleaſes ſhall be forgotten from this time forward: falls a wondring that there ſhould be <hi>ſuch a noiſe about expoſing of their Doctrines to open view;</hi> declares, that tho <hi>he diſcovered what he thought, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times ſaid briefly, why;</hi> yet he <hi>made not diſputing his buſineſs;</hi> and knows not how this ſhould be taken as a piece of controverſy againſt the Church of <hi>England,</hi> which he had not charged with <hi>Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>repreſentation,</hi> nor any body elſe, but thoſe only in general that are guilty. He complains that his ſecond <hi>Anſwerer</hi> makes that which they call <hi>Miſrepreſentation,</hi> to be <hi>in all the material points,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">P. 6.</note> a <hi>Repreſentation</hi> of the <hi>avowed Doctrine and Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of the Church of</hi> Rome; and proteſts, That if <hi>Popery be guilty of what he ſaies, it cannot enter into his thoughts there's any room for it in Heaven.</hi> For the <hi>very Title</hi> of his Book <hi>is a condemnation of the Religion to all thoſe horrid ſhapes it has been at any time expoſed in by the Members of the Reformation:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">P. 7.</note> And ſo is his pretence, that <hi>We
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:60861:12"/>charge Papiſts with nothing but what they expreſly profeſs to believe, and what they practice.</hi> But ſince they muſt not learn what <hi>Papiſts</hi> believe from the <hi>Council</hi> and the <hi>Catechiſm,</hi> but from the <hi>Writings</hi> and <hi>Sermons</hi> of <hi>Proteſtants;</hi> he is reſolved to give us a taft of their way of Repreſenting Popery; and therefore,</p>
               <p n="1">1. He recites ſeveral paſſages wherein Popery is Miſrepreſented, as he will have it, out of a Book of <hi>John,</hi> ſometime Lord Archbiſhop of <hi>York,</hi> and a Book of Dr. <hi>Beard,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">P. 9. to p. 17.</note> and <hi>Sutcliffs Survey,</hi> and the Book of <hi>Homilies.</hi> And in concluſion he tells us. That this is the <hi>Proteſtant Popery,</hi> which ſince he proteſts againſt no leſs than the <hi>Anſwerer, Proteſtants</hi> and <hi>Papiſts</hi> may now go <hi>ſhake hands;</hi> and <hi>What <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> poſſibility is there of farther diviſions?</hi> But if this be intended for a true Repreſentation of Popery, <hi>Roman Catholicks ſuffer under the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt injuſtice imaginable.</hi> And then follows a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hement expoſtulation againſt the iniquity of ſuch <hi>Miſrepreſentation.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">P. 18.</note> And whereas the <hi>Anſwerer</hi> bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med him for putting into the Proteſtant Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter of a Papiſt, thoſe ill conſequences we charge upon their Doctrines and Practices, as if we pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended that they think of their own profeſſion and practice juſt as we do:<note place="margin">P. 20.</note> He Replies, That this is a <hi>pretty ſpeculative quarrel,</hi> and <hi>a quaint conceit,</hi> but <hi>loſt, ſor coming in a wrong place.</hi> For the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſenter</hi>'s buſineſs was to <hi>draw the Character</hi> of a Papiſt, <hi>as it lies in the Peopels Heads,</hi> who when they hear one declaiming againſt Popery, do not <hi>diſtinguiſh between Antecedents and Conſequents,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the <hi>Doctrine of the Papiſts,</hi> and the fault
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:60861:12"/>we find with it, but <hi>ſwallow down all in the lump;</hi> and <hi>whoever ſuppoſes</hi> otherwiſe, <hi>muſt conclude them to be better at</hi> ſeparating, <hi>than the</hi> Chymiſts, and <hi>that in ſubtle</hi> Diſtinctions <hi>they are able to out-do</hi> Ariſtotle <hi>him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">P. 22.</note> This is in ſhort, what he ſays with much circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, and no little contentment, for four Pages to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether; and 'tis all that he thinks ſit to return to his <hi>Anſwerers</hi> careful diſtinction between matters of <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentation</hi> and of <hi>Diſpute,</hi> through all the Particulars: For though he confeſſes 'tis <hi>Learnedly</hi> done, yet the almoſt <hi>Forty Pages</hi> about it, might have been ſpared, becauſe <hi>this Diſtinction is not to be found in the Notion the people have of Popery.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">P. 23.</note>
               </p>
               <p>For the reſt, about his <hi>denying the Belief of our Interpretations,</hi> and the two other Particulars, <hi>p.</hi> 24. They are ſo little to the Purpoſe, that I can afford them no room in this Abſtract; and he that will not take my Word for it, may go to the Anſwer to <hi>Pap. Prot.</hi> p. 20, 21. and there ſatisfie himſelf.</p>
               <p n="2">2. To his Adverſaries Queſtion, Whether the <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techism</hi> may not be expounded <hi>by a private Spirit,</hi> as well as the <hi>Council?</hi> He ſays, <hi>Thus a Queſtion or two is a full Confutation of the Reflecter.</hi> To the Teſtimony of <hi>Canus,</hi> That <hi>that is not to be account<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Judgment of the Apoſtolick See, which is given only by the Biſhop of</hi> Rome, <hi>privately, maliciouſly, and inconſiderately,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">P. 25.</note> &amp;c. He replies, That ſo <hi>Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend an Authority,</hi> as that of the Biſhop of <hi>Condom,</hi> is not to be thus <hi>overthrown,</hi> ſince his <hi>Expoſition</hi> was <hi>examined with all due Deliberation, approved with all Solemnity,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">P. 26.</note> &amp;c. <hi>and recommended by his Holineſs to be read by all the Faithful:</hi> Upon which occaſion he puts himſelf into ſome Heat, That we who pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:60861:13"/>
                  <hi>againſt their Religion</hi> ſhould pretend to <hi>under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand</hi> it better than a <hi>Catholick Prelate eminent in the Church,</hi> &amp;c. and than thos;e who <hi>depend upon it for their Salvation.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">P. 27.</note> As to the Inſtances; and 1. Of the <hi>Invocation of Saints,</hi> he ſays; Their Aid and Aſſiſtance is limited to their Prayers, by the Biſhop of <hi>Condom,</hi> and cites the place; but to what his Adverſary ſaid concerning the Intention of the Council, and of the Catechiſm in this Matter, he ſays nothing. The Inſtance of <hi>Merit</hi> he paſſes by: But <hi>2dly,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">P. 28, 29.</note> and <hi>3dly,</hi> As to the <hi>Popes Perſonal Infallibility,</hi> and the <hi>Depoſing Power,</hi> he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pleads the Authority of the Biſhop of <hi>Condom,</hi> that they are no more than matters of <hi>School-Debate:</hi> and, as if he had been in good earneſt at firſt, he does again promiſe we ſhall be admitted into his Church, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the belief of theſe Articles: So that he has every way Repreſented the Faith of a <hi>Papiſt</hi> aright; and now has found out ſomething in his Adverſary to be <hi>anſwered with a ſmile,</hi> That a <hi>Proteſtant ſhould underſtand the Faith of a Papiſt better than the Papiſt himſelf does.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">P. 30.</note> And thus all being guarded by the Biſhop of <hi>Condom</hi>'s Authority, and his own Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal, it was his mere Civility to take any notice of his Adverſaries anſwers to his Argument about the <hi>Depoſing Power,</hi> from the want of an <hi>Anathema</hi> to the Decree. And ſo he replies, 1. That every thing is not <hi>an Article of Faith,</hi> which <hi>is declared in a Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Council, without an Anathema.</hi> 2. That <hi>to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree what ſhall be done,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">P. 30, 31.</note> does not include a Virtual Definition of Doctrine, as he thinks his Adverſary himſelf ſhewed under the next Particular, from the Council of the Apoſtles at <hi>Hieruſalem.</hi> 3. That
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:60861:13"/>the Depoſing Decree does not <hi>relate to things neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to Salvation,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">P. 32.</note> nor <hi>concerns the whole Church.</hi> And whereas his Adverſary imputes the Eſcape of thoſe that oppoſe this Decree, to a Change of Times, and the <hi>Popes want of Power,</hi> he tells us, That <hi>Oracles are ceas'd now-a-days.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. As to <hi>Veneration of Images,</hi> he ſays, That al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though <hi>Acts of Honour expreſſed to any Image that has Relation to ſome Inviſible Being, be ſuppoſed a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious Honour,</hi> yet <hi>all religious Reſpect and Honour is not ſo a Divine Honour,<note place="margin">P. 33.</note> as to make a God conſtructively of the thing to which it is paid:</hi> Otherwiſe <hi>Bowing to the Altar,</hi> and to the <hi>Name of Jeſus;</hi> cannot be excuſed,<note place="margin">P. 34.</note> ſince theſe things <hi>relate to the Inviſible Inhabitants of the other World;</hi> nay, <hi>All religious Reſpect, beſides to God,</hi> muſt then be <hi>conſtructive Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">P. 35.</note> Therefore as the different Kinds and Degrees of Civil Honour are diſtinguiſhed by the ſight of the Objects, tho the External Acts are the ſame, ſo the different Kinds and Degrees of Religious Honour are diſtinguiſhed by the Intention of the Givers, and by Circumſtances. He ſays further, as to the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alterableneſs of the Nature of Actions determined by a Law,<note place="margin">P. 36.</note> That if this makes the Intention of doing no evil in Bowing or Kneeling to an Image, unable to excuſe thoſe from ſin, who do this forbidden thing; this <hi>ſtrikes as ſeverely at Bowing to the Altar, and Kneeling to the Sacrament, as at them,</hi> ſince the Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons forbidden, are the ſame part of Divine Worſhip in both Caſes. Finally,<note place="margin">P. 36, 37.</note> That a Quaker may juſtifie his <hi>Tea's</hi> and <hi>Nays,</hi> by his Adverſaries Rule, That no Intention can alter the Nature of Actions deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined by a Divine Law, ſince it is ſaid, <hi>Matth.</hi> 5.34.
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:60861:14"/>
                  <hi>Swear not at all, but let your Communication,</hi> &amp;c. And now to give him his due, ſetting aſide the frivolous Inſtance of the <hi>Quakers,</hi> he has in this Particular come up fairly to his Adverſary, and ſaid what de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves; to be conſidered. Then he concludes with two or three <hi>Requeſts,</hi> which he <hi>hopes</hi> are not <hi>unreaſonable;</hi> to which his Adverſary gave ſuch reaſonable Anſwers, that we have heard of them no more ſince that time, [See <hi>Anſ.</hi> to <hi>Pap. Prot.</hi> p. 124, 125.] and therefore we have no reaſon to be troubled with them here. And ſo let us now come to a Reckoning.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>He grants his Adverſaries Diſtinction throughout, between matters of Repreſentation, and matters of Diſpute;</hi> which Diſtinction, ſince himſelf did not obſerve, he either wanted the Skill or the Honeſty of a Repreſenter.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The <hi>Defence of his Argument,</hi> That the Popes Perſonal Infallibility is not of Faith, <hi>from no General Council's having determined it,</hi> is dropt.</p>
               <p n="3">3. He will not be brought to ſay, Whether the Council of <hi>Trent</hi> had, or had not Authority to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lige Princes to receive thoſe Decrees which are not univerſally received; and ſo the <hi>Defence of his Argument, from ſome Decrees not being received,</hi> is dropt.</p>
               <p n="4">4. His ſolemn Cavil, That the Firſt <hi>Anſwerer own<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed</hi> ſome part of his (the <hi>Repreſenter</hi>'s) Doctrine, to be <hi>the Eſtabliſhed Doctrine of the Church of England;</hi> and his Objection againſt him for appealing <hi>to old Maſs-Books and Rituals,</hi> and that other for appealing <hi>to private Authors,</hi> are all three dropt.</p>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:60861:14"/>
               <p n="5">5. He will not ſay that the <hi>Depoſing Decree com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands a Sin;</hi> and to <hi>his Defence</hi> of himſelf againſt his firſt <hi>Anſwerer</hi>'s Charge, That by his Principles he is bound upon the Pope's command, <hi>to act ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Depoſing Power,</hi> is dropt.</p>
               <p n="6">6. His complaints againſt his firſt <hi>Anſwerer</hi>'s <hi>Repreſenting</hi> the matter of <hi>Diſpenſations;</hi> and his note upon St. <hi>Perpetua</hi>'s <hi>Viſion,</hi> are dropt: But his Invitation of us to come over to the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> upon his Terms, is not dropt; for we thank him, he has invited us again.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="answer">
               <head>
                  <hi>The Third Anſwer to the</hi> Repreſenter, <hi>being</hi> An Anſwer to a Papiſt Proteſting a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst Proteſtant Popery.</head>
               <p>To the <hi>Repreſenter</hi>'s wonder, That ſuch ado ſhould be made about his Firſt Book, the <hi>Anſwerer</hi> ſales,<note place="margin">P. 1.</note> That a <hi>Miſrepreſenter is ſo foul a character, that no man can wonder if we think our ſelves concerned to wipe it off;</hi> which ſurely may be done without offence to any, but thoſe that meant us, in the general Accuſation. To his complaint that the <hi>Anſwerer</hi> makes, All that which they call <hi>Miſrepreſentation,</hi> to be in <hi>all the material points a Repreſentation of the avowed Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine and Practice of the Church of</hi> Rome, he ſaies, That he has done him all the ſervice he can in diſtinguiſhing between matters of Fact, wherein
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:60861:15"/>if we charge them wrong, we do indeed Miſre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent them; and matters of Diſpute, in which, if we ſhould charge them wrong, it is not Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>repreſentation, but merely a wrong Judgment upon what they profeſs and practice.<note place="margin">P. 2.</note> And he had already ſhewn, That <hi>all matters of Fact</hi> (excepting ſome few points) <hi>in the Character of a Papiſt Miſrepre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented, are confeſſed and defended in the Character of a Papiſt Repreſented.</hi> Now Repreſentation or Miſrepreſentation is properly about matters of Fact. But as for the Conſequences we charge upon their Doctrines and Practices, and which were put into the <hi>Miſrepreſenting</hi> Side, to be taken off again in the <hi>Repreſenting</hi> Side; they are not matters of <hi>Repreſentation,</hi> but of <hi>Diſpute.</hi> To this purpoſe the <hi>Anſwerer</hi> argues, leaving the <hi>Repreſenter</hi> to apply theſe plain things to his <hi>Proteſtation againſt Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Popery;</hi> which amounts to thus much, That it could <hi>never enter into him, that there ſhould be any room for Popery in Heaven; and that he would as ſoon be a Turk as a Papiſt,</hi> if he thought as ill of the confeſſed Doctrines and Practices of the <hi>Church of</hi> Rome, as we do. Which would be a wiſe Speech no doubt, tho we hope a true one. For the reſt,<note place="margin">P. 3.</note> he ſaies, That <hi>his Title related only to his own Book; and the Book, to the Character of a Papiſt Miſrepreſented;</hi> and therefore 'tis hard that he muſt be <hi>drawn in to anſwer</hi> for more than he knows, even for all that any Proteſtant may have ſaid concerning Popery <hi>ſince the Reformation;</hi> and he thinks it ſtrange, that the <hi>Repreſenter, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of defending his own Characters, ſhould hunt about for new Miſrepreſentations for him to Anſwer.</hi>
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:60861:15"/>For ſince he has allowed the Diſtinction between matters of <hi>Repreſentation</hi> and <hi>Diſpute,</hi> and can find no fault with his Adverſaries performance about it; it ſhould ſeem we are agreed upon the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentation of <hi>Popery</hi> now at laſt,
<note place="margin">P. 4.</note> and therefore unleſs he <hi>were aſhamed</hi> of his own <hi>Popery,</hi> now we had clearly found it, why ſhould he divert from that, to new complaints of their being Miſrepre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented by others?</p>
               <p>The <hi>Anſwerer</hi> however was reſolved to ſee what occaſion there was for this freſh complaint.</p>
               <p n="1">1. And he ſhews,<note place="margin">P. 5, 6, 7, 8, 9.</note> That <hi>if what was tranſcribed out of the foreſaid Archbiſhop of</hi> York<hi>'s Book, be Miſrepreſentation, it is not a Proteſtant, but a Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh Miſrepreſentation: For the Archbiſhop cites his Authors for what he ſaies,</hi> tho the Repreſenter <hi>left them out;</hi> And this the <hi>Anſwerer</hi> thought good to ſhew from point to point: And concludes, That <hi>tho every Doctrine found in Popiſh Authors, ought not preſently to he accounted an Article of the Romiſh Faith; yet a Church</hi> ſo watchful to purge, expunge, and cenſure in all Caſes where her Intereſt is concern'd, is Reſponſible for thoſe Doctrines, which have her Toleration and Licenſe, and which <hi>any man among them is allowed to Teach, and to Believe.</hi> As for Dr. <hi>Beard,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Sutcliff,</hi> he ſaies,<note place="margin">P. 10, 11, 12, 13.</note> Thoſe Sayings do not concern <hi>Repreſenting,</hi> but <hi>Diſputing;</hi> and that the <hi>Repreſenter</hi> had unfaithfully concealed, either their Authorities or their Reaſons, which had made the thing plain; or curtail'd their ſayings, as he ſhews by ſeveral Inſtances out of Mr. <hi>Sutcliff;</hi> but that when ſuch Conſequences, are charged upon
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:60861:16"/>Popery, it is more to the purpoſe to Confute them, than to complain of Miſrepreſentation. Finally, As to the Book of <hi>Homilies,</hi> thoſe things which he hath taken out of it, as the <hi>Anſwerer</hi> tells him,<note place="margin">P. 14.</note> do no more than ſhew <hi>the Judgment of our Church about the Worſhip of Saints and Images in the Church of</hi> Rome; in which he cannot prove us to be Miſrepreſenters, otherwiſe than by <hi>confuting</hi> our Arguments; which yet would but ſhew that we make a wrong Judgment in a matter of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpute, not that we Miſrepreſent a matter of Fact. Upon this, the <hi>Anſwerer</hi> ſhews, That <hi>Papiſts</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſs and practice the ſame things that ever they did; and that all this grievous cry of <hi>Miſrepre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting,</hi> is grounded upon nothing elſe, but a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtation, That they do not believe thoſe ill things of their own Doctrine and Practice, which we do;<note place="margin">P. 15, 16.</note> which altho it be a new buſineſs yet, there was no Reaſon for it, ſince we never ſaid they did. In the mean time, the Cauſe is the ſame, that ever it was, which is a ſufficient Anſwer to all that he ſaies of Proteſtants and Papiſts <hi>ſhaking hands,</hi> &amp;c. And whereas he makes the diſtinction between Repreſentation and Diſpute, to be a ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culation, above the Vulgar, and ſo was not to be regarded by him who drew the Character of a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt as it lay in the peoples heads; The <hi>Anſwerer</hi> thinks, That he who undertakes to make Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racters, is bound to conſider what belongs to it; and withal,<note place="margin">P. 17, 18, 19.</note> That our people are not ſo ſilly as to think (for inſtance) that Papiſts believe the Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of Images to be Idolatry; or that Idolatry is lawful, becauſe they Worſhip Images; but that if
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:60861:16"/>he wrote his Characters for the Information of ſuch Vulgar Heads,<note place="margin">P. 20.</note> as he fancies, he wrote to inform thoſe that can <hi>neither write nor read.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. As to his Repreſenting, That he did it not by a private Spirit, ſince he followed the Catechiſm; the <hi>Anſwerer</hi> had reaſon to ask, Whether the Catechiſm may not be interpreted by a private Spirit, as well as the Council, ſince their Divines differ in Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation of both; and as for the Popes Approbation,<note place="margin">P. 21.</note> he ſaid that <hi>Bellarmine's</hi> Controverſies had it, as well as the Biſhop of <hi>Condom</hi>'s Expoſition; to which the <hi>Repreſenter</hi> would ſay nothing; and he now ſays, That by <hi>Canus</hi> his Rule, the ſaid Biſhops Expoſition has not the Authority of the Apoſtolick See, unleſs the Pope had given Judgment for it <hi>ex Cathedra,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">P. 22.</note> which the <hi>Repreſenter</hi> alſo would take no notice of: But what he ſays further concerning the Nature and Deſign of the Approbations given to the Biſhop of <hi>Condom,</hi> I ſhall wholly paſs over, ſince it is by this time ſomewhat plain, that this Biſhops Authority has enough to do to ſhift for it ſelf, and is not in a Condition to ſpare any help to his Friends. As to the limitation of the Aid of the Saints to their Prayers, he acknowledges that it is to be found in the Biſhop of <hi>Condom,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">P. 118.</note> though he miſſed it, becauſe it came not in in the right place. But whereas the <hi>Repreſenter</hi> juſtifies his renouncing the <hi>Popes Perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Infallibility,</hi> and the <hi>Depoſing Doctrine,</hi> by the Authority of the ſaid Biſhop; the <hi>Anſwerer</hi> plainly ſhews the Biſhops great Judgment, in having or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered Matters ſo, as to ſave himſelf both with Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants, and with the Pope. To the <hi>Repreſenters</hi> Second Invitation; he anſwers, by making this Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſal,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:60861:17"/>Whether their Church would refuſe him ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittance,<note place="margin">P. 15.</note> if he ſhould come in upon <hi>Bellarmine</hi>'s terms in theſe Points, which contradict the <hi>Repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi>'s; though there <hi>be no reaſon for this Diſpute,</hi> ſince as he ſaid before,<note place="margin">P. 16.</note> he likes not the <hi>Roman</hi> Faith as the <hi>Repreſenter</hi> has deſcribed it? Now to his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies in behalf of the Depoſing Doctrine being <hi>no Article of Faith,</hi> the <hi>Anſwerer</hi> ſays, 1. That where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as the <hi>Repreſenter</hi> would prove <hi>it was not ſo,</hi> becauſe no <hi>Anathema</hi> was fixed to the Decree; it is ſomething ſtrange, that he ſhould now be content to ſay, Every thing is not an Article of Faith, which is declared without an <hi>Anathema;</hi> for this is next to a down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right Conceſſion that his Adverſary had baffled his Argument; and ſhews manifeſtly that he would ſeem to ſay ſomething, when he knew he had no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to ſay to the purpoſe. 2. He ſhews that the Decree of the Council at <hi>Hieruſalem</hi> did include a Virtual Definition of Doctrine. And 3. That the Depoſing Decree <hi>concerns the whole Church;</hi> and if it be a wicked Decree, that <hi>it relates to a thing ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to Salvation,</hi> by commanding to do that which it is neceſſary to Salvation not to do; and therefore he expects the <hi>Repreſenters further Conſideration</hi> of his three Anſwers.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Concerning the <hi>Worſhip of Images,</hi> the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſenter</hi> bids ſo fair for a Diſpute, that the <hi>Anſwerer</hi> took the occaſion, and examined not only what the Biſhop of <hi>Condom</hi> hath delivered upon it, but the ſeveral ways of ſtating it by their Divines; ſhewing that their Images are <hi>Repreſentatives</hi> to receive Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip in the Name and Stead of the <hi>Prototype;</hi> that in this Notion Image-Worſhip is condemned in the
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:60861:17"/>Scripture, and in what the evil of it conſiſted; a more particular Abridgment of that juſt Diſcourſe upon this Subject I cannot make, without either wronging the <hi>Anſwerer,</hi> or detaining the Reader here too long; and therefore I refer him alſo to the Book it ſelf for an Anſwer to the Charge upon <hi>Bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing towards the Altar,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">P. 83.</note> &amp;c.<note place="margin">P. 106, &amp;c.</note> And to the Apology for Image-Worſhip, from the <hi>Degree</hi> of the Honour that is given to Images: And to the <hi>Repreſenters</hi> Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jections againſt that way of diſtinguiſhing Religious from Civil Worſhip, by making that to be Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous,<note place="margin">P. 37, 38,39, 40.</note> which is given to the Inviſible Inhabitants of the other World;<note place="margin">P. 123.</note> and likewiſe to the pretended Parity of Reaſon in the <hi>Quakers</hi> Caſe. And thus much may ſerve for the Anſwer to Papiſts <hi>Proteſting againſt Proteſtant-Popery.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="reply">
               <head>
                  <hi>The Third Reply of the</hi> Repreſenter, <hi>in Return to the Foregoing Anſwer.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THE <hi>Repreſenter</hi> finds as little Comfort in Proteſting, as <hi>Diſputing,</hi> and ſo falls to <hi>Accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modate the Difference between the Repreſenter and the Anſwerer;</hi> and calls his, Work <hi>an Amicable Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodation.</hi> For now he grants the Proteſtants are not guilty of Miſrepreſentation <hi>in a strict and proper Senſe,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">P. 1. 2.</note> and is very ſorry that he and his <hi>Anſwerer</hi> underſtood one another no better before: He thinks indeed it was his <hi>Anſwerer</hi>'s Fault, not to conceive
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:60861:18"/>him right at firſt; and that if his Book had never been Anſwered, the <hi>Peace</hi> had never been broke; but he is perſwaded the Difference may be yet com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded;<note place="margin">P. 3.</note> For the Caſe at firſt was no more than this, That he perceiving the Unchriſtian Hatred which grew in the Vulgar, upon that falſe Notion of Popery,<note place="margin">P. 4.</note> which our <hi>Miſconſtructions,</hi> &amp;c. had drawn in their Imaginations; He, I ſay, Good Man! No leſs in Charity to Proteſtants, than in Juſtice to Papiſts, drew his Double Characters, to ſhew how Popery is Miſrepreſented.<note place="margin">P. 5.</note> But then comes an <hi>Adverſary and ſays, He has proved that the Character of a Papiſt Miſpreſented contains nothing in it, which in a strict and proper Senſe can be called a Miſrepreſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi> Now really <hi>he never meant to Fight for a Word; and had he but imagined,</hi> that his Adverſary had contended for no more,<note place="margin">P. 6.</note> 
                  <hi>he would have ſpared him the Charges and Sweat of laying down his Proofs</hi> the ſecond time.</p>
               <p>Wherefore to end the ſtrife, he <hi>ſolemnly declares, that the Title of the</hi> Papiſt Miſrepreſented, <hi>is not to be taken</hi> in its ſtrict and proper Senſe, as <hi>Miſrepreſenting signifies</hi> only downright Lying, <hi>or falſly charging matter of Fact, the whole Character being not indeed of this Nature; but in its</hi> larger or leſs proper Senſe, <hi>as it comprehends both</hi> Lying, Calumniating, Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>interpreting, Reproaching, Miſconſtruing, Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judging, <hi>and whatever elſe of this kind.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But that we may know what a <hi>Lover of Peace</hi> he is, he muſt, aſſure the <hi>Anſwerer,</hi> That this <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſcenſion</hi> is <hi>purely</hi> out of <hi>good Nature;<note place="margin">P. 7.</note> for betwixt Friends, he does not think</hi> the Anſwerer <hi>has advanced any thing that has the Face of a proof,</hi> That <hi>there can
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:60861:18"/>be no Miſrepreſenting where there is an Agreement about matter of Fact.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Repreſenting,</hi> he ſays,<note place="margin">P. 8</note> 
                  <hi>being nothing more than ſhewing a thing as it is in it ſelf; as many ways as a thing can be ſhewn, otherwiſe than 'tis in it ſelf, ſo many ways may it be properly Miſrepreſented;</hi> ſo that the <hi>Deſcription muſt agree with the Thing,</hi> not only in <hi>Matter of Fact,</hi> but likewiſe in Reſpect of <hi>Motive, Circumſtance, Intention, End,</hi> &amp;c. But according to the <hi>Awſwerers</hi> Rule, had the <hi>two Tribes</hi> and <hi>an Half,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">P. 9.</note> been declared Guilty of <hi>ſetting up Altar againſt Altar;</hi> and <hi>Hannah been ſet out amongſt her Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours for a Drunken Goſſip;</hi> here had been no Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>repreſentation, becauſe of ſome <hi>Matter of Fact</hi> in the Caſe. The <hi>Elders</hi> too, that <hi>offered Proof</hi> againſt <hi>Suſanna,</hi> ſince they <hi>ſaw her in the Garden,</hi> &amp;c.<note place="margin">P. 11.</note> were no Miſrepreſenters: Nor the <hi>Jews</hi> againſt; our <hi>Saviour;</hi> nor <hi>Infidels</hi> againſt the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> and <hi>Chriſtians;</hi> nor ſhall any be <hi>excluded from a ſhare in this Favour,</hi> but they that have <hi>Malice enough to Calum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niate, but want Wit to give a Reaſon for what they do,</hi> &amp;c. So much was the <hi>Repreſenter</hi> overcome with <hi>pure good Nature,</hi> that for <hi>Peace</hi> ſake he would <hi>yield</hi> to a Principle that can do ſuch things as theſe, if his Word may be taken for the Reaſon; but we have another Reaſon in the Wind preſently; For if this ſame Principle which he has ordered to protect the lewdeſt <hi>Defamations and Perjuries,</hi> will but do its Office upon the Church of <hi>England,</hi> he has had his Reward: And ſo he ſhews what execution he can do in the Mouth of ſome <hi>Zealous Brother,</hi> whoſe <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and Intereſt engages him</hi> to ſet out the Church of <hi>England,</hi> as we Repreſent the Church of <hi>Rome:</hi> To
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:60861:19"/>which Purpoſe he puts a Sermon into his Mouth, which whether it be a Copy or an Original, the Diſſenters may ſay when they pleaſe. But the Heads of it are ſuch as theſe,</p>
               <p>After a ſolemn Preface of Exhortation to keep out of the <hi>Swing</hi> and the <hi>Sweep of the Dragons Tail,</hi> he lays down his Doctrine,<note place="margin">P. 13, 14.</note> That the <hi>Church of England Mens Marks</hi> are the <hi>Marks</hi> of the <hi>Beaſt,</hi> which he proves by the <hi>large Revenues</hi> and <hi>State</hi> of their <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">P. 15.</note> who wear the <hi>Miter</hi> and the <hi>Croſier</hi> upon their <hi>Coaches</hi> while they <hi>Live,</hi> and upon their <hi>Tombs</hi> when they are <hi>Dead:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">P. 16.</note> By the <hi>Weekly Bill</hi> of <hi>London,</hi> which ſhews that <hi>Mary</hi> has <hi>Nineteen</hi> Churches, and <hi>Chriſt</hi> but <hi>Three;</hi> by the <hi>Pictures</hi> in their <hi>Bibles</hi> and <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-Prayer-Books;</hi> and by many other Marks as good as theſe;<note place="margin">P. 17, 18, &amp;c.</note> which becauſe they ſtick faſt to us, as he thinks, for any thing the <hi>Anſwerer</hi> has ſaid, muſt come over again in another place, and therefore the leſs Repetition ſhall ſerve now.</p>
               <p>Sermon being done, he asks whether this be <hi>Miſrepreſenting in a ſtrict and proper Senſe;</hi> and if not,<note place="margin">P. 34.</note> he is contented that the Word Miſrepreſenting in his Book ſhould not be taken ſo, <hi>i. e.</hi> for downright Lying; but, as we heard before, for <hi>wry Interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, weak Reaſonings,</hi> &amp;c. And here ends the <hi>Ami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cable Accommodation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For his <hi>picking up New Miſrepreſentations,</hi> he ſays he did it to ſhew that the former were not his <hi>own childiſh Conceits:</hi> For leaving out the <hi>Authorities</hi> of the <hi>Arch-Biſh p</hi> of <hi>Y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rk;</hi> that this <hi>makes nothing againſt him,</hi> becauſe <hi>the Queſtion is not, What ſome private Authors ſay;<note place="margin">P. 35.</note> but, What the Church believes;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">P. 36.</note> whoſe <hi>Faith cannot be fairly Repreſented</hi> from their
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:60861:19"/>Books though <hi>publiſhed by the Authority of Superiours:</hi> For producing what <hi>Sutcliff</hi> laid to their Charge, without producing his <hi>Reaſons;</hi> that his Reaſons were <hi>none</hi> of the <hi>Repreſenters concern,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">P. 37.</note> becauſe they <hi>nothing belong to Repreſenting,</hi> nor has the <hi>Anſwerer put his Approbation to them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He charges the <hi>Anſwerer</hi> with leaving out <hi>propter Deum</hi> in a Citation out of the <hi>Pontiſical,</hi> and this becauſe the Words were not for his pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe.</p>
               <p>In Concluſion, he is reſolved not Diſpute, ſince the <hi>Anſwerer knows no Reaſon for all this Diſpute,</hi> p. 26. and he cares not whether the <hi>Anſwerer likes his Religion or not;<note place="margin">P. 38.</note> He will be no other than a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſenter still; for We wiſe Converts do not love to go out of our way, but upon very good Grounds: The Biſhop of Condom has undertaken his own Vindication;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">P. 39.</note> and if he does but come off as well as the <hi>Repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> and 'tis ſtrange if he ſhould not, let <hi>Bellar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine and other Eminent Approved Authors</hi> ſay what they can, he has <hi>no Concern in it,</hi> but his Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentation, and the Biſhops Expoſition, are the <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thentick Rule</hi> for the <hi>Expoſition</hi> of the Council of <hi>Trent;</hi> for the embracing the Catholick Faith, as <hi>Expounded</hi> by one, and <hi>Propoſed</hi> by the other, is ſufficient for a Perſon to be received into the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion of their Church.<note place="margin">P. 40.</note>
               </p>
               <p>We are now coming to the Foot of the Account; for beſides other Particulars of leſs moment that are dropt,</p>
               <p n="1">1. Whereas his only Reply to the clear and, particular Diſtinctions of his <hi>Anſwerer</hi> between
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:60861:20"/>Matters of Repreſentation, and Matters of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpute, was this, That theſe Matters did not, and could not lye in Vulgar Heads, with that Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction; his Defence of that Reply, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently of his confuſed and deceitful way of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſenting, is wholly Dropt.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The Defence of his Arguments, That the <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing Power</hi> is no Article of Faith; is now at laſt wholly Dropt.</p>
               <p n="3">3. His Defence of the <hi>Worſhip of Images,</hi> againſt his Adverſary's Diſcourſe, is Dropt; or to uſe his own Words, her <hi>took the Freedom grave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to turn over his Anſwerers Occaſional Pages a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout it.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">P. 39.</note>
               </p>
               <p>And now if the Reader will pleaſe to put all together, he will find by an eaſie Computation, That this was the poor Remainder of a Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie begun by the <hi>Repreſenter</hi> upon no leſs than Thirty Seven Articles: So that theſe Points having had the hard Fate to be ſerved by the <hi>Repreſenter</hi> as their Fellows were before, I reckon that he has Dropt and Dropt, till the whole Cauſe is Dropt at laſt; but this is one of thoſe Things in which he is <hi>not concerned;</hi> for though the <hi>Papiſt Miſrepre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented and Repreſented,</hi> be in a very forſaken Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, yet himſelf, the <hi>Repreſenter,</hi> was never more diverting, nor in better Humour all his Life: And who can blame a Man for not being ſorry for what can ne're be helpt? And therefore ſince he ſped no better with his Grave Undertaking, it was not amiſs
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:60861:20"/>to call a merry Cauſe, upon <hi>Miſrepreſenting in a ſtrict and proper Sence,</hi> and to bring in a <hi>Phanatick</hi> Repreſenting the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England</hi> in a Ridiculous Sermon.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="answer">
               <head>
                  <hi>The Fourth Anſwer to the</hi> Repreſenter, <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> An Anſwer to the Amicable Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodation.</head>
               <p>THE <hi>Anſwerer</hi> has no Reaſon to be diſpleaſed, that the <hi>Repreſenter</hi> now grants we do not <hi>Miſrepreſent</hi> the Papiſts in <hi>a ſtrict and proper ſenſe,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">P. 4.</note> viz. by Imputing ſuch Doctrines to them as they do not own. But he ſaies that the Deſign of the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſenter</hi> in his Firſt Book, was to perſwade our people that we were ſuch Miſrepreſenters; but that failing in the performance, he would now make good his Title of Miſrepreſenting in a <hi>leſs proper ſenſe,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">P. 6.</note> inaſmuch as he thinks we do unjuſtly condemn the Doctrines and Practices of the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> But why he ſhould tax us for this at all, the <hi>Anſwerer</hi> wonders, and that very juſtly, one would think, becauſe the <hi>Repreſenter</hi> has ſometime ſince diſclaim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Diſputing, without which it cannot be ſeen whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther we be Miſrepreſenters or not in this <hi>leſs, proper ſenſe:</hi> And therefore he tells him, That if he will vindicate the Doctrines and Practices of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> he muſt <hi>quit his retreat of Character-ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">P. 8.</note> and fall to <hi>Diſputing</hi> as their Fathers did; in which, he is ready to joyn iſſue with them: But that
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:60861:21"/>it was by no means civil to charge us with <hi>Lying,</hi> how prudent ſoever it might be upon another ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, ſince if he proceeds, in this way, he may be ſecure, that no civil perſon will care to diſpute with him. Now whereas the <hi>Repreſenter</hi> did in effect recall his grant, by attempting to prove largely, That there may be a Miſrepreſentation where there is an Agreement about the matter of Fact; becauſe there may be Miſpreſentation upon other accounts, <hi>viz.</hi> in reſpect of <hi>Motive, Circumſtance, Intention, End,</hi> &amp;c. Here the <hi>Anſwerer</hi> ſhews that theſe things do indeed belong to true Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſenting; but that they were too nicely di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſhed by the <hi>Repreſenter</hi> from matter of Fact; for he had given him no occaſion for the Diſtinction, ſince he had conſidered theſe things in thoſe matters which he charged upon the Church of <hi>Rome;</hi> For Inſtance, That not only Worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping of Images, but the Worſhippers <hi>Intentions,</hi> and all other circumſtances, without which the Nature of the Fact cannot be throughly under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, were taken into conſideration. Then he ſhews through all the <hi>Repreſenter</hi>'s Inſtances, That Miſrepreſentations were in Matters of Fact;<note place="margin">P. 12.</note> but wonders why he did not produce one In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of the like nature out of his Anſwers, if he thought there were any. For what could he gain by ſhewing, That in ſuch and ſuch caſes others have been Miſrepreſenters, unless, he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved withal, that we were Miſrepreſenters in like caſes? His inſtances ſhew, that they who tell a piece of a Story, may Miſrepreſent; but not that they do ſo, who faithfully relate the whole matter of Fact,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:60861:21"/>with all its circumſtances; which is our caſe; and he has not produced one example to the contrary; tho ſo to have done, had been more to his purpoſe, than all his other Inſtances. In ſhort, this matter was ſo fully Anſwered, that when we hear next of the <hi>Repreſenter,</hi> we do not find one word more about it.</p>
               <p>To the <hi>Zealous Brothers</hi> Harangue, he ſaies, tho it be granted that the Diſſenters Miſrepreſent our Church, yet this does not prove that we Miſrepre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent the Church of <hi>Rome;</hi> and therefore this is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but a device to get rid of us,<note place="margin">P. 15.</note> by throwing us upon the Diſſenters. But <hi>we are not for purſuing eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry New Game,<note place="margin">P. 16.</note> but will keep to our old ſcent.</hi> And yet he has made the Diſſenter ſay ſuch ſilly things of us, as no Diſſenter will own, unleſs he has heard them among the Quakers. This the <hi>Anſwerer</hi> plainly ſhewed through, almoſt all his Fifteen particulars of the Charge againſt the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and by the way, where it was any thing needful, he taxed the unreaſonableneſs and folly of the Charge, which yet was more than he was bound to, ſince if it came to the Trial, we have ſome reaſon to think that there is not a zealous <hi>Brother</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> no nor <hi>Friend</hi> neither, but would be aſhamed to own it. So that this deſign of <hi>Repreſenting</hi> and <hi>Miſrepreſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> to which I may add the <hi>Repreſenter</hi>'s yielding in pure good Nature, that henceforth <hi>Miſrepreſenting</hi> ſhall be underſtood in its <hi>leſs proper ſenſe, ends only in Ridiculing the Church of</hi> England, with which we are content, if they will permit us truly to Repreſent theirs.</p>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:60861:22"/>
               <p>To what the <hi>Repreſenter</hi> offered, for ſeeking out new Miſrepreſentations, the ſum of what is Anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, is this, That it is in the main agreed what the matters of Fact are with which the Papiſts may be charged; and ſince theſe only are the proper Subject of Repreſentation, the ill conſequences which Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants have urged againſt their Doctrines and Practices, ought not to have been put into the <hi>Character of a Papiſt Miſrepreſented,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">P. 24.</note> unleſs he could ſhew, that we ſay that Papiſts do believe thoſe Conſequences: And therefore the <hi>Repreſenter</hi> vain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly endeavours to excuſe himſelf for putting them into that Character, by hunting about for new pretended Miſrepreſentations, to imploy his <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerer</hi> withal. This I gather to be the <hi>Anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er</hi>'s ſenſe, from his reference to what he had pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved before.</p>
               <p>As to the Archbiſhop of <hi>York;</hi> the Anſwerer ſaies, he did not Miſrepreſent the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> in ſaying that <hi>Stapleton</hi> ſaid,<note place="margin">P. 25.</note> 
                  <hi>We muſt ſimply be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve the Church of</hi> Rome <hi>whether it Teach True or Falſe.</hi> The moſt that can be made of it, is, That according to one of their allowed Doctors, Thus a Papiſt muſt believe. And therefore if it be a Miſrepreſentation of the Doctrine of the Church of <hi>Rome, Stapleton</hi> is to be thanked for it in the firſt place, for ſaying ſo; and in the next, the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> for allowing him to ſay ſo; and then the Arch-Biſhop for reporting what he ſaid, tho he does not ſay that one Doctor may make Doctrines for the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:60861:22"/>
               <p>The Caſe of Mr. <hi>Sutcliff,</hi> he ſays, is different; and he ſhews that he <hi>expreſly diſtinguiſhes between what the Papiſts teach,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>P.</hi> 26, 27.</note> and what himſelf concludes from ſuch Doctrines; and therefore that he does not Miſrepre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent the Papiſts.</hi> So that how little ſoever the Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenter thought himſelf concerned in <hi>Sutcliff</hi>'s Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonings, becauſe Reaſoning belonged not to a Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenter; yet ſurely it belonged to a Repreſenter to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſh beween the Doctrines we charge upon the Papiſts on the one ſide, and the Arguments we bring againſt theſe Doctrines on the other.</p>
               <p>To the Charge of omitting to render <hi>propter De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um</hi> into Engliſh; He ſays, It was omitted he knows not how or why; but very jus;tly blames the Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenter for inſinuating that it was diſhoneſtly omitted, ſince it was the <hi>whole Deſign of that Diſcourſe about the Worſhip of Images,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>P.</hi> 28.</note> to ſhew that <hi>Image Worſhip</hi> is Evil, tho <hi>God</hi> was worſhipped by it. I will upon this occaſion add, that the Anſwerer could not but know his own foul Dealing in this Charge, which is ſo very manifeſt; that this Injuſtice, if there were nothing elſe, does aſſure me, that he muſt make a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother <hi>Change,</hi> before we can expect much ſincerity from him.</p>
               <p>With like honeſty, he diſingages himſelf from all Obligation to diſpute concerning the <hi>Worſhip of I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages,</hi> &amp;c. 1. Becauſe the Anſwerer <hi>knows no Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon for all this Diſpute;</hi> which words did not at all relate to that Diſpute, but to the Queſtion about the Biſhop of <hi>Condom</hi>'s Authority. 2. He <hi>was never concerned whether the Anſwerer liked his Religion or not.</hi> But if he could have anſwer'd that Diſcourſe, <hi>all that the Anſwerer could have ſaid would not have hindred him.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">P. 29.</note>
               </p>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:60861:23"/>
               <p>For the Reſt; the Anſwerer ſays, that the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſenter</hi> and the Biſhop of <hi>Condom, reaſon'd</hi> and <hi>ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gued</hi> at firſt, as well as <hi>Repreſented;</hi> and ſince their Repreſentation is offer'd as a Rule by which we may be taken into the <hi>Roman</hi> Church, they were the more concern'd to <hi>juſtify their own Reaſonings;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">P. 30.</note> which ſince it is declined, our People will be apt to <hi>think why Papiſts decline the Diſpute, who are never known to avoid Diſputing, when they think they can get any thing by it. And thus</hi> the Anſwerer <hi>takes leave of the Repreſenter,</hi> believing that <hi>this Matter is driven as far as it will go.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="reply">
               <head>The Fourth Reply of the Repreſenter, in behalf of his Amicable Accomodation.</head>
               <p>THis laſt Reply is made up;</p>
               <p n="1">1. Of inſulting over the Anſwerer, for offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing no more than he did in Anſwer to the Zealous Brother's Sermon againſt the Church of <hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. Of more and more out-cries upon the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants for Miſrepreſenting the Papiſts.</p>
               <p>But the Particulars that come under theſe Heads, together with his Reflections by the bye, will be beſt produced in the following Anſwer, where I ſhall conſider what Reaſon he has for this kind of proceeding.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="answer">
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:60861:23"/>
               <head>The Fifth Anſwer to the Repreſenter in Return to his laſt Reply.</head>
               <p>IF the <hi>Seven and Thirty</hi> loſt Points had been reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered, the Repreſenter could not have entered the Liſts with more ſeeming ſatisfaction, in himſelf, than he ſhews in his laſt Reply. But he has made a ſhift to forget them, and that's as good. What the Anſwerer ſaid, that <hi>the Matter was driven as far as it would go</hi> (whatever the Repreſenter imagines) I find ſtill to be true. For with reference to the chief mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Diſpute betwixt us, we are parted; and, I think, never like to meet any more about it. Indeed as to the <hi>manifold Charge ſun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ed up againſt the Church of England, that matter,</hi> as he truly obſerves, <hi>is not driven as far as it will go:</hi> And it ſeems he intends to <hi>drive</hi> it farther and farther. But why that ſhould ever come to be a matter of Debate betwixt us, any one who conſiders the Controverſy from firſt to laſt, muſt needs wonder.</p>
               <p>The Deſign of what has been ſaid on behalf of the Church of <hi>England</hi> has been to make evident theſe three Things.</p>
               <p n="1">1. That we do not charge the Papiſts with ſome things which the Repreſenter will have us to charge them with.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That ſome things which he faith we falſly charge them with, are maintained and practiſed by them.</p>
               <p n="3">3. That allowing them to maintain and practiſe only, what themſelves acknowledg that they do maintain and practiſe, yet there are ſufficient Reaſons
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:60861:24"/>why we cannot comply with Popery, altho refined after the neweſt Faſhion.</p>
               <p>This is the ſum of what has been argued on our ſide. Now how comes his <hi>Zealous Brother's</hi> Cant to be an Anſwer to all this? I know not I muſt confeſs how to imagine any Diſſenter to be ſo ridiculous as to object againſt us, what the Repreſenter makes him to Object: And without <hi>Flattery</hi> or <hi>Fawning,</hi> I may ſafely affirm that there are not many who do it. But ſuppoſe there ſhould; will ſuch their Objections prove againſt the Firſt particular above mentioned, that <hi>we charge Papiſts with what we deny we charge them with?</hi> Or againſt the Third, That <hi>allowing them to maintain and practiſe, what themſelves acknowledg that they maintain and practiſe, we ought to comply with Pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry.</hi> I think that no Man in his Wits will aſſert this. And therefore we may juſtly ask what is to be done with all that has been ſaid upon theſe particulars? and whether there not having been any ting that is material urged againſt them, does not imply that there is nothing material to be urged; and conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, if the Anſwerer had not ſome Reaſon to ſay, that <hi>the matter was driven as far as it will go?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As to the ſecond particular, <hi>viz.</hi> that ſeveral things which we are ſaid falſly to charge them, with are maintained and defended by them; This indeed the Character which he made, <hi>little more than in Jeſt,</hi> for his Zealous Brother, doth ſeem more directly to oppoſe. And yet it might be eaſily anſwered, that this <hi>Brother</hi> in his Zeal might urge what was <hi>Falſe</hi> againſt <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s,</hi> tho we urged nothing but what was <hi>True</hi> againſt the <hi>Papiſts.</hi> Which with a great deal more the <hi>Anſwerer</hi> offered to the conſideration of the <hi>Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenter;</hi> and he is now told that he <hi>pſſed over</hi> this ſame
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:60861:24"/>charge upon the Church of <hi>England,</hi> with <hi>a Light Touch, &amp;c.</hi> And much adoe there is, becauſe he was <hi>not for purſuing every new Game, but for keeping to the old Scent.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">P. 3, 4.</note> For what could poſſibly come more croſs to the <hi>Repreſenter,</hi> than that after all his Doubling and Shifting, he ſhould ſtart <hi>new Game</hi> for us, and yet we ſhould be for <hi>keeping to the old Scent?</hi> And therefore I do not wonder to hear him complaining in this manner. <hi>And is it poſſible then that the Diſputing humour is ſo ſoon off? We have heard of nothing hitherto ſo much as of Diſputes — and yet the Anſwerer is as unwilling to Diſpute as the Repreſenter — Here's not a word now of Diſputing — And is it not ſtrange that be ſhould draw me out to Diſpute — and when his own Turn comes of Diſputing he ſhould let the matter Fall, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe, forſooth, he'll keep to his old Scent?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now really this would almoſt perſwade a Man to let him go for good and all; as he might have done if he had obſerved but a little moderation. But he gives it out, that in his <hi>Brother</hi>'s Character of the Church of <hi>England, Almoſt every Point urged with the ſame Proofs of Scripture and Reaſon, which Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants produce againſt the Papiſts: That there is ſcarce an Argument in the Character, but is exactly parallel to what the Church of</hi> England <hi>uſes in her Defenſe againſt Popery; that the Grounds of the Arguments are the ſame, the manner of urging them the ſame, the Max<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ims on which they ſtand the ſame, and then the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons which preſs them home, are they not the very ſame which the Anſwerer himſelf in his former Diſcourſe urges againſt him?</hi> And he turns it upon his An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerer, That <hi>a little prudence would ſerve him to ſay nothing in ſuch a Cauſe as will admit no better a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence.</hi> This I muſt needs ſay, is a little too tyranni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:60861:25"/>in a Repreſenter under his Circumſtances; and would tempt a Man againſt his own Inclinations to follow him a little farther now, under his new Shape.</p>
               <p>I tell him therefore, in the firſt place, that a cloſe Diſputant would have preſſed him to ſhew, that the Reaſons upon which we proceed in our manifold Charge againſt the Papiſts are falſe and unſatisfacto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry; and not have ſuffered him to run out into an Inquiry, whether the Reaſons upon which his <hi>Zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Brother</hi> proceeds againſt us, be the ſame with them, or no. Or, if this were to be allowed him, we might be well excuſed from anſwering him in this matter; ſince the particular Controverſies which the Church of <hi>England</hi> hath with the Diſſenters, have been managed on her behalf, not ſo long ſince that it ſhould be forgotten; and the <hi>difference of the Caſe</hi> between the Separation of Proteſtants from the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and of Diſſenters from the Church of <hi>England,</hi> was ſhewn after all, and that <hi>in very good earneſt.</hi> For this being not taken notice of by Repreſenter, it might very well ſet off our Debt to him for a <hi>Charge</hi> upon the Church of <hi>England,</hi> which himſelf meant <hi>little more than in jeſt.</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, altho he glories in this Charge more than in all his other Performances, yet ſince he frequently inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mates that he intended no more by it, than to <hi>Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicule</hi> our Charge againſt the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> 'tis all one, as if he had given it under his hand, that his Cauſe is more ſafe by <hi>ridiculing</hi> what we ſay, than bye <hi>replying</hi> to it like a Diſputant. Now on the other hand, we think our Charge muſt needs have been carefully laid, and well defended, if at laſt it wlll ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit of none but <hi>Ridiculing Replies:</hi> And ſo we might
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:60861:25"/>without much danger, leave things as they are, and put it to the venture, whether the World will not think ſo too. But becauſe he boaſts ſo very much, that this Diſcourſe which he has compoſed for the <hi>Brother,</hi> is not yet ſufficiently anſwered, and as ſome think, he may grow a little popular by it; I care not if I go on with him in ſome part of his own way; and, in compliance with the Opinion of others, inquire into the difference of thoſe Objections upon which we proceed againſt the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> from thoſe upon which <hi>his zealous Brother</hi> proceeds againſt the Church of <hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. I grant that <hi>our Prelates</hi> have <hi>Revenues,</hi> and I believe <hi>Coaches, Miters, Croſiers</hi> and <hi>Copes.</hi> Now if there be any reaſon why his <hi>Brother</hi> calls theſe: <hi>Popiſh,</hi> 'tis this, that theſe things were not in uſe in <hi>our Saviour's, and in the Apoſtles times.</hi> But when did we ever object againſt any thing that is meerly <hi>circumſtantial</hi> amongſt them (as theſe things are) that it was not uſed in our Saviour's, or in his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles Times? Have we not ſaid it a thouſand times, that we like nothing the worſe becauſe the Papiſts, approve it, provided it be uſeful; nay, if it be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent and harmleſs? As for their <hi>Ornaments</hi> and <hi>Ceremonies,</hi> where does any one find that in the Controverſies now on foot betwixt us, we do at all inſiſt upon them? Tho we cannot but think many of them to be neither grave nor decent, their Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber too great, and too much Religion placed in them by ſome People. So that, tho <hi>there is ſcarce an Argument in the Character, but exactly parallel to what we uſe,</hi> and tho <hi>ALMOST EVERT Point is urged with the ſame Proofs,</hi> &amp;c. yet ſurely the Firſt <hi>Point</hi> is none of them. And therefore let's try the next.</p>
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:60861:26"/>
               <p n="2">2. It is objected againſt us, that <hi>we make Gods of dead Men,</hi> and this is proved by the <hi>weekly Bills of Mortality,</hi> where our Churches are called by the ſame <hi>Titles</hi> that they had in times of Popery. Now if by, <hi>making Gods of dead Men,</hi> be meant making the Saints ſo many, Independent Deities, there is then a great deal of difference between what the <hi>Zealous Brother</hi> objects againſt us, and what <hi>We</hi> object a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Papiſts, as well as between the Reaſons of our Objections: For we never object this againſt them. But if by this Expreſſion be meant, giving that Worſhip to the Saints, which belongs only to God and our Saviour; we then allow our Objection to be the ſame, but do think that we have much bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Reaſons to object this againſt the Papiſt, than that of a <hi>weekly Bill of Mortality.</hi> For we appeal to the <hi>Publick Addreſſes</hi> which are made to Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> and other Saints, with all the Circumſtances of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Adoration; to their <hi>Litanies</hi> and to the <hi>Hymns</hi> of their eſtabliſh'd Offices, wherein they are often in voked after the ſame manner, as God himſelf is; to their appropriating to particular Saints, diſtinct Powers of doing good to their Worſhippers; to their Acknowledgment, that the Saints are Mediators of Interceſſion; to the Prayers that are made to them in all places, as if they were omnipreſent; to the Senſe alſo of their Council of <hi>Trent,</hi> that they are to be prayed unto with <hi>mental</hi> as well as <hi>vocal</hi> Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, as if they knew our Hearts. All which I hope is ſomething more than that in the <hi>weekly Bill of Mortality,</hi> and in common Converſation, we call our Temples by the ſame Names they formerly had. And yet the Repreſenter asks, <hi>Wherein have I Ridiculed the Church of</hi> England? <hi>I have done no more in my
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:60861:26"/>Character againſt her, then what they have been doing theſe hundred and fifty Years againſt the Church of</hi> Rome? ſo that it ſeems we have for <hi>theſe hundred and fifty Years</hi> charged them with <hi>Worſhipping</hi> the Saints upon no better grounds then their <hi>weekly Bills of Mortality. Only,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>what I have done in a kind of jeſt, and without endeavouring to delude any body with ſuch kind of Sophiſtry, they have been do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the greateſt earneſt, and by it making good their Cauſe.</hi> So that he confeſſes his Charge upon our Church to be carried on with a <hi>kind of Sophiſtry:</hi> only what he has done <hi>in a kind of jeſt,</hi> we have been doing againſt them <hi>in the greateſt earneſt;</hi> i. e. we have in <hi>good earneſt</hi> charged the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> with giving that Worſhip to Saints which belongs to God only, upon nothing elſe but the <hi>Titles</hi> of Churches, ſuch as ours have in the <hi>Bills of Mortality.</hi> But ſurely his greateſt <hi>Sophiſtry</hi> of all lies in this, that he <hi>endeavours to delude</hi> People into this Opinion, which yet if he could, he muſt delude them into another Opinion too, that <hi>Bellarmin</hi> and all the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Champions of old Popery, were a company of Fools, to be at ſo much <hi>Sweat</hi> and <hi>Charges</hi> to maintain the <hi>Worſhip of Saints,</hi> and to defend it, as they have done, when they could ſo eaſily have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied it. For that nothing is eaſier than to make good our diſowning it againſt the ground upon which he charges us with it, I ſhall preſently make appear.</p>
               <p>To let paſs his Suggeſtion, that the <hi>London Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches were firſt built by the Papiſts;</hi> his adding that we <hi>rebuilt them, with the ſame Titles, Invocations and Dedications which they uſe,</hi> ſhews how little he is to be truſted in a Queſtion of Antiquity, who talks ſo careleſly of things that are notorious in our own
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:60861:27"/>Days. Our Fathers indeed found the <hi>Titles</hi> conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient enough, and the <hi>Churches</hi> themſelves reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble good Churches, and retain'd them both. But when we <hi>raiſed them out of their Aſhes,</hi> we <hi>dedicated</hi> them to no Saint, whatever has been done in this kind formerly; nor have we ſince <hi>invocated</hi> any Saint in any one of them, but we keep the <hi>Titles</hi> ſtill. And does our new Repreſenter expect that we ſhould Anſwer ſuch Objections as theſe? At leaſt I deſire him not to think that we will make a practice of it. Muſt our retaining theſe Titles, neceſſarily infer a virtual Dedication of our Temples to thoſe Saints, by whoſe Names they are diſtinguiſhed from one another? But what if we had called them by the Names of thoſe <hi>Streets</hi> only where they ſtand, had they then been <hi>dedicated to the Honour</hi> of the Streets? We ſay that the <hi>Hundred Thirty and Two</hi> Churches here, which are known by the Names <hi>dead Men and Women,</hi> are with us <hi>God's Houſes,</hi> and dedicated to his only Service, no leſs than the <hi>Five</hi> that are diſtinguiſhed by the Names of <hi>Chriſt</hi> and the <hi>Trinity.</hi> And me thinks ſo acute a Diſputant as he is grown, might have ſeen that the Title of one Church diſtinguiſhing it from the reſt, does not ſhew who is ſerved and worſhipped there, when the ſame Service and Worſhip is uſed in all of them. That which we blame them for is, that they conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue to worſhip <hi>Dead Men and Women</hi> in thoſe Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches which bear their Names, and in thoſe which do not. For if in <hi>Chriſt's Church</hi> they call upon the Bleſſed Virgin; tho the Church has its <hi>Title</hi> from <hi>Christ,</hi> yet 'tis a <hi>Houſe of Prayer</hi> to Her as well as to Him. And if in the Churches which are known by her Name, we call upon <hi>God only,</hi> and worſhip him
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:60861:27"/>
                  <hi>alone,</hi> they are his <hi>Houſes</hi> intirely, and none of Hers. But after all, where does the Anſwerer preſs him with the <hi>Titles</hi> of their Churches? And yet the Reaſons which preſs home the Arguments, are they not the very ſame which the Anſwerer himſelf urges againſt him the Repreſenter?</p>
               <p n="3">3. I confeſs that I have ſeen <hi>Pictures</hi> in ſome <hi>Engliſh Bibles</hi> and <hi>Common-prayer Books,</hi> and <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron</hi> painted on <hi>each ſide of the Commandments</hi> upon ſome of our Altar pieces; which things how they have crept in amongſt us I cannot tell, for they have no publick Authority from our Church. The Anſwerer made his gueſs, and perhaps it will not be eaſy to mend it. But upon this great Occaſion, the Repreſenter has brought in his <hi>Rigid</hi> Brother making us worſe than the Papiſts themſelves, forgetting that he undertook to repreſent us not altogether ſo Bad, and therefore he ſhould at leaſt have corrected him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in this manner; <q>Indeed, Beloved, I told ye at firſt, that theſe <hi>Church-of-England</hi>-Men are with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the <hi>Swing of the Dragon's Tail;</hi> but I had not lied to ſay that they are under the <hi>Feet</hi> and the <hi>Belly,</hi> more than the <hi>Papiſts</hi> themſelves are. For the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts do no more towards the <hi>placing of Image</hi>-Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip in the <hi>Word of God,</hi> than by a cleanly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veyance of that Commandment which forbids it, out of the way. But theſe Church-of-<hi>England</hi>-Men, <hi>as they are called, have given that Abomination of Images themſelves, a place in every Leaf of their Bible, in the very Word of God; which is the greateſt Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument of Soveraign Honour.</hi> Nay, in ſome of their Bibles you ſhall find <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron</hi> ſtand in the very next Leaf to the <hi>Ten Commandments;</hi>
                     <pb n="52" facs="tcp:60861:28"/>which what is it, Beloved, but a <hi>Defiance</hi> to the <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond?</hi> Whereas the Papiſts being more modeſt than to affront it, have put it away far from them. <hi>But this is not all, my Brethren, for they pray to their Pictures; for if you but look over their Shoulders, you'l ſee their Pictures in the very heat of their De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion, under their very Eyes, in the Leaves of their Common-Prayer Books; And therefore, mark me now Beloved, if we muſt believe our own Senſes, they pray to the Pictures,</hi> and to the Leaves, and to the Idol Common-Prayer Books and all.</q>
               </p>
               <p>This indeed had been ſomething like, and would have pieced well with what follows, that our <hi>Altars have their Images too, and that in a more profane way than the Papiſts,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Well; but let us ſuppoſe our Church bound to anſwer for theſe <hi>Pictures;</hi> and for <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron,</hi> &amp;c. Are we enjoyned to pay them any Worſhip, as they of the Romiſh Communion are obliged to pay to their Images? The Council of <hi>Trent</hi> has determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, <hi>That due Honour and Veneration muſt be given to Images, and that the Honour which is given to them is referred to the Things which they repreſent.</hi> Has the Church of <hi>England</hi> done any thing like this? We read of ſeveral Prayers uſed at the <hi>Conſecration</hi> of Images amongſt them: But whoever heard of any ſuch thing practiſed at the ſetting up of <hi>Moſes;</hi> and <hi>Aaron?</hi> We know that they walk many Miles in Pilgrimage to particular Images, and that they think much more good is to be expected from ſome, than from others: But who ever thought ſo among us, or imagined that the Pictures of <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron</hi> in <hi>Cornhill,</hi> were more to be honoured than thoſe in
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:60861:28"/>
                  <hi>Woodſtreet,</hi> or in any other place? So that how ſilly ſoever the <hi>Zealous Brother</hi> may appear to be in impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to us, upon ſuch frivolous grounds, the worſhip of Images; I am ſure that he who made the Harangue for him, is either much more ſo, or ſomething that is worſe, in pretending that when we urge the ſame againſt the Papiſts, the Reaſons we go upon are no better than his.</p>
               <p>But we do at leaſt <hi>make Images</hi> and <hi>Pictures,</hi> which the <hi>ſecond Commandment expreſly forbids,</hi> as he makes his Brother ſay. And now a Reaſon of the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerer is produced, that <hi>no Intention can alter the nature of Actions which are determined by a Divine Law.</hi> I would therefore know of him, whether there be, or be not good reaſon to make us certain, that the ſecond Commandment does not abſolutely forbid the making of Images and Pictures, but only with reference to worſhipping them. If there be no good Reaſon for it, let him then tell me, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther any Intention can juſtify the making of Images againſt an abſolute Law to the contrary. If there be, let him then but confeſs what he thinks of this Objection that he has put into his Brother's Mouth; and there's one labour ſaved.</p>
               <p>I confeſs, it were not ill for him if ſome <hi>Intention</hi> might juſtify the breaking of the ninth Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; for he pretends that the <hi>New</hi> Common-Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er-Books do not <hi>profeſs that hatred</hi> to <hi>Image-Worſhip,</hi> which the <hi>Old</hi> ones did: When in the <hi>Commination</hi> to which he refers, the very firſt inſtance runs thus; <hi>Curſed is the Man that maketh any carved or molten Image to worſhip it.</hi> Does he think that his <hi>Diſſenting Brother</hi> muſt anſwer for theſe things.</p>
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:60861:29"/>
               <p n="4">4. Neither is he more Juſt to us in making his <hi>Zealous Brother</hi> to object againſt us that we <hi>worſhip Saints and Angels.</hi> For, to paſs by the Argument about <hi>erecting Temples to them,</hi> to which we have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready ſpoken; Is our giving Thanks to God upon <hi>ſet Days</hi> for ſuch eminent Examples of Faith and Vertue, as the firſt Propagators of the Goſpel were? Is our commemorating their Patience, and all their other Divine Graces, to excite one another to the Imitation of them? Is our Praying to God that we may be Followers of them, who through Faith and Patience inherit the Promiſes? Is this, I ſay, any thing like to what the Council of <hi>Trent</hi> declares, That <hi>they think wickedly who deny that Saints are to be Invoked?</hi> Is it of the ſame nature with owning them to be <hi>Mediators of Interceſſion,</hi> the ſame with putting up them that ſort of Petitions which are fit to be offered to God only? Or does our Praying upon St. <hi>Michael</hi>'s Day, that by <hi>God's ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment his holy Angels may ſuccour and defend us,</hi> come near even ſo much as to one ſingle <hi>Holy Michael Pray for us?</hi> which Form of Words, tho much inferiour to what is ſometimes uſed in the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> we never dare to venture upon, becauſe we cannot make Addreſſes either to him, or to any other Angel or Saint, but by interpretation we muſt aſcribe the Divine Attribute of Omnipreſence to them, and for many other Reaſons, which yet we have not been able to get an Anſwer to from theſe Men. But he ſays that we <hi>Pray</hi> on St. <hi>Michael</hi>'s Day, <hi>as if God were not able to defend us, and therefore we ſeek ſhelter under the Angel's Wings:</hi> And this ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly is to <hi>worſhip Angels.</hi> By like reaſon if we pray
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:60861:29"/>for our <hi>Daily Bread,</hi> we pray as if God were not able to preſerve us without it: And this would be to worſhip Bread. The Repreſenter makes too bold with his <hi>Zealous Brother,</hi> and with us too, if he would have it thought that we reaſon againſt them at this rate. But by this time I hope he ſees to how little purpoſe he applies that of the Anſwerer to this matter, <hi>viz.</hi> that <hi>All worſhip of Inviſible Beings is Religious Worſhip, &amp;c.</hi> For as yet he has not proved that we <hi>worſhip</hi> Saints or Angels; and if he has done his beſt towards it here. I will be bold to ſay, that he knows he cannot prove it againſt us; as we can a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them, if there were any need of it: But there is no need of it, becauſe they confeſs it.</p>
               <p n="5">5. As for what is objected about our <hi>Idolatry in Receiving the Sacrament;</hi> if I did not know the Prompter, I ſhould be aſhamed to find it amongſt ſuch Inſtances as are ſaid to be <hi>built upon the ſame Maxims,</hi> that our Objections againſt the Papiſts are. For how far ſoever <hi>We</hi> and the <hi>Zealous Brother</hi> might in other caſes be ſaid to agree in the Reaſons of what we Object; I am ſure it is moſt unreaſonable to ſay we agree in this. For do we, as the Papiſts, hold that the Bread and Wine are changed into the natural Body and Blood of Chriſt? Do we require any wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip to be paid to the Elements after Conſecration? Do we elevate or carry them about, on purpoſe to have them adored by the People? Nay, with refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to our receiving the ſame in the poſture of <hi>Kneeling,</hi> is it not as fully as can be declared, <hi>That what poſture is meant for a ſignification of our humble and grateful acknowledgment of the benefits of Chriſt to all worthy Receivers; That no Adoration is hereby in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:60861:30"/>for that the Sacramental Bread and Wine re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main ſtill in their very natural Subſtances, and the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Body and Blood of our Saviour are in Heaven and not here?</hi> Which Declaration is the more ſignificant, one would think, as being made by our Church in Oppoſition to thoſe who <hi>do Adore</hi> the Sacrament: Eſpecially ſince it was not the poſture of <hi>Kneeling</hi> when the <hi>Sacrament</hi> is received, which of it ſelf could make ſuch a Declaration needful, but the Scandal which they give to the World who Adore it. Had this been conſidered by the Repreſenter, his Brothers <hi>Zeal</hi> might well have been ſpared in ſaying, <hi>They may ſay, they do not pay Religious Worſhip to the Bread and Wine, and Honour the Sacrament as God: But what, muſt we not believe our ſenſes in ſo plain a Caſe?</hi> Or elſe his Zeal ſhould not have ſtopt here, but carried him a little farther, to appeal to his <hi>own Eyes</hi> that we honour the <hi>Patin</hi> and <hi>Chalice</hi> as Gods too, by <hi>falling down to them on our Knees,</hi> for this is as <hi>plain a Caſe</hi> as the other; and our Church has made no <hi>Declaration</hi> againſt it in ſolemn and particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Terms neither, as it has againſt the <hi>Adoration</hi> of the <hi>Bread</hi> and the <hi>Wine.</hi> But I gueſs that the <hi>Zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Brother</hi> when he is once at liberty to ſpeak for himſelf, will confeſs that he <hi>ſees</hi> neither the one nor the other; and that it is no affront to his <hi>Eyes</hi> to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quit us of Adoring the Sacrament, and to yield that when we receive it, we Adore God and him only, in a poſture which as we think, well becomes the thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Receivers of ſuch Holy Myſteries.</p>
               <p>However, tho we, it ſeems, muſt not be believed when we ſay that <hi>we do not adore</hi> the Sacrament at all; yet we will not be ſo hard to the Church of
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:60861:30"/>
                  <hi>Rome,</hi> but believe her telling us that ſhe <hi>does Adore</hi> the Sacrament, and that <hi>with Divine Honour too.</hi> And when the <hi>Zealous Brother</hi> gets our Church at any Advantage like this, or can find out any practices amongſt us like thoſe above mentioned, we ſhall hear him, I doubt not, ſpeaking to better purpoſe for himſelf, than as his <hi>Brother</hi> here has taught him.</p>
               <p>And now, I think, I have omitted nothing in the firſt <hi>Five</hi> of the <hi>Fifteen Parallels,</hi> that required the leaſt notice, but have rather ventured being laugh'd at by the Repreſenter for giving any ſerious Anſwers, where he meant only to <hi>Ridicule.</hi> But by this he may ſee what little reaſon there was to Crow over his Adverſary as he does upon this occaſion; which was all that I intended. And therefore ſince it is needleſs to <hi>drive</hi> the <hi>Parallel</hi> any farther with that circumſtance which I have hitherto uſed; I muſt not do a needleſs thing, which according to one of his weighty Obſervations, <hi>would be Six-pence a piece more for the Curious:</hi> Eſpecially ſince the Anſwerer has done Reaſon enough to the remaining Particulars. For tho the Repreſenter, to ſave himſelf from any further Reply, comes off with telling him that he anſwered the whole charge with, <hi>The Diſſenters ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver charged us with this or that, &amp;c.</hi> and nothing elſe; yet the Reader will find more ſaid than this comes to, if he will conſult the Anſwer it ſelf, inſtead of taking the Repreſenters word. But I hope <hi>Five</hi> of his Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars have been handled his own way: And now I offer him this, either in full Satisfaction, or in part of Payment; let him chuſe, as he likes, 'tis all one to his Humble Servant. And therefore if he will pleaſe to call upon me for Arrears, I promiſe him
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:60861:31"/>that our <hi>calling upon the Birds, the Beaſts, and the Fiſhes,</hi> ſhall not be forgotten, nor <hi>our crying out to Dead Men, in our moſt ſolemn Devotion,</hi> nor the <hi>Apochrypha</hi> in the <hi>Liturgy,</hi> nor the <hi>Rochet,</hi> the <hi>Alb,</hi> and the <hi>Tunicle,</hi> nor any thing elſe which yet wants a <hi>Vindication,</hi> as he ſays: But, to return him one of his familiar Phraſes, I ſhall <hi>take occaſion of playing him the ſame Tune over again as diſtinctly</hi> upon the remaining <hi>Ten,</hi> as he has had it already upon his firſt <hi>Five</hi> Parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars.</p>
               <p>And now let us go on with his Reply; in which the next thing I obſerve, is, that he will needs have the Anſwerer to <hi>bid fair for the good opinion</hi> of Diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters and <hi>to curry cloſely with the</hi> Diſſenters, and to <hi>throw thoſe ſcandals upon his own Church in good earneſt,<note place="margin">Pag. 5.</note> which the Repreſenter did little more than in jeſt.</hi> If the Repreſenter could have turned his Adverſaries Pen againſt the <hi>Diſſenters,</hi> there are ſome would have had a better opportunity of <hi>currying cloſely with the Diſſenters;</hi> and I ſhall tell him who they are, before I have done with him. But, it ſeems, we are not for doing every good thing, in the very nick when he would have it done. And ſo to be revenged on us, we muſt be repreſented as <hi>currying with the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenters;</hi> which yet we are as far from, when we own our Agreement with them in thoſe many things, which they no leſs than we, object againſt the Papiſts; as from <hi>currying with the Papiſts,</hi> when we confeſs that we agree with them in thoſe fewer things that are to be objected againſt the Diſſenters. And yet <hi>currying</hi> with the Diſſenters is not ſo great a Fault, but he could tell them upon the Spot, how their Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings are at an end, <hi>now our Churches power has been
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:60861:31"/>ſomething check'd,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pag. 5.</note> which he thinks they may <hi>Reflect upon.</hi> But if the Repreſenter would win their good opinion, he ſhould of all things beware of putting them in mind to <hi>Reflect;</hi> leſt when they begin to Reflect upon thoſe things of which he ſpeaks, they ſhould chance to Reflect upon other things of which he ſpeaks not.</p>
               <p>Me thinks too, I may reaſonably ſuſpect a little currying of the Repreſenter in what comes next. For, whereas the Anſwerer thought the Diſſenters <hi>too wiſe and cautious to take Characters</hi> [of us] <hi>from</hi> [Their own] <hi>open and profeſſed Enemies;</hi> (for that was his plain meaning) the Repreſenter underſtands him, as if he had meant <hi>our, i.e.</hi> the Church of <hi>Englands profeſt Enemies:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pag. 6.</note> and then hopes that our People will henceforth be ſo wiſe, as not to take Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racters of Popery from us, who are, as he ſays, <hi>Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies</hi> to Papiſts. But whether he was reſolved to make this miſtake for the ſake of the neat Turn, or to ſave himſelf from ſaying whether he was <hi>Friend</hi> or <hi>Enemy</hi> to the Diſſenters, I leave him to reſolve. But I hope he does not expect that I ſhould take notice of every ſuch little Reflection, as he knows this to be.</p>
               <p>And yet I muſt needs vindicate the Anſwerer from that Charge, that whereas the Repreſenter granted, that his Proteſtant Character of a Papiſt was not made up <hi>wholly</hi> of down-right Lies, the Anſwerer <hi>ſtretches this Courteſy with a witneſs,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pag. 9. Pag. 10.</note> and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes that we have the Repreſenter's word for it now that we are guilty of no Miſrepreſentation at all of matters of Fact, which he, the Repreſenter, never did, nor will allow. But in this the Anſwerer is wronged, who very well remembred, that his Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſary
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:60861:32"/>did a little diſpute his Churches owning the <hi>Depoſing Power,</hi> and two or three Points more, which he thought fit to drop at laſt. Now therefore, as the Anſwerer had frequently ſaid before, that the matters of Fact were the ſame in both Characters, <hi>very few things excepted;</hi> ſo in his laſt Anſwer, he was to be underſtood in courſe with the ſame Excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>viz.</hi> that we now had our Adverſaries Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, that in the Character of a Miſrepreſented Papiſt, there were no Proteſtant Miſrepreſentations of Popery properly ſo called; and ſo, that a very few Points excepted, we are agreed on both ſides upon the matters of Fact. And this one would think was plain enough in the laſt Anſwer, where the Anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er thus interprets the Conceſſion of his Adverſary. <hi>Whatever he at firſt pretended, he grants now, that we are not in a ſtrict and proper ſenſe Miſrepreſenters; and thus farewel to Character-making, ſince Papiſts and Proteſtants that underſtand theſe matters, <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. to An. Accom. </seg>
                     </label> 
                     <note place="margin">p. 8, 9.</note> are in the main</hi> (not abſolutely in every point, but in the main) <hi>agreed what is the Character of a Papiſt, tho they differ in their Opinions about him,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>I know indeed the Repreſenter would extend the <hi>down-right Lies,</hi> from which he does not abſolutely acquit us, to more Inſtances than thoſe excepted, by the Anſwerer. For which he appeals to his own Character of a Papiſt miſrepreſented, where he has repreſented the Proteſtants as Liars, in charging the Papiſts with other things diſowned by the Church of <hi>Rome:</hi> Which is one of the fineſt Fetches that is poſſible. For tho in that Character, he has made the Proteſtant to charge the Papiſt with all that we in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed charge him with; yet he has made him do
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:60861:32"/>more, and therefore might ſafely appeal to his own Character, to prove that we are <hi>Liars</hi> in <hi>ſome</hi> things; always ſuppoſing that he is the honeſteſt Man in the World, in repreſenting the Proteſtant Repreſentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Popery. But how often muſt he be told, that he has been a falſe Repreſenter of us as to this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter? That he ſometimes brings in Proteſtants char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging Papiſts, (1.) In ambiguous Terms, which ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit of different Interpretations; for inſtance, under the Head of <hi>Praying to Images,</hi> which is the firſt Point he mentions. (2.) With owning the dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Conſequences of their Doctrines and Practices, as that Papiſts <hi>do believe their Sins to be infalliby re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted upon Abſolution, whether they reſolve upon A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendment or no:</hi> which is his ſecond Inſtance, and there are two or three more, to the ſame Tune. (3.) With ſome things that we do not impute to 'em at all, either as Principles or Conſequences; witneſs that Inſtance which he has the fore-head ſtill to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt upon. <hi>For,</hi> ſays he, <hi>Are their Sermons in Latin? Do they teach in unknown Tongues?</hi> as if we charged them with this. I know not what every Proteſtant in the World may have ſaid in his heat againſt Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts: But I am apt to think that it will be as hard to find a Proteſtant that hath ſaid this againſt them, as to find a <hi>Zealous Brother</hi> that will own the Cant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Sermon he hath made againſt us. Upon one or other of theſe three accounts he might well appeal to his own Characters to convict us of Lyihg, and ask the Anſwerer <hi>what he thinks</hi> of this, or that which Proteſtants charge upon Papiſts; ſuppoſing, as I ſaid before, that he delivers <hi>Oracles</hi> always, when the is ſetting us out to the World.</p>
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:60861:33"/>
               <p>And now, I ſay, 'tis too late for the Repreſenter to ask us, <hi>what we think</hi> of theſe things; becauſe, not to mention the ſecond Anſwer, his firſt Anſwerer has told him very particularly what <hi>we think</hi> of them, what we do charge them with, and what not. And ſince he has ſaid nothing to it, it is unreaſonable to expect that we ſhould do the ſame thing over and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver again, as often as he is pleaſed to put the Queſtion to us. As for <hi>firing the City,</hi> and <hi>killing</hi> Sir <hi>Edmund-Bury Godfrey,</hi> &amp;c. what have theſe things to do in the Character of Popery? I ſuppoſe 'tis no Article of the Repreſenter's Faith; that Papiſts did not theſe things; I am ſure 'tis none of mine, that they did.</p>
               <p>Having upon no better grounds than theſe accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the Anſwerer of Miſrepreſenting him, he runs out into general and paſſionate Expoſtulations con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the injuſtice of thoſe who <hi>for their own In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt</hi> ſupport the falſe Notions which the People have of Popery, leſt <hi>themſelves ſhould appear the Deceivers.</hi> At length he asks, whether altho <hi>the People muſt be preached into a Dread of Popery, it be a Chriſtian Method to make uſe of Artifices to encreaſe the Horror?<note place="margin">Pag. 12.</note> Why ſhould every thing the Papiſts do be ſtretch'd and ſtrain'd, and forc'd to make it ugly?— 'Tis true, this is proper enough to win upon the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bile, who make no diſtinction between Real and Artifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial Monſters; 'tis well enough, where the Intereſt is beſt maintain'd by the madneſs of the People. But where's the Chriſtianity all the while, where's Truth and Charity?</hi> Why truly not ſo much as there ſhould be, where either theſe things are done on the one ſide, or falſly ſaid to be done on the order. Now it muſt not be quite forgotten that the Repreſenter
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:60861:33"/>wrote his Proteſtant Characters of Popery, as they lay in his own and the Peoples Heads; and made all his Anſwerers work in diſtinguiſhing between <hi>Repreſentation</hi> and <hi>Diſpute;</hi> between Principles that are <hi>owned,</hi> and Conſequences that are <hi>denied</hi> by the Papiſts, utterly uſeleſs; becauſe things did not and could not lie thus diſtinctly in the <hi>Peoples</hi> Heads. For Inſtance, Becauſe if a Preacher ſhould ſay that though the Papiſts think it lawful to worſhip Images, yet it is plainly forbidden in God's Word ſo to do, and that too as an Idolatrous Action; the poor Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple preſently conclude, that the Papiſts believing it to be Idolatry, differ from us in no other thing, but that we think Idolatry, and forbidden Worſhip, to be unlawful, and the Papiſts do not think ſo. But if the Repreſenter believed this of the People; <hi>Where was Chriſtianity, where was Truth and Charity,</hi> when he wrote his Repreſentation of Popery, under colour of diſabuſing the People; and made one part of a Papiſt's Character to be this, that he abhors Idolatry? for thus the People would he betrayed into a belief, that he does not ſo much as worſhip Images; for <hi>Conſequents</hi> and <hi>Antecedents</hi> are ſo jum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled in the Peoples Heads, that nothing can <hi>lie diſtinctly</hi> there. We indeed do not think ſo meanly of them, and therefore might honeſtly urge <hi>Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> and <hi>Conſequences</hi> againſt that and other <hi>Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctices</hi> of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church. But he, it ſeems, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved they could not diſtinguiſh between the one and the other; and then I am ſure if they acquit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Papiſts of the <hi>Conſequence,</hi> it would go hard if they did not acquit them of the <hi>Fact</hi> too; and therefore whether he put the Denying of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:60861:34"/>into the Papiſt's Character with an honeſt Deſign, at leaſt, whether he had any reaſon to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject againſt the diſtinct proceeding of the Anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer, I dare almoſt now appeal to himſelf. But, as I obſerved before, the Anſwerer made him aſhamed of imputing this kind of <hi>madneſs</hi> to the People, and ſo we heard no more of it in his next Reply. But yet the <hi>Intereſt</hi> we are ſaid to have in the People muſt ſtill be imputed to their <hi>madneſs.</hi> And what <hi>madneſs</hi> is it now? Why they <hi>cannot diſtinguiſh be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween Real and Artificial Monſters:</hi> Which is as much as to ſay, that we have made the Papiſts <hi>Monſters,</hi> by telling notorious Lies of them; and the People are ſo mad that they cannot find it out. But may not I take my turn now to ask, <hi>Where's Chriſtianity all this while; where's Truth and Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty?</hi> Why muſt we be branded with the Imputation of Falſhood and Calumny, and our Chriſtian Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren treated in that manner, as if they were mere ſtupid Creatures, and more fit to herd with Beaſts; than to live amongſt Men?</p>
               <p>As for our ſelves being thus urged, we beg leave to appeal to All that know us, whether this odious Character be any way ſuitable to our Converſation; and then, whether we have deſerved it for the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagement of this Controverſy in particular, we appeal to the World. We appeal to all Men of Sincerity and Underſtanding, what colour of Reaſon the Repreſenter had here to ask, Why <hi>praying to Images, leave to Sin for Mony, Forgiveneſs without Repentance,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>ſhould be ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged againſt them to make them the Object of Hatred, and the Subject of popular Fury?</hi> Have not his An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerers more than once publiſhed clearly and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinctly
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:60861:34"/>what we do, and what we do not charge them with in every one of theſe Reſpects? Has he convinced them of any Inſincerity, nay, of any miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take in the ſtating of theſe things? Has he taken no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of any thing they have ſaid about them? Why would he not be brought to confeſs the Juſtice of our charging them ſo far as we have done, and our Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice to them in charging them no farther, or at leaſt to confute us by ſhewing wherein we had done un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtly? What other Conſtruction now can <hi>Truth</hi> and <hi>Charity</hi> make of theſe Proceedings, but that he would not confeſs that we do them no wrong, and yet could not prove that we do? But then certainly he ſhould at leaſt have been ſilent, and not go on as he does to declaim againſt us; as if he really believed we were thoſe odious Miſrepreſenters and Falſifiers, which he would have the World believe that we are.</p>
               <p>He ſays indeed, that the Anſwerer <hi>unhappily takes it to himſelf, as if He and His were arraigned of Lying and Calumny,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>whereas the Repreſenter ſpoke only in general, without ſo much as hinting upon any party or perſon in particular.</hi> But ſurely when after the firſt Anſwer that was made in behalf of the Church, of <hi>England,</hi> the Repreſenter without telling us the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars why, could yet declare that he would <hi>be a Turk as ſoon as a Papiſt, if the Anſwerer had rightly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſented Popery;</hi> we muſt have as little underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, as he allows to the <hi>Mobile,</hi> not to find that we are principally intended in theſe general Declamati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. He thinks the Anſwerers <hi>over ſollicitude to prove his Innocence,</hi> may in ſome <hi>breed a ſuſpicion</hi> of his Guilt. But whether it be Innocence or Guilt that makes us ſollicitous to clear our ſelves, we may now
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:60861:35"/>leave the World to judg. One thing, I take it, is eaſy to be diſcerned, that tho our Adverſary Rowls in Figures to heighten the injuſtice under which <hi>He</hi> and <hi>His</hi> have ſuffered by Miſrepreſentations, yet he throws the Guilt ſo faintly upon the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> as if he were conſcious of being unjuſt to us all the while.</p>
               <p>As for the People of our Communion, whom he complements under the Title of the <hi>Mobile,</hi> we may ſay without vanity, that how ſcornfully ſoever the Repreſenter treats them, we ſhall never be aſhamed to compare them with their Neighbours; and that it would be a better World for the Repreſenter, if they were as ignorant and ſtupid as he would have them thought to be.</p>
               <p>But no more of what he has ſaid in this fit of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger; for here's a ſudden change, and now behold him the gayeſt and merrieſt Man alive. He fancies the Anſwerer left him to wonder who thoſe <hi>We</hi> are that <hi>are not Miſrepreſenters in a ſtrict and proper notion of Miſrepreſenting, i.e.</hi> who do not belye the Papiſts. For indeed he <hi>would gladly know who thoſe We</hi> are, <hi>that he might return them his thanks for this ſo kind Office— Did he but know the Men, he would never permit them to lye obſcured under the general name of</hi> We. No, <hi>he would particularize them to the World— For why? are not ſuch Men Prodigies of Truth, Honeſty, and Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice? — Men that never miſrepreſented the Papiſts! Why theſe are admirable Men indeed, and not to be heard of every day!</hi> Now really this, with all that belongs to it, is allowed to be very well for the kind, and ſo much the better, becauſe it more and more appears, that tho he can be angry without a cauſe, yet a ſmall
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:60861:35"/>matter will pleaſe him again. For he is delighted beyond meaſure with wondring who theſe <hi>We</hi> are, and <hi>wiſhes there be no miſtake in it,</hi> and makes it <hi>hard to imagine who they ſhould be:</hi> But I'le warrant him, he has 'em preſently, as hard as it is. For in the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry next place he tries whether the Anſwerer by his <hi>We,</hi> ſhould mean <hi>We Proteſtants.</hi> And that is a pretty near gueſs for the Firſt. But then alas! who can believe it, that <hi>We</hi> Proteſtants <hi>ſhould be no Miſre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſenters?</hi> He, <hi>for his part,</hi> would willingly give ſomething for the ſight <hi>of the Man that thinks so,</hi> who would be the <hi>greateſt Miſrepreſenter of All, in vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for the Truth of All that has been invented againſt the Papiſts theſe hundred and forty years.</hi> Why then, ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, they are not <hi>We Proteſtants.</hi> But for all that, upon conſideration, he thinks he may take it for granted that they are <hi>We</hi> Proteſtants. For the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerer <hi>vindicates Protestants,</hi> and for himſelf, <hi>one may ſwear he's a ſtan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>h True Proteſtant, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s never ſcrupling at any thing that's for running down the Papiſts, tho it be currying favour with and colloguing the Fanaticks.</hi> And thus the Anſwerer coming croſs in his way, his Fit takes him again; for he cannot abide the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerer, and ſo there's and end of his Mirth: And now in ſober ſadneſs <hi>we muſt ſuppoſe</hi> that the Anſwerers <hi>We,</hi> are <hi>We Proteſtants.</hi> For which reaſon the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſenter begins the World again, and is reſolved to prove out of the Sermons and Books of Proteſtants, that <hi>We Proteſtants</hi> are Miſrepreſenters: And ſo he falls to work about it in good earneſt through the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining part of his Book. Now I am ſo far from being angry with him for this, that I rather wiſh ſome merry Youth were to take him up here, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quite
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:60861:36"/>his Railery, and keep up the good humour a little longer. And if it ſhould come into any Bodies Head hereafter, who is given that way, to lay the Pleaſant and the Angry Repreſenter together, as it might be done: The Jeſt would go rarely forward, and that to ſome Bodies coſt too, that may be thinks little on't.</p>
               <p>For, was it not the <hi>Repreſenter</hi> that would be <hi>glad to know</hi> who theſe Men are that do <hi>not miſrepreſent Papiſts, theſe Admirable Men that are not to be heard of every day;</hi> theſe Men, that <hi>were he but aſſured of the Being of ſuch Men,</hi> he <hi>ſhould begin to think</hi> Aſtrea <hi>was returned again!</hi> Did he not wiſh to know them, that he might <hi>particularize them to the World,</hi> nay and <hi>have their Names Blazoned in every Sheet upon Pillars erected to their Memory?</hi> Yes ſurely, this was the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſenter</hi> himſelf. Why then, Dear Sir, be happy and joyful, for many ſuch <hi>Admirable Men,</hi> as theſe, <hi>are in being</hi> I aſſure you, and <hi>to be heard of every day;</hi> But becauſe it will be too great a charge to <hi>erect Pillars</hi> for 'em All, I ſhall at preſent recommend but two of 'em to your Acquaintance, who are already <hi>particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larized to the World,</hi> by the Names of the <hi>Firſst</hi> and <hi>Second</hi> Anſwerers to <hi>A Papiſt Miſrepreſented and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſented.</hi> What pity is it that ſuch Friends ſhould be <hi>obſcured</hi> ſo long <hi>under the general Name of</hi> We, and be no better known to one another? Theſe, Sir, are the Men whom you deſire to honour, as if they were made on purpoſe for it. For why? Tho very honeſt, Gentlemen they are, and their Words may go for as great a matter, yet they have a notable Quality be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, never to think of <hi>Repreſenting</hi> the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> without <hi>proving</hi> what they ſay. Why, Sir,
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:60861:36"/>they have been lately tryed upon no leſs than <hi>Thirty</hi> and <hi>Seven</hi> Points of <hi>Popery;</hi> and have born the Teſt of a ſevere, watchful, double-dealing Adverſary; and one as vehemently deſirous to find falſe Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenters among Proteſtants, as you can be to know the true ones. Now, Sir, judg if theſe two are not likely to prove Right and True Men: For the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſary is to this day roaming up and down amongſt other Mens Books to get Proteſtant Miſrepreſentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons for them to Anſwer; a plain ſign, you will ſay, that he has found none of their own to call them to an Account for. And ſo having found out your Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable Men for you, I wish you much joy of one another.</p>
               <p>Now this is too Blunt, I confeſs, to go for <hi>Railery;</hi> but 'tis <hi>True</hi> tho, and that's almoſt as good: And the Repreſenter may ſee by it how another would have handled him upon this matter, if he had not by good fortune fal'n in my way. It is to me a moſt unac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countable thing, why the Repreſenter ſhould ſearch for more and more Miſrepreſentations, Miſquotati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and ſuch like faults in Proteſtant Authors, and forſake the Defence of his own double Characters, if indeed he thinks they may be defended: But if he does not think ſo, it were but an honeſt Mans part to confeſs it, and then I think the Controverſy were at an end. Certainly the deſign of his firſt Book, which he ſtill pretends to vindicate, was to give us an account of the Doctrines and Practices of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> upon which ſcore he took upon him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf the Title of a Repreſenter. 'Tis true he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to diſpute for them too; but that deſign fell to the ground upon the firſt Attempt that was made
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:60861:37"/>upon him, and I believe he will hardly ſtoop to take it up again. But then to illuſtrate the Repreſenting part, he ſhewed on the other ſide how Proteſtants, as he ſays, have Miſrepreſented Papiſts. So that here was a ſolemn Controverſy begun upon ſo many ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral points, about Repreſenting and Miſrepreſenting; and it was, one would think, very fairly carried on by the Firſt Anſwerer, who we know went on with the Repreſenter from point to point, diſcovering, where need was, his Ambiguities and Fallacies on both ſides, mending his Characters, and giving a correct and plain account of the Doctrines and Practices of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> in oppoſition to that lame and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitful account thereof. which the Repreſenter had publiſhed. The ſum of the performance was to ſhew how much and no more we abſolutely charge upon the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and in matters of charge not ſo clear as the reſt, how far and no farther we accuſe them; every Particular being guarded with reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Proofs and Teſtimonies. They ſecond Anſwerer perceiving into what miſtakes the Repreſenter was wandring, by confounding the proper Subject of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentation, with Subjects of Diſpute, went as par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly through all the points, and plainly diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed thoſe things under every one. Now would not any Man of common ſenſe imagine, that, if the Diſpute were pertinently carried on, the Queſtion muſt be this, Who gave the trueſt account of the Faith and Worſhip of the Church <hi>Rome,</hi> the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſenter, or the Anſwerer? And if it were perti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nently managed, that this Queſtion muſt be driven through all the <hi>Thirty Seven</hi> Points, as it has been done once and again on our behalf. And, therefore
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:60861:37"/>to what end the Repreſenter ſhould trouble himſelf to find out new Repreſentations in the Books of other Proteſtants, a Man may well wonder for a while, tho at laſt he will ſettle upon the true Reaſon, that the Repreſenter was Sick of defending his own.</p>
               <p>If it be ſaid, that one part of his buſineſs at leaſt, goes forwards ſtill, which was to ſhew, that ſome Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants have been Miſrepreſenters; I deſire it may be conſidered too, whether this was not in order to the ſetling of a clear and indiſputable account between us, what are, and what are not the Doctrines and Practices of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> as to the <hi>Thirty Seven</hi> Points. For granting now, (and 'tis a good large Grant to be made at once) that the Repreſenter did ſincerely give in his own former Proteſtant thoughts of Popery, and (as far as he could under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand them) thoſe apprehenſions what Popery is, which lay in the Heads of the Vulgar; then ſo far as the Anſwerers confeſſed this was not a true Repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, if Proteſtants did thus charge the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> ſo far I ſay they complied with the Repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters deſign, which was to correct ſuch, if there were any ſuch miſtakes going amongſt Proteſtants. But ſo far as they owned the charge in the Proteſtant Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter to be good againſt the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> if the Repreſenter diſowned it, he had in this caſe nothing to do, but to confute their Teſtimonies, and to ſhew that in thoſe particulars as well as in others, his <hi>Church</hi> was Miſrepreſented. And therefore if he had been ſincere, the Controverſy had proceeded thus on his ſide; and nothing could have diverted him from pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding in this manner, if he had been able to make any thing of it. But inſtead of this, he has for some
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:60861:38"/>time forſaken his <hi>Thirty and Seven Chapters,</hi> and em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed himſelf in turning over ſome Books of Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants, to find out ſuch Sayings as he thinks there is any colour to call <hi>Miſrepreſentations;</hi> nay, he is fal'n ſo low as to pick out what <hi>Miſquotations</hi> of Authors he can find amongſt them, and to tax them here and there for Hiſtorical Paſſages.</p>
               <p>But did ever either of his Adverſaries undertake to juſtify all that any Proteſtant Divine, or Hiſtorian has at any time ſaid in oppoſition to Popery? Or, was it not poſſible to give a more honeſt account of Popery than he did, to diſcover his fallacious way, of repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting his own Church, and the true ſtate of the Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions that have been hitherto diſputed, without ſuch an undertaking? Nay have not his Anſwerers effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally done it, without any ſuch undertaking? ſo effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctually that he has forſaken the defence of his double Characters under the <hi>Thirty Seven</hi> Points? Why then muſt they be bound to Anſwer for all that every Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant has ſaid againſt the Church of <hi>Rome?</hi> Will he anſwer for all the Popiſh Miſrepreſentations of Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants, that I can bring before him? I ſhall try him a little as to this before I have done: And I think with ſome better Grace, than this Task has been put upon us withal. For if it be but a mean way of carrying on the Controverſy, as I confeſs it is, yet he has for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced us to it by inſiſting upon it ſo obſtinately, that we have now no other way to let him ſee the incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniency of it, but by turning it upon himſelf. And, which is ſomething too, we have cleared our Hands of him as to the Original Controverſy, for he has dropt that quite away, and ſo having no Arrears to be reproached with, we may handſomly enough talk
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:60861:38"/>with him upon this new Score; and I will venture before-hand to ſay thus much, that he is likely to be as deep in our Debt for this, as he is for his firſt deal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings with us. Nor am I afraid thus to ſpeak may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief in this matter, tho he ſeems to have taken up a way of writing now, that will not fail him in haſte; for as long as he can but find out any new ſevere Say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of Proteſtants againſt Popery, 'tis but furniſhing out a new Book with 'em, and he may as well call it by the Title of a Fifth or a Sixth Vindication of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, as by any other Title whatſoever. Nay the Vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dication will go forward, if he can but find out a <hi>Vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar Head</hi> without a Name, to ſay that he believes the Popiſh Sermons are in a <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nknown Tongue,</hi> or any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thing as extravagant as that.</p>
               <p>But tho it be no part of buſineſs to bring off e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very thing that has been ſaid or done by Proteſtants, yet I ſhall a little examine what our Repreſenter has charged thoſe with, whom he has ſingled out to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe them to the World. For I am much miſtaken if even here, he has not expoſed himſelf a great deal more than any Body elſe: Since he does often take the liberty to fill up his Tragical Declamations againſt Proteſtants, by ſpiteful Conſtructions, weak Inferen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and now and then by falſe Accuſations, which is never more intollerable, than when a Man is in the ſame Breath exclaiming againſt the Miſrepreſentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of others. For my own part, where his Accuſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in whole or in part fall juſtly, there ſhall they lye for me, nor will I make another Man's Fault my own by going about to defend it. And if he had ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken the ſame care not to make himſelf Guilty, by accuſing the Innocent, he had come off better upon
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:60861:39"/>this Theme of Arraigning particular Men, as wild as it is.</p>
               <p>He begins firſst with <hi>Sutcliffs Inference</hi> from <hi>Aquinas,</hi> which I confeſſ is a very ſilly one; tho I think it had been not only for <hi>Sutcliffs</hi> credit that this matter had been let alone, but for <hi>Aquinas</hi>'s too, whoſe Principle is no very wiſe one. But I ſee no reaſon why the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerer ſhould have been <hi>aſhamed to print it over again,</hi> ſince he did it only to ſhew that <hi>Sutcliff</hi> inferred his Accuſation by Conſequence from what an Author of their own had ſaid, but not to juſtify the Inference. And for any thing the Anſwerer has ſaid, the Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenter is at liberty to go on with his charge of <hi>Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance</hi> or <hi>Malice</hi> againſt <hi>him that drew the Conſequence,</hi> to call him a <hi>Fool</hi> in this buſineſs, if he believed the Conſequence to be Good, or a <hi>Knave</hi> if he did not.</p>
               <p>But I would gladly know how the Repreſenter can clear himſelf from groſs. Miſrepreſentation in the next Inſtance, where falling upon the Author of the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſenting Catechiſm</hi> for charging them with praying to Images,<note place="margin">P. 19.</note> he makes it to be a Crime, which his firſt Anſwerer had cleared them from in ſaying, that we do not <hi>charge</hi> them <hi>with praying to Images without any far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Reſpect.</hi> For many not a Man <hi>pray to Images,</hi> and yet not pray to them <hi>without any further Reſpect?</hi> This would make one believe that he writes only for the <hi>Mobile,</hi> in whoſe Heads things cannot <hi>lye diſtinctly.</hi> But 'tis not ſo honeſt tho, eſpecially in a Man that complains of Miſrepreſentations. But by this time, I hope, he is made ſenſible of his miſcauriage here, by what the Author of the Catechism has done to juſtify his charge. And ſo I paſs over this complaint, and come to the next.</p>
               <pb n="75" facs="tcp:60861:39"/>
               <p>Which is of a Sermon that charges them with pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to Reliques too. Now whether the Preacher had any particular Teſtimonies that there are ſome a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them who do <hi>not only Worſhip,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">P. 20.</note> but <hi>likewiſe call upon Martin's Boots, &amp;c.</hi> I know not and therefore cannot at preſent paſs Sentence againſt him; eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally ſince I am well aſſured that the Council of <hi>Trent</hi> condemns thoſe in general,<note place="margin">Concerning the Conſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of <hi>Eorum opis impetrand<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> cauſâ.</hi> Seſſ.25. See <hi>Defence of Exp. of Doctr. of Ch. of Engl.</hi> p. 24, 25.</note> 
                  <hi>who affirm that the Memories of the Saints are in vain frequented, for the obtaining of help from their Reliques, and other their ſacred Monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,</hi> or Remains. Now if <hi>Martin's Boots</hi> and <hi>Joſeph's Breeches, &amp;c.</hi> are the Reliques of Saints, then they are not only <hi>to be venerated,</hi> as the Council affirms, but the Memories where they are, muſt be frequented also, <hi>for obtaining help</hi> from them. This, I think, is no <hi>Miſrepreſentation,</hi> no <hi>wry Intepretation,</hi> no Imputation upon them from <hi>Ignorance or Malice in drawing the Conſequence.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the next place the Anſwerer of <hi>Catholicks no I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolaters,</hi> is made a Miſrepreſenter for ſaying, that the common Anſwer of <hi>Catholicks,</hi> that their Adora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Euchariſt cannot be <hi>Idolatry,</hi> is becauſe they <hi>believe the Bread to be God, juſt as the Worſhippers of the Sun, believed the Sun to be God:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">P. 20.</note> whereas <hi>the Catholicks do not believe the Bread to be God, &amp;c.</hi> To which I ſay, 'tis ſo notoriouſly known that Papiſts believe (as they tell us) the Bread to be <hi>Tranſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiated,</hi> that if the Anſwerer's Words be as they are here fet down, 'tis yet a mere Cavil to pretend that he would inſinuate as if the Papiſts believed that which they Adore to be Bread, as we believe it is no more. And the Argument is good thus, if their miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take, who believed the Sun to be God, did not excuſe
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:60861:40"/>their worſhipping the Sun from being Idolatry; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther will their miſtake, who believe what they wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip to be Bread no longer, but God, excuſe them, if it be Bread ſtill. But I ſuſpect the Words are more clear and full in the Anſwerer, at leaſt, I make no doubt that they are ſufficiently ſecured from the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſenter's Interpretation of them, by other Paſſages in Connexion. For the Repreſenter has not referred us to the Page, where he has picked up this Excepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which omiſſion I believe was deſigned, becauſe he has neglected ſuch reference in four or five Inſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces more. But tho I have upon this diſadvantage gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven him a particular Anſwer here, yet I do not intend to uſe him to it. For the employment he has found out for us at preſent, is not of that weight, that I ſhould be obliged to turn over whole Books, and ſome of 'em no ſmall ones neither, to find out a ſingle Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage that he thinks fit to carp at. And therefore, at preſent; I will not be concerned with the Vindicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of thoſe <hi>Deductive Abſurdities, which</hi> Dr. St. <hi>would perſwade to be Doctrines of the Roman Church:</hi> For the Repreſenter here refers to <hi>the general current of his Diſcourſe</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and which is yet more unreaſonable,<note place="margin">Pag. 21.</note> has given me a whole Book written in confutation of the Doctor to anſwer. For the like reaſon as he has referred the proof of <hi>a hundred and fifty Lyes</hi> (without giving one Inſtance) againſt <hi>John Fox's Acts and Monuments,</hi> to the <hi>Examen of</hi> John Fox<hi>'s Calendar, p. 3. p.</hi> 412. ſo do I too. Thus alſo the Arch-Biſhop of <hi>York</hi> miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quoting St. <hi>Thomas</hi> and <hi>Bellarmine;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">P.22,23,24.</note> and <hi>old Dr. Willets</hi> proof out of St. <hi>Bernard,</hi> that the Pope is <hi>Antichriſt;</hi> and Bp. <hi>Taylor</hi>'s miſquotations and corruptions of Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors, which ſome Anſwerer of his has <hi>made to appear,</hi>
                  <pb n="77" facs="tcp:60861:40"/>ſhall with all the reſt of this kind, paſs off together without any further notice. For ſtill I ſay 'tis too hard an Impoſition, for the Repreſenter in a few Lines to oblige us to read over ſo many Books; and which is by no means to be ſubmitted to, unleſs the Fate of the cauſe depended upon it, which I am not yet convinced it does. And therefore once again, I muſt deſire him to give in his particular Exceptions againſt our Authors in their own Words, if he thinks fit to go on in this way, and to tell us the particular Page or Section where ſuch Paſſages are to be found; and then he ſhall have my Judgment in the caſe: But if he leaves all upon his own and his Friends credit, I ſhall be ſo civil as to do ſo too.</p>
               <p>I come now to his charge upon Dr. <hi>Tillotſon,</hi> for abuſing <hi>Eſtius;</hi> but whether <hi>Eſtius</hi> be not more obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to Dr. <hi>Tillotſon</hi> than to the Repreſenter, I leave it to others to judg, when I have given a particular ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of this matter. I do acknowledg that thoſe Words cited by the Repreſenter are in <hi>Eſtius;</hi> but tho I cannot ſay whether the Dr. minded them or not, yet I believe it will either way appear, that the Repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter had but little reaſon to make this an Inſtance of our <hi>endeavouring to prove ſome Folly upon the Papiſts, out of their own Authors, and then bringing in Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors quite contrary to their own ſenſe and words. Eſtius</hi> concludes that the <hi>Fire</hi> which the Apoſtle ſpeaks of, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.15. is the <hi>Fire of the Day of Judgment,</hi> which ſhall <hi>prove</hi> every Mans work, and <hi>purge that which is not already purged.</hi> And at length he comes to ſpeak of the <hi>Purgatory of Souls after this Life, which ſeems not only not to be ſupported, but to be overthrown alſo by this place of the Apoſtle, ſince the whole purgation is reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:60861:41"/>to the laſt Judgment.</hi> To this he anſwers, that <hi>thus much is manifeſt againſt the Sectaries, from his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation of the place, that in the World to come ſome Sins are to be forgiven,</hi> viz. <hi>theirs who ſhall be purged and ſaved by Fire. Nor,</hi> ſays he, <hi>does it follow from the Purgatory Fire of the laſt day, that no Purgatory of Souls is left before that day, any more than it follows from the Purgatory of Souls, that there is no purging in this Life;</hi> which, allowing for the principles of his Church, is with the reſt that follows to this purpoſe, a good and ſolid Anſwer to the foreſaid Objection. And this was the Doctor's Ground for ſaying, that <hi>Eſtius contends that it cannot be concluded from hence that there is no Purgatory.</hi> But then he goes on, <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, we muſt know that as the Scripture often leaves a particular Judgment to be underſtood, under a general Judgment, and from the laſt day in which all ſhall be judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, will have the day of every ones Death to be underſtood in which each Man is judged by himſelf; ſo from the Fire that is to go before the Face of Chriſt at the general Judgment, and to purge whatſoever at that time remains to be purged, it leaves a certain Fire to be underſtood, in which a particular Judgment is exerciſed for the purging of Souls preſently after this Life.</hi> Then come in the words cited by the Repreſenter. <hi>Wherefore by this way the Puniſhment of Souls in Purgatory is well and ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lidly gathered.</hi> But how is it <hi>well</hi> and <hi>solidly gathered</hi> this way? Does <hi>Eſtius</hi> ſay that the puniſhment of Souls in Purgatory is implied in, or that it does any way follow from that general Purging which is to be at the Day of Judgment? No, he ſays not a word than looks this way; but only that one leaves the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to be underſtood, that is to ſay, if a Man has a
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:60861:41"/>mind ſo to underſtand it, but not elſe. For 'tis a ſhame to repeat that, becauſe where the Scripture ſpeaks of a general Judgment, it ſuppoſes that we muſt dye firſt; therefore when it ſpeaks of a general Purgatory of Men, it leaves a Purgatory of Souls be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forehand to be underſtood, or <hi>well and ſolidly gathered.</hi> But the Repreſenter will ſay, the Queſtion is not whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Eſtius</hi>'s way of <hi>gathering</hi> Purgatory from this Text, be good and ſolid; but whether <hi>Eſtius</hi> does <hi>contend</hi> for no more than that Purgatory cannot be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verthrown by it, as the Dean pretended. I grant this, to be the Queſtion, and it ſhall have an Anſwer, if it has not had it already. Whether the Dean made the ſame obſervation that I have made upon this my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterious buſineſs, I cannot certainly ſay, having never ſpoken with him about it: But I preſume he did, becauſe it will clear him from any great matter of blame, in taking no notice of the Paſſage cited by the Repreſenter. The Caſe in ſhort is this, <hi>Eſtius</hi> was very clear in this Point, that St. <hi>Paul</hi> does not here <hi>ſpeak of a Purgatory of Souls, but of that Fire which is to prove the works of. All at the day of Judgment.</hi> But then he muſt guard himſelf as well as he could from the charge of interpreting this place, otherwiſe than the <hi>Latins</hi> had interpreted it at <hi>Florence;</hi> which made it neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry for him to bring in his third Queſtion, <hi>An &amp; quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modo probetur,</hi> whether and how it can be proved from this place, that there is a Purgatory for Souls after this Life, in purſuance of which Queſtion he ſays what we have already cited. Now, although in his Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation of this Text, he could own, as he did, with great; modeſty and good reaſon, that he did not fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low <hi>Bellarmine, Lenſaeus, Vicus; Bonaventure</hi> in all
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:60861:42"/>things; yet when the Name of a Council lay croſs to him, no other kind of modeſty would ſerve but ſome appearance at leaſt of ſubmiſſion to it. And therefore obſerving <hi>that the Latin Fathers thought that Purgato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry was to be eſtabliſhed upon this place, tho the Greek Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers diſſented;</hi> he alſo <hi>thought</hi> it needful to <hi>gather</hi> it as <hi>well and ſolidly</hi> as he could, from this place too. For by that time he had done his beſt, <hi>proving</hi> was dwind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to <hi>gathering;</hi> and to ſuch a way of gathering too, that, the premiſes being conſidered. I leave it to all impartial Men to conſider, whether ſo Judicious a Man as <hi>Eſtius</hi> was, <hi>contended</hi> for the point; or rather if the modeſt <hi>Eſtius,</hi> in the ſtrait he was in, did not chooſe to talk beneath himſelf, in compliance with the <hi>Latin</hi> Fathers at <hi>Florence.</hi> So that at laſt we have here an Example of the Servitude of Ingenuous Minds in the Church of <hi>Rome;</hi> but not of <hi>charging Folly upon the Papiſts out of their own Authors.</hi> For this was that which the Dean declined the doing of; whereas if he had ſaid, <hi>Nay, All that</hi> Eſtius <hi>contends for from this place is, that it cannot be concluded from hence that there is no Purgatory, altho he makes a hard ſhift to avoid falling foul with the</hi> Florentine <hi>Council;</hi> here had then been no colour for accuſing him of Miſquotation, it had alſo done his buſineſs as well; only this had been to charge Folly upon <hi>Eſtius,</hi> and upon the <hi>Latin</hi> Fathers too, which it ſeems the Dean had no mind to do.</p>
               <p>I proceed next to his Charge upon the Author of <hi>The Devotions of the Church of Rome.</hi> And firſt he accuſes him of quoting <hi>Eſcobar</hi> for that which he does not ſay in the place cited; nay, <hi>there is not one word of it to be found in him there.</hi> Now to know whether this be ſo or not, it is but fair to take the whole Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:60861:42"/>of that Author, for which he refers us to <hi>Eſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bar,</hi> and not as it is ſlily gelt by the Repreſenter. The Paſſage is this: <hi>They tell us there is a vaſt number of Sins in their own Nature Venial, which are ſo very inconſiderable that an infinite Number of them altogether, will not deprive a Man of the Grace and Favour of God, or make up one Mortal Sin; and for the pardon of which there is no need or occaſion for the Mercy of God.</hi> Now <hi>Eſcobar</hi> in the place cited, <hi>Tract.</hi> 2. <hi>Exam.</hi> 1. <hi>Chap.</hi> 4. in anſwer to that Queſtion, <hi>N.</hi> 15. <hi>Whether many Venial Sins of themſelves, and formally ſpeaking, can make up one Mortal Sin?</hi> ſays thus, <hi>No, becauſe innumerable Venial Sins do not deprive a Man of the Grace of God.</hi> But the Repreſenter will not allow, that there is <hi>one word</hi> of that Paſſage, at leaſt, to be found there, that <hi>for the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don of ſuch Sins there is no need, or occaſion, for the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of God.</hi> But I am ſure the <hi>thing</hi> is to be found there; For he ſays <hi>N.</hi> 1. that a <hi>Venial</hi> Sin is that which <hi>does not render a Man worthy of Eternal Puniſhment:</hi> And now if innumerable Sins of this ſort do not of themſelves make up one Mortal Sin, I think it is plain that take them altogether, and there is no occaſion for God's Mercy in the pardon of them, unleſs it be Mercy to par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don where there is no deſert of Puniſhment. 'Tis true, <hi>Eſcobar</hi> ſays that they are worthy of <hi>Temporal Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment:</hi> but our Author was not obliged to take any no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of that, becauſe that which he complained of was not, that theſe Doctrines brought Mens For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes, in this World, into danger; but that by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of 'em, <hi>Men are in wonderful danger of being cheat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in a matter of ſo great moment as their Eternal Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation.</hi> So that altho the Repreſenter profeſſes that <hi>this Doctrine is contrary to their Belief,</hi> yet, at
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:60861:43"/>leaſt, he muſt confeſs that it was not contrary to <hi>Eſcobar</hi>'s; and therefore that he hath wronged our Author in charging him here with Miſquota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <p>The ſame Book ſays in another place, <hi>p.</hi> 56. That <hi>their ſaying the ſame thing ſo often over, in their Jeſus Pſalter, is not contrived to help and aſſiſt attention,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>but out of pure Vanity and Oſtentation, or as it were to flatter our B. Saviour, or the Saint they pray to.</hi> And this the Repreſenter calls <hi>throwing Dirt blindfold,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pag. 26.</note> &amp;c. and ſuch <hi>Miſrepreſenting,</hi> that if the <hi>State or Civil Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment</hi> were ſerved ſo, there would <hi>be a — at the end of it.</hi> By which, I gueſs, he would be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent that the Author were hanged. But one would be willing to know firſt what he has done to deſerve it. Why, ſays the Repreſenter, <hi>This is the Reaſon he gives of our Devotion.</hi> What? that all who uſe thoſe Forms of Devotion which the Author cenſures, have no other <hi>End or Intention,</hi> but <hi>pure Vanity and Oſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation or Flattery?</hi> ſo indeed the Repreſenter would inſinuate: But, as I ſhall make appear, the Author's meaning was that the Repetitions themſelves which he ſpake of, were purely <hi>vain, and do not ſerve to any good and prudent End:</hi> For which he chiefly blames the <hi>Contrivers</hi> of 'em, as the words plainly enough ſhew. But what reaſon he had to ſay this, was laid down juſt before in theſe words. Their <hi>Manuals</hi> of Devotion <hi>are ſo full of Tautologies, and vain Repeti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, then they muſt needs come under the cenſure of our B. Saviour,</hi> Matth. 6. <hi>tho they uſe his holy Name. For so in the</hi> Jeſus Pſalter, <hi>at the end of the Manual of Prayers and Litanies, printed at</hi> Paris, in <hi>Engliſh,</hi> An. 1682. <hi>in a Litany of Fifteen Petitions, the Name</hi>
                  <pb n="83" facs="tcp:60861:43"/>Jeſu <hi>is repeated over above 130 times: And in the ſame Book, in the Litany of the B. Virgin, they pray to her by</hi> 40 <hi>ſeveral Names, being only ſo many diſtinct Praiſes of her.</hi> Now this the Repreſenter thought fit to ſuppreſs, which would have ſhewn that he did not make <hi>Vanity,</hi> &amp;c. to be <hi>the Reaſon</hi> of the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples Devotion, but that he charged their Forms of Prayer with <hi>vain Repetitions.</hi> And here the Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>senter ſhould have ſhewn, if he were able, that the Repetitions mentioned do not fall under our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our's prohibition of <hi>vain Repetitions;</hi> that they could be <hi>contrived</hi> for ſome <hi>good and prudent End;</hi> that they ſerve to any thing better than <hi>Oſtentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> or <hi>Flattery:</hi> Here, I ſay, he ſhould have employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his Skill, and told us what are vain Repetitions, if theſe are not. But this was ſomething a harder Task, than to take a Paſſage by it ſelf, without that Connexion which would have explained it, and to repreſent the Author by it as odiouſly as he could. For, I ſay it again, he does not make <hi>Vanity,</hi> &amp;c. the <hi>Reaſon</hi> of their Peoples <hi>Devotion,</hi> even in uſing theſe vain Repetitions. But indeed he ſays plainly enough, that they are ſo contrived for Vanity, and Oſtentation or Flattery, that they are not Helps, but Hinderances to Devotion. But however, does not this Author make Vanity to be the <hi>End</hi> and <hi>Reaſon</hi> of their Contrivance, who compoſed thoſe Forms? No, not that neither; for tho that Expreſſion <hi>out of pure Vanity,</hi> &amp;c. be, I confeſs, ſomething obſcure, and ſeems to look that way, yet it was not his meaning, as any Body will ſay is plain beyond all Exception, that conſults the whole place. For thus begins that particular to which this Paſſage belongs.
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:60861:44"/>
                  <hi>Seventhly, Their Manuals and Books of Devetion, which they give their People to read inſtead of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, which they forbid to be uſed, tho they may DESIGN THEM AS HELPS, yet I muſt range them amongſt the Hindrances of Devotion.</hi> By which it is evident, that he meant not to charge even the <hi>Contrivers</hi> of theſe <hi>Tautologies,</hi> with any deſign to lead the People to <hi>Vanity,</hi> becauſe he ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes that they might <hi>deſign</hi> them as <hi>Helps,</hi> and not <hi>Hindrances.</hi> The Book which he carps at, is written with great Judgment, and no leſs Modeſty; as one may diſcern by this, that the Repreſenter could not find a more convenient Paſſage for his Anger to work upon, than that which we have ſeen. But we muſt not forget that he is all this while making good his Title of a <hi>Repreſenter.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And now the Biſhop of <hi>Kilmore</hi> is called to account for miſrepreſenting the Papiſts, by <hi>putting them upon the ſame File with Infidels and Pagans.</hi> For, as <hi>Delphos</hi> worſhipped <hi>Apollo,</hi> &amp;c. So, in Popery, <hi>England</hi> worſhipped St. <hi>George,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pag. 26.</note> &amp;c. And as the Pagans had their Gods for the ſeveral <hi>Elements,</hi> for <hi>Cattle</hi> and <hi>Fruit,</hi> for <hi>ſeveral Profeſſions,</hi> and <hi>ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Diſeaſes, to pray to: So, in Popery, they have one Saint for the Fire,</hi> &amp;c. Now if this be miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>repreſenting at all, 'tis miſrepreſenting with a wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, <hi>i. e.</hi> in the Anſwerer's Phraſe 'tis miſrepre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting <hi>in a ſtrict and proper ſenſe,</hi> and in the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſenter's Phraſe, <hi>downright Lying.</hi> For I do not find that the Biſhop affirms any thing in all this, but matter of Fact. But will the Repreſenter ſay that Papiſts have not Tutelar Saints for ſeveral Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, and ſeveral Saints to pray to, for their Cattle,
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:60861:44"/>and the Fruits of the Earth? Is it true or falſe that St. <hi>Roch</hi> is prayed to in caſe of the <hi>Plague,</hi> St. <hi>Petro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nella</hi> under <hi>Agues,</hi> St. <hi>Apollonia</hi> againſt the <hi>Tooth-ach?</hi> I ſhall expect his Anſwer to this; and if he dares not deny it, as I am perſuaded his Modeſty will not ſuffer him: I ſhall then ask him where the miſre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſenting lies? If it be ſaid to lye in this, that the Biſhop <hi>puts them upon the ſame File with Pagans,</hi> let us ſee how far he does ſo. He had laid down that Rule of God's Word a little before, <hi>Thou ſhalt wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip the Lord thy God, and him only ſhalt thou ſerve.</hi> And then he proceeds to the Compariſon, in which indeed he muſt be ſuppoſed to tax the Papiſts with contradicting that Rule, by their practice of worſhipping their diverſity of Saints, no leſs than the Pagans by ſerving their ſeveral petty Gods. But he is ſo far from ſaying, that in all reſpects they are as bad as Pagans, which one would underſtand by <hi>puting them all upon the ſame File,</hi> that he does not enter upon a Compariſon of Aggravations, in reſpect to this very matter of Worſhip; but only ſhews that Rule is viola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted this way, no leſs than that. Now if this be a true Charge, I conceive it is no ill manners to ſpeak the Truth in a Caſe of ſuch vaſt Concern. If it be Falſe, the Repreſenter had done more Service to his Cauſe, and won more deſerved Thanks from his own Communion, as well as ours, by ſhewing the difference between the one and the other, with reſpect to that Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, than by declining, as he has done, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the Juſtification, but very craftily the Confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion too of the Fact upon which the Charge is
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:60861:45"/>grounded: Inſomuch as they <hi>in whoſe Heads no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing lyes diſtinctly,</hi> would be almoſt perſuaded, that the Repreſenter accuſed the Biſhop of <hi>down-right Lying,</hi> and that perhaps the Papiſts have not their Tutelar Saints, and Saints proper for ſeveral Occaſions to pray to, as the Biſhop pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended. But any thing in the World ſhall ſerve to ſwell the Charge, when Proteſtants are to be ſet out for Miſrepreſenters.</p>
               <p>As littie reaſon do I find for his ſevere charge up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ſame Biſhop, for obſerving that ſome place their whole Worſhip of God in Bodily Exerciſe; meaning,<note place="margin">Pag. 26, 27.</note> as I have good reaſon to offer for it, not <hi>All,</hi> but <hi>Some</hi> Papiſts. For the Biſhop pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded to lay the ſame charge upon the Diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters (without any currying I aſſure you), nay, to thoſe of our Communion alſo, as any one may fee, <hi>pag.</hi> 11. And what was ſaid particularly of the Externals, in which thoſe Papiſts truſt, whoſe Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion runs out into nothing but External Show, ſeems to me to note no more, than the greater danger they of the <hi>Roman</hi> Communion are in of falling into this kind of Hypocriſy, by reaſon of the vaſt number of Ceremonies and Obſervations which they, above all other Chriſtians in the World, have brought into Religion. Theſe are the Paſſages which Anger and Ill-will have pick'd out of the whole Sermon, to expoſe the Biſhop to His Majeſty's Diſpleaſure; by which one may ſee what little cauſe the Repreſenter had to ſay, that <hi>he pretends to His Majeſties Word for abuſing them.</hi> If the Reader deſires to know the motives he had for Preaching and Publiſhing this <hi>Sermon,</hi> he will
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:60861:45"/>not take them, I ſuppoſe, as they are Ridicul'd by the Repreſenter, but go for 'em to the <hi>Preface</hi> it ſelf, which declares what they were; and then he will find that the Repreſenter has <hi>abuſed</hi> the Biſhop.</p>
               <p>Now whereas he found ſome Paſſages <hi>in the Book of Homilies</hi> of the <hi>ſame</hi> ſtrain with what he had noted in the foreſaid Sermon;<note place="margin">Pag. 2 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> the ſame An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer will therefore ſerve for both: And what he adds beſides, in contempt of <hi>thoſe Divines</hi> that <hi>compiled</hi> the <hi>Homilies,</hi> is as eaſily anſwered with Contempt. And ſo I come to that <hi>hearty Family-Prayer,</hi> which, as he ſays, <hi>has raiſed up</hi> from Turk and Pope, defend us Lord, <hi>a Note or two higher;</hi> in as much as it runs thus. <hi>O Lord confound Satan, Antichriſt, with all Hirelings and Papiſts.</hi> This Prayer, he tell us, <hi>is added to the end of the Singing Pſalms, in a common Prayer Book, Printed at</hi> Oxford, <hi>in the Year</hi> 1683, <hi>in Twelves;</hi> by which I gueſs he would bring that Univerſity too, as well as the foreſaid Biſhop, under His Majeſties Diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure. And therefore this Accuſation is not to be paſſed lightly over. Now <hi>Henry Hills</hi> could have given him abundant ſatisfaction in this matter, if he had been conſulted. For, upon the beſt Inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry I can make, I find that no Pſalms, in Twelves, were Printed in <hi>Oxford</hi> before the the Year 1684, and therefore no ſuch Impreſſion, as the Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenter means, could be there in 1683. But this is not all: for neither had thoſe Printed in 1684, that <hi>hearty Family-Prayer,</hi> which he talks of. But the Truth of the Caſe is this, <hi>Henry Hills,</hi> or he and his Partners, had Printed theſe very Pſalms, in
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:60861:46"/>Twelves, which the Repreſenter mentions, and that to a vaſt number, as I am informed by thoſe who will make it out, if it be required. Now if <hi>Henry Hills</hi> bound up his Pſalms with the <hi>Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford</hi> Common-Prayer Books, the Univerſity is no more to anſwer for that, than if he had bound up his own Life with one of them. It is ſuch a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother Suggeſtion the Repreſenter offers at in a Marginal Note elſewhere,<note place="margin">Pag. 30.</note> where he makes the Fire of <hi>London</hi> to be imputed to the Papiſts, in the <hi>Plates of the Common-Prayer Books Printed at</hi> Oxford, An. 1680. For no ſuch Plates were Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted there, however they came to be bound up with ſome Common-Prayer Books Printed that Year at the Univerſity. I am apt to think <hi>Henry Hills</hi> is able to give as good an account of this too, as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother. And I believe he can gueſs very nearly, who did not only Print ſince 1678, but hes alſo very lately Sold, a certain <hi>Confeſſion of Faith,</hi> as <hi>hearty</hi> as the foreſaid Family-Prayer; for there <hi>Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laters and Hereticks, Papiſts and Ana-baptiſts,</hi> are all put together, as <hi>Limbs of Antichriſt.</hi> But ſome Men take themſelves to be priviledged to do theſe bold things themſelves, and to accuſe others of the like when they have done. I am ſure that either the Repreſenter, or he, is not a little to blame for theſe unhandſome Inſinuations; my own ſuſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cions in this caſe I do not care to tell, and therefore I leave it betwixt them Two, <hi>to ſet the Saddle on the right Horſe,</hi> as the Repreſenter ſpeaks upon another occaſion.</p>
               <pb n="89" facs="tcp:60861:46"/>
               <p>Another way of Miſ-repreſenting them which he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plains of, is <hi>in laying on the colours with ſo much craft on the Papiſts Tenets, that though they are the very ſame, with what the most learned Proteſtants hold themſelves, yet they ſhall appear ſo foul and monſtrous, as if nothing leſs than a certain Damnation attended their Abetters. This,</hi> he ſays, <hi>is done in ſeveral inſtances;</hi> which makes me wonder that he choſe ſo unlucky an inſtance, as that of our <hi>rendring them ſo <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nchriſtian, for not allowing Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation to any out of their own Church;</hi> in a word, for damn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Proteſtants.</hi> But do we Miſrepreſent them in this? mark how the Repreſenter makes it out, Dr. <hi>Tillotſon</hi> in the fore-mentioned Sermon, <hi>inveighing againſt the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charitableneſs of Papiſts — at last in a rapture of Charity concludes,</hi>
                  <q>I have ſo much Charity (and I deſire always to have it) as to hope that a great many among them who live piouſly, and have been almoſt inevitably de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in that Church by the prejudice of Education and an invincible Ignorance, will upon a general Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance find mercy with God.</q> Now inſtead of this, the Repreſenter <hi>expected</hi> from the Doctor <hi>ſome extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary piece of Charity both for the Reformation and example of the Papiſts;</hi> and <hi>yet,</hi> ſays he, <hi>after all the outcry and busſle, he wont allow one more grain of Mercy to the Papiſts, then the Papiſts do to them, that is onely to ſuch who having lived piouſly and truly repented of their Sins, have an invicible Ignorance to attone for all other errours of the underſtanding, which is the very Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the Papiſts, in reſpect of ſuch who die out of the Communion of their Church.</hi> So that we have Miſ-re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſented Papiſts in pretending that they do not allow as great hopes of Salvation to us continuing and dying Proteſtants, as we allow to them continuing and dying Papiſts.</p>
               <pb n="90" facs="tcp:60861:47"/>
               <p>Now I confeſs I am under ſome temptation to ſhew who is the Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>repreſenter in the Caſe; but this is ſo good a hearing, that I will not go about to clear our ſelves from being Miſ-repreſenters upon this occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, but take him at his word, that here we are Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>repreſenters: nay, more than that, I will thank him for taking all opportunities to report us for ſuch Miſ-re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſenters, to the people of both Communions; for thus it may be hoped that we ſhall never more be troubled with that Argument to perſwade Ours, and to confirm His, in the Communion of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church, that ſince we grant the Papiſts a poſſibility of Salvation, and they utterly deny a poſſibility of it to us, the Communion of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church muſt needs be the more ſafe, inaſmuch as both parties agree in a poſſibility of Salvation in that Church, but they do not both agree upon ſuch a poſſibility in ours. And ſince we are proclaimed Miſ-repreſenters upon this account, I deſire alſo that from this time foreward, the Trade of going up and down with peremptory denouncing Damnation to all of our Communion, may be at an end, and never heard of more: And that no advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges may be made of our charitable hopes and conceſſions in behalf of ſome that dye in the Communion of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> ſince it ſeems the <hi>Doctrine of the Papiſts is the very ſame in reſpect of ſuch who dye out of that Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion:</hi> Or at leaſt, that no regard be given to thoſe of the Roman Church who ſhall hereafter poſitively de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce Damnation againſt us, ſince the Repreſenter will have it that we are as poſitive againſt them, inafmuch as to ſay that <hi>Papiſts are guilty of ſins inconſiſtent with Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, is but to ſay, they are damned in another phraſe.</hi> The Repreſenter I ſay, who takes upon him to correct all falſe notions of Popery, and is therefore much to blame,
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:60861:47"/>if he be ignorant of the Doctrines of Popery, has declared to the World, that whether in the way of Hoping,<note place="margin">P. 28.</note> or of Cenſuring, <hi>Proteſtants and Papiſts ſay the ſame thing of each other:</hi> And therefore I think the foreſaid Requeſts are very reaſonable ones; ſo that this one matter is in a way of being fairly compounded, and if the Repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter likes it, I am ſure both parties are well pleaſed.</p>
               <p>For want of other complaints, he takes up one at length, which he had dropt ſome time ſince, <hi>viz.</hi> That we <hi>rake together ſome odd and extravagant Opinions of ſome Authors,<note place="margin">P. 29.</note> to ſet them down for the received Doctrine of the Church.</hi> Which complaint he ſupports by no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe but ſuppoſing that the ſo often-mentioned Archbiſhop of <hi>York</hi> is guilty of this in citing <hi>Bulgradus,</hi> &amp;c. and that this <hi>is enough to make any extravagancy paſs for an Article of Faith.</hi> Now he does not ſo much as make it appear that this Archbiſhop pretends the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>travagancies for which he brings thoſe Authorities, to be <hi>Articles of Faith</hi> in the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> But how far their Church is chargeable with the ſeveral Extravagan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies of their Authors, and what uſe we may and ought to make of their Divines and Caſuiſts, &amp;c. in the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſies now on foot, the Repreſenter has been al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready told very diſtinctly;<note place="margin">Pap. not Miſ. rep. by Prot p. 67, 68, 69.</note> and when he thinks fit to Reply, he ſhall not want an <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwer.Anſw. to Pap. </seg>
                  </label> 
                  <note place="margin">Prot. <hi>p.</hi> 9.</note> In the mean time, to convince us of the unwarrantableneſs of this method, and what a wretched thing it is to charge pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Doctrines upon a Church as Articles of her Faith, he brings in a Popiſh Preacher inveighing againſt the ill Manners, and eſpecially the diſloyalty of Proteſtants, upon one paſſage in the <hi>Decay of Chriſtian Piety,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>P.</hi> 30, 31, 32.</note> ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in Sir <hi>R. Baker,</hi> and a third in <hi>Jovian.</hi> Now I ſay, let them who do thus argue againſt the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> as he makes his Popiſh Preacher to inveigh a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:60861:48"/>us, let them I ſay take the ſhame of it. But for any thing that he has done hitherto, the men are yet to be found out: though I do not know but upon ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry diligent ſearch ſome one ſuch or other may be taken amongſt us; and when that happens, he ſhall go for me, and keep company with that once Proteſtant who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved the Sermons of the Papiſts were made in a lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage unknown to the People. Now he confeſſes all this <hi>Harangue</hi> to be a piece of Sophiſtry, which he has put into the mouth of a <hi>Popiſh Preacher:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">P. 33.</note> Which is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough for me, and I am not at all moved hy his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending this was done to make us aſhamed of <hi>practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing it in good earneſt,</hi> as he has <hi>ſeen and heard</hi> that we do. For this is a reaſon I am now pretty well uſed to, it being the very ſame wherewith he defends that ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diculous Sermon which he compoſed for the <hi>Zealous Brother.</hi> And therefore I ſhall even pin this <hi>Harangue</hi> to the remainder of that Brother's Sermon, that when one is called for, the other may not be forgotten.</p>
               <p>And ſo at laſt we come to Miſ-repreſenting, in <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation to ſome matters of Fact and Hiſtory,</hi> and here he <hi>hopes the Reader will diſcover</hi> notable things. The firſt Miſ-repreſentation of this Kind, in which he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, was the Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>repreſenting of the <hi>Rich Hangings,</hi> the <hi>Maſſy Plate, and other things which Adorned the Altars in the times,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">P. 33.</note> before the Reformation, the <hi>Candleſticks, Crucifixes,</hi> and <hi>Shrines; Three Epiſcopal Houſes,</hi> with <hi>Four or Five Churches,</hi> &amp;c. For theſe were Repreſented as <hi>Superſtitious,</hi> or <hi>Superfluous,</hi> and <hi>forthwith were immediately blown up.</hi> Now a man ſhall not preſently find how this comes to be Miſ-repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, the Papiſts in <hi>relation to ſome matters of Fact and Hiſtory.</hi> He names but one Proteſtant, ſpeaking of theſe things, <hi>viz.</hi> Dr. <hi>Heylin,</hi> and he too, is brought
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:60861:48"/>in agreeing with the Repreſenter in charging thoſe doings upon <hi>Covetouſneſs, Ambition and Envy;</hi> nor is any other Cited as contradicting him. Was not the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſenter full of choler and bitterneſs, that he muſt needs eaſe himſelf whether it be in fit place or not? I ſee the bottom of this buſineſs plainly enough: If that Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of Doctrine and Worſhip which our Church made, be not blackened enough already, he is reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to charge upon it all the faults of the great Men that made advantages by the Change. But muſt the Vices of the States-men in thoſe days neceſſarily affect the Reformation? Why then muſt not, the Vices of Popes affect Popery? If he has a mind to it, let him repreſent the former ten times worſe then they were, and when he has done, I will ſhew him as many Popes Repreſented, by their own Hiſtorians as really bad, as he has made thoſe by Fiction, and this too by Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians of no leſs Credit amongſt them, then Dr. <hi>Heylin</hi> is with us. The Repreſenter owes us a good Turn, and if he can but bring in the word <hi>Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>repreſenting.</hi> 'tis all the pertinence he cares for, though it be Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>repreſenting <hi>Plate</hi> and <hi>Hangings.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Again,<note place="margin">P. 34.</note> becauſe he fancies that King <hi>Henry</hi> the Eighth <hi>made way for Proteſtantiſm to enter into the World</hi> (in which however, he is miſtaken) he taxes him boldly of <hi>Vile Extravagancies,</hi> the reſpect that is due to <hi>Crown'd Heads,</hi> no nor the conſideration of that <hi>Line</hi> in which this Prince ſtood amongſt them, being not able to reſtrain him. But where is the Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>repreſentation complain'd of? Certainly the Popes Power here might be an <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpation,</hi> though the motive upon which <hi>Henry</hi> the Eighth threw it quite off, (as it had been curbed by his Predeceſſors before) ſhould not prove the beſt in the World: But let the Repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:60861:49"/>here alſo uſe his liberty of rendring him as odious as he can, remembring all the while that the Faults of that Prince reflect no leſs diſhonour upon the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> then upon the Church of <hi>England,</hi> as 'tis now Reformed: For 'tis certain, that in all other points he was a Papiſt, excepting that only of the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premacy; unleſs the Repreſenter will ſay that the whole of their Religion is in effect this, that the Pope ſhould be all in all, in the Dominions of every Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Prince in the World.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Luther</hi> comes next upon the File for <hi>Marrying a Nun</hi> contrary to his <hi>Vow of Chaſtity.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">P. 34.</note> By which he means a Vow of <hi>Caelibacy,</hi> as if the Marriage Vow, were not a vow of Chaſtity too. But do not their own Divines ſay, that the vow of Continency may be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented with? And has not the Pope diſpenſed in grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter matters? Had <hi>Luther</hi> marryed with his Diſpenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, he had it ſeems committed no fault at all. And we are apt to think that if notwithſtanding his Vow, he had good reaſon to marry, he might do it ſafely e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough without the Popes Diſpenſation. But where's the Miſ-repreſentation now? Why, here's a Vow of Continency Repreſented as a raſh and inconſiderate Vow, and this is <hi>Miſ-repreſenting Papiſts in relation to matters of Fact and Hiſtory.</hi> And thus alſo honeſt Sir <hi>William</hi> Miſ-repreſented <hi>Chalices,<note place="margin">P. 35.</note> Croſſes, Images,</hi> nay, <hi>Guineas,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Into Popiſh Trinkets and Trumpery, and made them fit for ſeiſure.</hi> But I ſay neither was Sir <hi>William</hi> honeſt in doing it, nor the Repreſenter over wiſe in mentioning it here.</p>
               <p>His next Fling is at Sir <hi>Richard Baker,</hi> who up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Executions of ſeveral great Men in Queen <hi>Mary</hi>'s Reign, chanced to ſay according to his wonted Eloquence: <hi>Now the Cataracts of ſeverity will be open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:60861:49"/>that will make it rain Blood.</hi> Well, but to bring off honeſt Sir <hi>Richard</hi> for once, he does not ſay that this <hi>severity</hi> was Tyrannical or Unjuſt, for if he had, cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly the Repreſenter had brought us all under the laſh for it: But the ends of theſe great People being Tragical, he thought good to ſet the matter off with a <hi>Tragical,</hi> or, as the Repreſenter calls it, a <hi>pat phraſe,</hi> without any futher deſign. And then as for the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Blood ſpilt in Queen <hi>Marys</hi> Reign, which he ſeems to charge altogether upon <hi>Provocations, Tumults, Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions,</hi> and <hi>Rebellions;</hi> he is guilty of the ſame fault, which he accuſes Proteſtants of, <hi>viz.</hi> Of Repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting things by <hi>halves.</hi> Were none put to death in thoſe days but for ſuch cauſes? Were <hi>Cranmer, Ridley, Latimer, Taylor,</hi> and almoſt all the 300 ſpoken of, burnt for Hereſy or not? Was not the Queſtion con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Sacrament of the Altar, the burning Queſtion? For thoſe that were guilty of the Abuſes he mentions, they might thank themſelves, we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend them not. But what colour is there for Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting all as ſuch? And why will the Repreſenter put us upon talking of theſe things, who had ſaid nothing of them, if he had not forced us to it in our own de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence.</p>
               <p>But to ſee now how much there goes in the telling a ſtory: <hi>Queen</hi> Elizabeth <hi>put to death,</hi> as he ſays,<note place="margin">P. 36.</note> 
                  <hi>Two hundred Perſons upon the ſcore of Conſcience, without any actual Crime or Miſdemeanour againſt the Ancient Statutes of the Land.</hi> Two hundred Perſons! Truly I do not know but in her long Reign of about 40 Years, ſo many might be put to death. But I wiſh the Repreſenter, ſince he pronounces in general with ſo much confidence, had named <hi>One</hi> or <hi>Two</hi> that were put to death <hi>upon the ſcore of Conſcience,</hi> and likewiſe what point of <hi>Conſcience</hi>
                  <pb n="96" facs="tcp:60861:50"/>it was. However ſomething is neceſſary to be ſaid in general Anſwer to that Charge which he plainly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends, though he would not plainly ſpeak it out. In ſhort therefore, about ten Years after the Queen came to the Crown, Pope <hi>Pius Quintus</hi> ſends over his Bull for the Excommunicating and Depoſing her, upon which followed the Statute againſt the Execution of it: Which yet did not hinder ſeveral Prieſts and Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuits from trying to have it Executed, in purſuance whereof the Queens Life was more then once in dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger. And therefore when no other Remedy would ſerve the turn, all Popiſh Prieſts of the Queens Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, were baniſhed under the Penalty of Treaſon, and had forty days given them to prepare for depart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. This Law was made at leaſt twelve years (I believe more) after the Popes <hi>Breves</hi> were ſent hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: And upon this Law ſome Prieſts that were af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards found here, were Executed, and ſome were not, who though coming into <hi>England</hi> contrary to the Law, yet withal, giving ſecurity for their dutiful Behaviour to the Queen, were, without changing their Religion, ſet at liberty: For, if we may, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve one that knew theſe things better then the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſenter ſeems to do, though our Princes judged it neceſſary for their own ſafety, that this Law ſhould continue in force, yet to avoid the doing of any thing that looked like putting men to death <hi>upon the ſcore of conſcience,</hi> they qualified the rigour of it by their own Mercy, where a Treaſonable deſign did not otherwiſe appear. For when <hi>Goodman</hi> a Jeſuit, was Reprieved by King <hi>Charles</hi> the 1ſt,<note place="margin">An. 1640. Jan. 25.</note> and the King was Expoſtula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with by the Parliament about it, he ſignified the cauſe to be this, that <hi>Goodman</hi> had been found guilty, merly as being a Prieſt, which was the reaſon of the
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:60861:50"/>King's mercy, and that in this clemency he did but fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the examples of his, Father, King <hi>James,</hi> and of Queen <hi>Elizabeth.</hi> Now whether we ſhould believe King <hi>Charles</hi> the Martyr, or our Repreſenter, I leave others to judge. This general account may ſerve for, his general charge; and I do not think fit to run out into more particulars, unleſs the Repreſenter gives oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion; but I leave him to conſider better of theſe things: And when he has done it, he may perhaps feel a little ſhame for having ſaid juſt before in the Caſe of Queen <hi>Mary, Now one would think to be just to Crowned Heads, the Blood ſhould not be expoſed alone to the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, but likewiſe the Occaſions and Provocations given:</hi> And in Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi>'s caſe I will adde, And the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy alſo that was s;hewn, notwithſtanding thoſe <hi>Occaſions</hi> and <hi>Provocations</hi> that were <hi>given</hi> her.</p>
               <p>But whereas he calls the Law we ſpeak of a <hi>Law of her own contriving, a Law ſo cruel that the like is ſcarce to be found among the</hi> Mahometans, <hi>who though they have conquered many Chriſtian Nations, yet never, as he has heard of, made it Treaſon for their Natives to profeſs their own Religion, or maintain their Paſtors.</hi> To let paſs the Miſrepreſentation he inſinuates, of <hi>making it Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to profeſs their own Religion,</hi> it would almoſt tempt a man to ſearch the Records of old Time, to ſee if ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing has not paſſed in the World as <hi>cruel</hi> as this Law, if it had been executed to the utmoſt rigour. For why? ſhould Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> under whoſe Reign our Nation purchaſed ſome Glory abroad, ſuffer now at home the imputation of being the moſt Tyrannical Prince that ever was in the World; beyond the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples of <hi>Mahometans?</hi> and of Mahometans too in their ſeverity towards the Chriſtian Nations which they have Conquered; why, this is ſtrange indeed,
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:60861:51"/>and not to be taken upon the Repreſenters word: For there are <hi>Annals</hi> that ſpeak of a certain <hi>Law,</hi> not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed for the Baniſhing of people <hi>upon the ſcore of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience,</hi> but the keeping of them at home to be tormen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for their Conſcience. Had they been ſuffered to uſe the Liberty that our Saviour once gave, of Flying, into another Country, when they were Perſecuted in their own; it had been a favour in compariſon to the reſtraint; and Death had been a mercy to the Vexati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons they endured. The <hi>like</hi> to this indeed <hi>is ſcarce to be found even amongſt thoſe</hi> whom the Repreſenter ſpeaks of: And which made the caſe yet harder, this <hi>People</hi> had not deſerved ill of the State, they neither ſided with Forreign Powers, nor with Domeſtic Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels; nay, they had behaved themſelves ſo well, that there was nothing but their Vertue to make them fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. But Hiſtories ſay that thoſe of them who eſcaped by miracles of Providence, were well received everywhere, and eſpecially by a Prince who was not of their Religion, but yet to his immortal Glory gave them Refuge and Relief in his own Countries.</p>
               <p>As to the <hi>Powder Plot</hi> which he next mentions: His inſinuation concerning my Lord <hi>Cecil,</hi> has been ſo often expoſed, and if it were true, is ſo unable to leſſen the guilt of thoſe that were concerned in it, that I ſee no reaſon why I muſt needs enter into that Hiſtory: We do not charge all of that Communion with it, but we have reaſon vehemently to ſuſpect all that went a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout to excuſe, and poſitively to condemn all that thought fit to praiſe the Traytors. But if we ſhould have charged, as he pretends we do, the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> with this Treaſon, yet I am confident the Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion of the <hi>West</hi> ſtands not altogether ſo fair to be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted to the Church of <hi>England:</hi> For ſurely there was,
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:60861:51"/>no Act of this Church for the Excommunicating and Depoſing of the King; but it was the fight of the Pope's Brief to ſuch a purpoſe as that, inſpired one of the Traytors, as himſelf confeſſed, with thoſe thoughts that at laſt ſetled upon the <hi>Powder Plot.</hi> And I think it was a Church of <hi>England</hi> Parliament, and a Church of <hi>England</hi> Army that ſo loyally ſerved his Majeſty upon that occaſion in the <hi>West:</hi> But let the Repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſhew, if he can, that the Papiſts were as ſerviceable in the prevention of the <hi>Powder Plot.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We are now drawing to an end of a tedious Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint, which ſurely cannot laſt much longer, when he is fain to ſpin it out, with a ſtory of the <hi>long diviliſh Knives</hi> which Papiſts were ſaid to procure for <hi>cutting of the Proteſtants Throats.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">P. 39.</note> For I am ſo perfect a ſtranger to the leaſt report of this matter, till I met with it here, that I can ſay nothing to it. As for the Fire of <hi>London,</hi> that I confeſs I have heard of, and likewiſe that many char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged it upon the Papiſts; now for thoſe that did ſo, I hope I may without offence offer that excuſe for their credulity, which I take a hint of from the Repreſenter himſelf: It could not be expected but that the grief of ſo undoing a Calamity in vaſt numbers of ſuffering Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, ſhould diſcharge it ſelf in accuſing thoſe as the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors of it, who, as they believed, were well pleaſed with it: As for the Repreſenter, what his thoughts are towards <hi>London,</hi> he has given us plainly to underſtand, in calling it <hi>a Proteſtant Sodom,</hi> which <hi>Heaven</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed. Now I dare ſay this was not meant for a la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentation over the ſins and ſufferings of the City: But if men will go on to inſult at this rate, they ſhould however, be leſs clamorous againſt thoſe miſtakes of which the greateſt occaſions are given by them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.</p>
               <pb n="100" facs="tcp:60861:52"/>
               <p>Then as to that which he calls a <hi>Monſieur's Invention:</hi> They that gave credit to it, have this to ſay for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, That <hi>Du Moulin</hi>'s public offer to make full proof of his ſtory, when Authority ſhould require it, ſtood many years, even to the day of his death; which was no improbable argument that he was provided with reaſonable good teſtimony, though it was not thought fit to call upon him for it. This may be ſaid to ſhew, that if there were never ſo many that ſwallowed the ſtory, yet this was no reaſon for the Repreſenters furi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous exclamations: For I am by no means ſatisfied that they who believed it, did ſo <hi>in defiance to all their Senſes;</hi> for though there were <hi>Actors</hi> and <hi>Contrivers</hi> of the Murder of King <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt, <hi>as public as the noon-light,</hi> yet I do not feel any ſuch <hi>contradiction</hi> in ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing that ſome <hi>Contrivers</hi> there might be who were <hi>not as public as the noon-light:</hi> And when the Repreſenter thinks of it better he will ſay ſo too, unleſs he will ſay, that becauſe the Contrivers of that dark Treaſon of the <hi>Powder Plot,</hi> were at laſt as public as the noon-light, therefore that <hi>it was in all likelihood a Contrivance</hi> too, of <hi>the good Lord Cecil,</hi> cannot be credited, but <hi>in defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance to all our Senſes.</hi> And yet after all, how does it appear that we have laid any ſuch ſtreſs upon <hi>Du Mou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lin</hi>'s Relation, as the Repreſenter intimates: For my own part in all the converſation I have had amongſt Proteſtants, I can remember nothing concerning it, but that it has been ſometimes a little wondered at, that he was never required to prove his ſtory. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I doubt the Repreſenter has here plaid the part of an unwiſe man, in reviving a ſtory to the diſadvantage of the Papiſts, which died with the firſt report of it, as we thought at leaſt; for unleſs the Repreſenter thought we had ſome reaſon to believe it, why ſhould
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:60861:52"/>he go about to complain that we do believe it? I think we have been more Juſt to his Party, than he has. For our ſenſe as to this matter is, that ſince now the ſtory is not capable either of being proved, or diſpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, it is to be let fall, and the World is no more to be troubled about it; though whilſt <hi>Du Moulin</hi> was alive, it was not to be expected but that one or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther would be harping upon it.</p>
               <p>At laſt he comes to the <hi>Garagantua Miſ-repreſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of them all, that is,<note place="margin">P. 40.</note> the Divine</hi> Oates <hi>with his Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt Plot.</hi> And here, as from a Caſtle where he is ſafe from all poſſbility of Aſſault, he bids defyance to us with all the Rhetoric, that Anger and Scorn can in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpire a man withal. But becauſe he lets fly at the <hi>Pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pits</hi> for this, and ſo makes the Clergy to have given what Authority they could to <hi>Oates</hi> his lyes from their <hi>Pulpits,</hi> I muſt needs change a word or two with him about that in our own Defence, and tell him that neither is himſelf of that Credit, nor the thing it ſelf ſo likely, but that it ſtood in great need of particular proofs. I know not but that amongſt Ten thouſand Men, here and there one might deliver the news of the <hi>Pilgrims,</hi> and the <hi>Black Bills</hi> from the Pulpit. But I never heard of any that did, and I almoſt think that if the Repreſenter had known a few Inſtances of this Kind, out they had come, if it had been for nothing but to ſupport the Credibility of his general Accuſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. And to go further with him, whereas he confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently ſays, that <hi>the WHOLE Plot was received with that welcome and Credit, that what would have been queſtioned in the very Scripture, was entertained with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any ſcruple.</hi> I will make bold to ask him, by whom it was entertain'd, did himſelf believe the <hi>whole</hi> Plot, while he was a Proteſtant? If he did, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:60861:53"/>we have not loſt one of the wiſeſt of our Party, If he did not, neither did any body elſe; that ever I could hear of, though perhaps many might be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve more then was true. But for a more particular account who believed much, who little, who nothing at all of <hi>Oates</hi> his Diſcoveries, and the reaſons of the ſeveral Opinions, he muſt excuſe me for that; I am reſolved not to be drawn in. Nor have I lately ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken with every Man in the Nation. And 'tis onely for a Repreſenter to talk of theſe matters, and to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce generally without exception, though he does it alſo without examination of the particulars be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hand.</p>
               <p>Thus far I have waited upon the Repreſenter in examining the Reaſons, upon which he pretends that we uſe I know not how many Methods to Miſ-repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Papiſts, though it has been every ſtep out of the way: For if all had been true that he pretends, what is all this to the Defence of his <hi>Thirty Seven</hi> Chapters? What is it to his Anſwerers, who had no more to do then to rid their hands of thoſe Thirty-Seven Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters? And they have done it ſo effectually, that the Repreſenter has thought good to rid his hands of them too.</p>
               <p>But I think by this time, it may appear that he has all this while given us juſt cauſe to complain, that we are many ways Miſ-repreſented by Papiſts, though the Repreſenter without juſt cauſe, was reſolved to be before hand, in the ſame Complaint againſt us.</p>
               <p>For not to repeat thoſe <hi>Miſ-repreſentations, Falſe Conſtructions,</hi> and <hi>Wry Interpretations</hi> of Proteſtant Authors, &amp;c. which I have ſhewn him to be guilty of, in examining ſome of his Complaints; it were a very eaſie matter to convict him of no leſs untrue then
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:60861:53"/>ſpiteful inſinuations againſt all Proteſtants without ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception in this, and in his other pieces. I ſhall at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent give but one Inſtance, and that in this his laſt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply, where he ſays, that the <hi>Proteſtant Perſwaſion has its Name, Being,<note place="margin">P. 17.</note> and ſupport not from what it is in its ſelf, but from what it is not, in defying and proteſting a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt their Neighbours.</hi> 'Tis eaſie to ſee what notion of Proteſtants ſuch Paſſages as theſe are intended to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>print upon the minds of Men. But does the Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenter in good earneſt, believe that our Religion is a mere Negative Religion, and that we ſhould have none at all, if we had no <hi>Neighbours to defie,</hi> and to <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt againſt?</hi> Or does he believe that our Religion ſo far as it is Negative, is <hi>ſupported</hi> by <hi>defying and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſting</hi> againſt other Men; does he not know that we at leaſt pretend to <hi>ſupport</hi> it by Reaſon, Scripture, and Antiquity? Nay, does he believe that there are no Affirmative points of Religion which we maintain a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them, and in reſpect of which they do in reali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty proteſt againſt us, though it ſeems we have got the <hi>Name</hi> of Proteſtants. If he does believe thus of us, much more if knowing the contrary, he ſays ſo how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, Where'<hi>s</hi> Truth, Charity, or Juſtice? If we take the Religion, of Proteſtants, as it ſtands in oppoſition to the Errors of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> it is in many Points Affirmative, and the Negative is on that Churches ſide. For inſtance, that God onely is to be Worſhipped, is as Affirmative a Concluſion, as that God is but One, and that Chriſtian people are bound to read the Scriptures is as Affirmative, as that they are bound to ſay their Prayers, and that the Laiety have a Right to the Communion under both Kinds; is ſurely as Affirmative, as that they have a Right to <hi>One</hi> only. Why then does the Repreſenter ſay, that
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:60861:54"/>the <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Profeſſion <hi>has its Name, Being, and Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port; not from what it is in its ſelf, but from what it is not?</hi> But to let this paſs, what although the Points held by us in oppoſition to the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> were only Negatives; yet, why muſt we be ſo bitterly repreſented, as if our Perſwaſion were ſupported by nothing but pieviſhneſs and a Spirit of Contradiction to our Neighbours? Why muſt we be brought in as <hi>defying and proteſting againſt our Neighbours?</hi> As if we oppoſed their Doctrines and Practices, in deſpight to the Jews, and not rather blamed them for ſaying and, doing thing which we at leaſt think are not to be ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified? There are divers things ſurely, which neither Chriſtians nor Men ought to do; And ſo far as our Religion ſtands in not doing ſuch things, one would it is not the worſe for being Negative, nor our Practice to be blemiſhed for having its Name from what it is not. And therefore when Men come in with their Negatives in Religion, and their proteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions againſt falſe perſwaſions and evil practices, they are not without more ado to be repreſented as <hi>Defying</hi> and <hi>Proteſting againſt their Neighbours.</hi> But leaſt of all, ſhould it be infinuated, as if our whole Religion in effect, ſtood in this <hi>Defying</hi> and <hi>Proteſting:</hi> For we do in the firſt place Glory in this, that we are <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians,</hi> though we are not aſhamed to be called <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants.</hi> In our Religious Aſſemblies, where we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs our Faith before God and the World; we proteſs no other Articles of Faith, then thoſe in which the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> agrees with us. By this it is that we are Chriſtians, and it is this that makes them ſo. This Faith which we profeſs, and into which we were bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized, is the Foundation of our aſſurance, that if we live accordingly, we ſhall be ſaved, and of our hopes
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:60861:54"/>that thoſe among them, who are diſpoſed to receive the Truth, and repent heartily of all known ſins, ſhall find Mercy with God, notwithſtanding their Captivity to thoſe Errors, which if we ſhould profeſs, we could not have the leaſt hope for our ſelves. In the mean time for our Negatives againſt that Church, we offer in our own defence, that the Religion which the Scriptures teach, is ſuch a Negative Religion as ours, they not injoyning, and in ſome points forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding what we do not do; and that the truly Primitive Fathers neither profeſſed thoſe Doctrines, nor did thoſe things, which the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> would have us to profeſs and to do; ſo that their Religion was not more poſitive, nor leſs Negative then ours. But if it grieves good Men in the <hi>Roman</hi> Communion, that there ſhould be amongſt Chriſtians, any Proteſtation of one Party againſt what is done by another, it is a grief al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo to us; only with this, difference, that we cannot help it, but they can. For if they will Reform the Terms of their Communion by the Scriptures, and Primitive Antiquity, they ſhall ſoon ſee an end of our proteſting, and that our Perſwaſion is not ſupported, as this Repreſenter faith, by <hi>defying and proteſting a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt our Neighbours;</hi> then which he could not have ſaid a viler thing againſt us, no not if he had put us <hi>upon the ſame File with Infidels and Pagans;</hi> ſince this is in effect to ſay, That we have no Religion but in croſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to other, People.</p>
               <p>But at this rate we have been uſed all along, though we have made no complaints of it, onely they force us to it now, whether we will or no: Thus even in their <hi>Catechiſms,</hi> where one would expect plainneſs and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerity, we find our ſelves Miſ-repreſented in that man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, as if there was no ſuch way of making Novices
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:60861:55"/>faſt to their Church, but by giving them falſe notions of ours: For at preſent; to name no more then their famous <hi>Doway</hi> Catechiſm, there you find ſhall find the Teacher giving this wiſe reaſon, <hi>Why Proteſtants are ſo ſo divided, and damn one another for Miſ-believers? Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Abridgment of Chriſtian Doctr. <hi>p.</hi> 42. <hi>Doway</hi> 1655.</note> forſooth, <hi>it is the very ground-work of Proteſtancy that all men, even the whole-Church of God, are fallible and ſubject to errour.</hi> We ſay indeed that all men are ſubject to errour; but the very <hi>ground-work of Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy</hi> is not as this Catechiſt pretends that the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> and every other Church is ſubject to errour, but that ſhe hath actually erred, and that grievouſly too. And his Inference from hence is no leſs a Miſ-repreſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion then his principle: <hi>So that,</hi> ſays he, <hi>they cannot pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to Certainty or Infallibility in any one point of their Belief.</hi> So that becauſe he is pleaſed to put <hi>Certainty</hi> and <hi>Infallibility</hi> together, he muſt needs teach his Scholar that we have not ſo much as <hi>Certainty</hi> of our Faith, nay, not of <hi>one Point</hi> of it; and which is ſtill more falſe, that we <hi>cannot pretend</hi> to it. No wonder that we find it ſo hard a matter to get a little Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe about Religion with thoſe whom they have had the breeding of, when we ſee what an abſurd pretence to Religion they repreſent ours to be all at once; eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially ſince they take care to let them know, that <hi>'t is not well poſſible for any two Proteſtants or Sectaries to be of one Religion,<note place="margin">Id. p. 42.</note> every man expounding the Scriptures as he lifts, and no one having power to control the others Expoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of it.</hi> Which if their Schollars believe, they muſt needs conclude the Proteſtants muſt profeſs as many Religions almoſt, as they are men and Women; ſince it <hi>is not well poſſible for any two of them to be of one and the ſame Religion:</hi> And, I think, any body may ſee that this is taught to diſcourge all who are educated in this
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:60861:55"/>perſwaſion of us, from hearing what we have to ſay for our ſelves, ſince by hearkning to one or two of us they are never the nearer, but muſt talk perhaps with a million before they can underſtand the Religion of Proteſtants, nay, and ſhall then be as much to ſeek for it as they were at firſt. For what he ſays of <hi>every mans expounding the Scripture as he liſts, no one having power to control the others Expoſition of it:</hi> It is alſo an untrue ſuggeſtion, if by expounding the Scripture <hi>as we liſt,</hi> he means arbitrary and groundleſs Expoſitions of Scripture. Which when the Repreſenter pleaſes, I can prove the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> to be more guilty of then a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Church that we know in the World beſides: If any are guilty of it amongſt us, there is a power in our Church to control them, which has alſo been uſed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on occaſion, unleſs by power he means a <hi>Cudgel,</hi> and this we do not take to be Church power. Again, he ſays that <hi>all Heretics pretend equally to the Scripture for their Novelties and Hereſies,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Id. p. 44.</note> (which is not true nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther) <hi>no one of them ever yielding to another:</hi> Which is notoriouſly falſe; for many of thoſe whom he calls He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retics, have yielded to the reaſonings of others out of the Scriptures, who are alſo Heretics with him: And this plainly ſhews that ſome of theſe men care not what they ſay to diſgrace us, when they will ſo poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively affirm a thing which 'tis impoſſible for them to know but it may be falſe; nay, which 'tis not <hi>well poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible</hi> for them not to know that it is falſe.</p>
               <p>'Tis after the ſame way that our Doctrines and Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctices are repreſented by retail; of which I ſhall give you but one inſtance which I well remember, and that is where the Catechiſt aſſuring his Scholar that their Laiety <hi>receive whole Chriſt under one kind:</hi> Tells him alſo that this <hi>is incomparably more than the pretended Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formers
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:60861:56"/>have under both,<note place="margin">Id. p. 205.</note> who receive onely a bit of Bakers Bread, with a poor ſup of common Vintners Wine.</hi> By which ſcandalous way of repreſenting our Communion to a Novice, he would be apt to believe that when we celebrate the <hi>Euchariſt,</hi> out great buſineſs is to ſend to the Baking-houſe for Bread, and to the Tavern for Wine; and ſo we fall to eating and drinking without any more ado. If he would be Steeling his Novice a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt us, he ſhould at leaſt have been ſo juſt to us, as to let him know that we do not give the people <hi>common Bread and Wine,</hi> though we do not pretend to give them the natural ſubſtance of <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s Body and Blood.</p>
               <p>For that way of Miſrepreſenting us by charging the particular opinions of ſome Proteſtants upon all: They have the confidence to do it, even in thoſe points where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in neither Proteſtants nor Papiſts are of the ſame mind among themſelves: And though the <hi>Doway</hi> Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſm repreſents us ſo divided that 'tis not well poſſible for any two of us to be of the ſame Religion, yet when again 'tis for their turn to Repreſent us otherwiſe, there is not an odd opinion of any Proteſtant, but forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with it belongs to the Religion of all the reſt. Thus we have been charged for <hi>making God the Author of Sin;</hi> and that for nothing but for the ſake of thoſe O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions held by ſome Proteſtants, which are no leſs ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemently defended by ſome Papiſts: In which kind of Repreſentations no man, I think, has out done the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciler of Religions</hi> (whoever he was) printed in the year 1663. <hi>They teach,</hi> ſays he, <hi>profane, falſe, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly Doctrines, as for example: That God is the Author of Sin; that Chriſt deſpaired upon the Croſs.</hi> Which la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Opinions, this man and Fevardentius, and divers o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, as I well remember, faſten upon <hi>Calvin;</hi> and then talk as if it was the received Doctrine of all Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants.
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:60861:56"/>So ſays he,<note place="margin">P. 14.</note> 
                  <hi>They ſay that Chriſt ſuffered the pains of Hell upon the Croſs, and that this was is his Deſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion into Hell. See</hi> Calvin <hi>here,</hi> Pſal. 15. Now I think <hi>Calvin</hi> does ſay ſo: But 'tis ſo ſmall a matter in Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon, to charge what one ſays upon All, that I ſhall lay no great ſtreſs upon it. But that which fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows is admirable: <hi>Neither,</hi> ſays he, <hi>are they miſerably mad only, but alſo diabolically malitious; for its of meer purpoſe they ſay and do thus, leſt that by clear places of Tradition and Scripture they ſhould be conſtrained to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs that there is a Purgatory.</hi> Are not theſe rare Men, thus at once to charge us with what we do nat ſay or do, and withal to pronounce concerning our <hi>Intentions</hi> in ſo doing, and that in this Vile manner, that no honeſt Heathen ever uſed his Neighbour ſo? Nay, if you will believe this Repreſenter,<note place="margin">Ibid.</note> 
                  <hi>They that hear Sectarian Miniſters are not Believers, for they do not truly believe in God the Father Almighty, nor in Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt his only Son.</hi> For he knows their Hearts bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then they do themſelves:<note place="margin">P. 15.</note> and let them be never ſo confident that they do, he will prove that they <hi>do not believe in the Holy Ghost.</hi> And he peremptorily ſays that they <hi>do not believe the Communion of Saints:</hi> And laſtly, That <hi>neither do they believe forgiveneſs of ſins.</hi> For which he brings an excellent Reaſon, Becauſe they ſay ſay, <hi>The Prieſts cannot forgive Sins:</hi> Though we do not ſay that neither, but only that they cannot for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give Sins <hi>Abſolutely;</hi> which now they would per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wade us too, to be their own Doctrine.<note place="margin">P. 16.</note> Thus he has made us Infidels almoſt throughout the Creed, only at laſt he grants, that we believe the <hi>Reſurrection of the Fleſh, and the Life Everlaſting;</hi> which I wonder at, becauſe it was as eaſie to invent a reaſon why we believe not this neither, as for all the
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:60861:57"/>reſt. But then even in this matter, we are no better Believers then the Devil. <hi>For,</hi> ſays he, <hi>this they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, and ſo do the Devils.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>No wonder therefore that he comes afterward, and puts us upon the <hi>ſame File with</hi> Turks <hi>and</hi> Heathens. <hi>As the</hi> Turks <hi>are divided and ſubdivided among them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, ſo are the</hi> Proteſtants. <hi>The</hi> Turks <hi>whereſoever they come, demoliſh Churches, deſtroy Croſſes, and beat down and break Altars,<note place="margin">P. 37.</note> and Images; ſo do the</hi> Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants. <hi>The</hi> Turks <hi>cannot abide Praying to Saints; no more can the</hi> Proteſtants. <hi>The</hi> Turks <hi>love not Beads nor Holy Water; no more do the</hi> Proteſtants. <hi>The</hi> Turks <hi>above all things, hate the moſt Holy Sacrifce of the Maſs, and ſo do the</hi> Proteſtants; <hi>which alone is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to ſhew that in their Religion or Belief, they are like</hi> Turks <hi>and</hi> Heathens. This I think may ſerve at leaſt, to ſet againſt the <hi>Biſhop</hi> of <hi>Kilmor</hi>'s Parallel: Though I ought to ask the Biſhops Pardon for making the Compariſon. For as to that Parallel between <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants</hi> and <hi>Turks,</hi> it is not in every particular true, for <hi>Proteſtants</hi> do not <hi>demoliſh Churches whereſoever they come,</hi> nor <hi>break, down Altars,</hi> nor <hi>deſtroy Croſſes,</hi> nor always <hi>Images.</hi> And as to the particulars that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree to both, how much malice ſoever there may be, I am ſure there is little Wit in putting them and us to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether upon theſe Accounts. For certainly, we are no more obliged to do any ill things, becauſe the <hi>Turks</hi> themſelves forbear them, then we are obliged to forbear any uſeful or innocent Cuſtoms, merely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the <hi>Papiſts</hi> uſe them. Had this Reconciler ſhewn our Agreement with the <hi>Turks</hi> in ſome Practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. that we could not but confeſs they are to blame for; this indeed, had been a ſhrewd Inſtruction to us, to amend that in our ſelves, which we cannot but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:60861:57"/>in People ſo groſly deceived as they are. Now this it was, that the Biſhop of <hi>Kilmore</hi> did in that Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon of the <hi>Papiſts</hi> Worſhipping their <hi>Tutelar Saints,</hi> with the <hi>Heathens</hi> Worſhipping their <hi>Petty Gods.</hi> The Papiſts do with us, juſtly condemn theſe Practices of the Heathens. The Biſhop only deſires them, being thus prepared, to look at home. But to infer that in <hi>our Religion, we are like</hi> Turks <hi>and</hi> Heathens, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we forbear thoſe things, which the <hi>Turks</hi> are to be juſtified in not doing; is a Miſ-repreſentation of us, upon ſo <hi>wry an Inference,</hi> that if there be not want of <hi>Wit,</hi> to excuſe it, it will be found equivalent to a down-right Miſ-repreſentation, which the Genius of this Author, as it appears, by the particulars of this Book, makes me fear it is.</p>
               <p>And of a great many particulars which I might note, there is one not to be let paſs, and that is,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>P.</hi> 16.</note> that he does in <hi>very good earneſt,</hi> affirm that we adore the Sacrament, though the Repreſenter would be thought to charge us with it, <hi>little more then in Jest.</hi> For ſays the Reconciler, <hi>Though they ſay thus of us, for Worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping of Images, yet they can diſpenſe with themſelves in Worſhipping their Sacrament.</hi> And if this be not jeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, 'tis ſomething a great deal worſe; for it is as no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious, that we do not Worſhip the Sacrament, as it is that the Papiſts do.</p>
               <p>But to go on with him a little farther. <hi>Their Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers</hi> faith he, <hi>what are they forſooth? Intruders, Thieves and Robbers; Hypocrites, Ravenous Wolves, and Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derers; Sons of</hi> Belial, <hi>Falſe Prophers,<note place="margin">P. 51.</note> and Prieſts of</hi> Baal; <hi>which is their Hereſy, Rebellion and Stubbornneſs againſt the Church. — And if the Preachers be ſo, What muſt the Hearers be? Why ſure enough, they ſhall both fall into the Ditch of Everlaſting burning Brimſtone
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:60861:58"/>and Fire,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nleſs they be Converted, do Penante, and live in the Church.</hi> Now this way of Miſ-repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentation by railing at, and damning us, is as crafty a method, as any they have to imprint upon weak minds an incurable prejudice againſt our Communion. For when we are confidently repreſented as damnable Wretches, that ſhall certainly be <hi>Damned,</hi> if we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue <hi>Proteſtants;</hi> eſpecially by Men, that at other times talk demurely, and always look gravely when they give us theſe good words, it cannot be expected, but that ſome or other ſhould believe there is more then ordinary Reaſon for it, though they are not able to find it out. We may ſay what we will in our own Defence, let but theſe Men go on to ſay ſtill that we are <hi>Damned,</hi> and the very noiſe and din of theſe words, and the like, ſhall make them deaf to all the Reaſons we can bring. And therefore every degree of this dealing, is to be condemned in any party, wherever it is found, becauſe it is a way to work upon the Paſſions and Imaginations of People; and inſtead of directing, it does but confound their Judgment. But I muſt needs ſay, we have ſuffered under this injuſtice by thoſe of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> beyond any exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples that I have yet ſeen.</p>
               <p>Of which, I will give the Repreſenter one inſtance ſo remarkable, that it may ſerve inſtead of a great many. Mr. <hi>Harding,</hi> who had to do with no leſs a Man than Biſhop <hi>Jewel,</hi> thought fit to uſe us in this Faſhion,<note place="margin">Confut. Fol. 202.</note> as follows: <hi>Ye are moved by the Inſtinct of Satan; the Devil hath you faſt bound, and ye are the Children of the Devil: Ye are the limbs of Antichriſt.</hi> Our Church, he calls <hi>the Synagogue of Antichriſt and Lucifer;</hi> and we are no better with him, then <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane Hell-hounds,<note place="margin">F. 195.</note> Wicked</hi> Cains <hi>brood, Turkiſh</hi> Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guenots
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:60861:58"/>
                  <hi>worſe then Infidels;</hi> nay, he ſays that the <hi>Fiends of Hell begat Lutherans and Calviniſts;</hi> and that <hi>we would ſay if we durst, that Christ is the Abomination of Deſolation,<note place="margin">F. 194. F. 225.</note> and that Antichriſt is the true God.</hi> And then I think he had reaſon to ſay, That <hi>the Devil coming from Hell, hath carried us away.</hi> Thus in his <hi>Rejoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> he bids the <hi>Hell-hounds of</hi> Zuinglius <hi>and</hi> Luther<hi>'s, Litter,<note place="margin">Rejoynd. <hi>p.</hi> 178, 207, 111.</note> bark until their bellies break;</hi> and calls the <hi>Defender</hi> one that <hi>is like a mad Dog;</hi> and for all this, tells him that he <hi>will leave his Vile Eloquence to himſelf,</hi> [the Defender.] He that has a mind to ſee more of this, may find two Pages in Folio full of it, juſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Preface to the Biſhops Defence of his Apology. Now it is eaſie to Judge what effects this kind of Elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence will work upon weak minds, eſpecially when he that uſes it, has the Face to ſay as <hi>Harding</hi> did in the Preface to his Confutation. <hi>The manner of writing, which I have here uſed, in Compariſon of the Adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries is ſober, ſoft, and gentle, and in reſpect of their heat, bitterneſs, and railing, as many tell me, over-cold ſweet, and mild.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I do not ſay, that they never ſpeak of us, but in this ſtrain; for I do well remember that the <hi>Apology</hi> for the Papiſts which came out about Six or Seven Years after the Reſtoration, treats us after another manner, I mean <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s</hi> of the Church of <hi>England;</hi> for then it could call us <hi>Men, Brethren, and Fathers,</hi> and would fain unite them and us together againſt the <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natics:</hi> For why? then we were ſome-body, and it was not amiſs to <hi>curry</hi> with us: But there was a time when we indeed were as no-body; and then the Diſſenters were worth being <hi>curried</hi> with; inſomuch that Dr. <hi>Holden,</hi> who was always eſteemed by us as a perſon of the beſt temper and trueſt moderation among them,
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:60861:59"/>could not forbear ſhewing the difference he put be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween them and us, even where there was no neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty at all ſo to do, but the mere neceſſity of <hi>currying:</hi> For to a <hi>Diſcourſe concerning Infallibility in Religion,</hi> Printed at <hi>Amſterdam</hi> 1652. Dr. <hi>Holden</hi> gave his ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation in theſe words amongſt others, That the Book <hi>demonſtrated the falſe Foundations of the Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian Conſiſtory; of the Socinian Ratiocination; of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dependents Private Spirit; and of the ERRONEO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S, OR RATHER NO GRO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>NDS OR PRINCIPLES OF THE LATE PAR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TIC<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>LAR ENGLISH PROTESTANT SCHISMATICAL STNAGOG<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>E.</hi> But why are the ſeveral Diſſenters ſo ſoftly and gently touched? <hi>Presbyterian Conſiſtory,</hi> what harm in a <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtory?</hi> or in <hi>Ratiocination?</hi> Nor is much anger ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed in giving the <hi>Private Spirit</hi> to the <hi>Independents.</hi> Why, ſurely theſe are all complemented in compariſon to the Church of <hi>England,</hi> which is <hi>the Particular Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh Proteſtant Schiſmatical Synagogue</hi> of <hi>Erroneous, or rather of no Grounds or Principles</hi> at all. But why this difference I ſay? Why, nothing is plainer, it was then <hi>THE LATE</hi> Church of <hi>England:</hi> But when the <hi>Apology</hi> came forth, it was then the <hi>Preſent</hi> Church of <hi>England</hi> again. Then was Then, and Now was Now. Thus we are uſed by ſome of the very beſt of them.</p>
               <p>But to return to our <hi>Reconciler,</hi> He wiſely conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that we might take ſanctuary in the <hi>Bible</hi> againſt the hard words and reproaches they perſecute us with; and therefore to ſpoil that retreat, he will not allow that we have the Word of God amongſt us; for thus he faith, <hi>The Proteſtants, or Sectarian</hi> Bible <hi>is defective, therefore evil, and conſequently not the Word of God; for, beſides, what we have above ſaid, almost every year
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:60861:59"/>they correct it and mend it, chop it and change it, as do their Almanacks, adding thereunto what they will, and ſubtracting what they pleaſe.</hi> This is ſuch Miſ-repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting, that I had rather the Repreſenter ſhould give the proper name to it, then do ſo my ſelf: Nay, if this man were to be believed, we make ſuch material alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations in the Verſion or Edition of our <hi>Bible</hi> every year, as infers a neceſſity of altering our Religion upon it, the <hi>Bible</hi> being the ground of our Religion; for ſays he, <hi>Neither do they change their</hi> Bible <hi>onely, but alſo their Religion and Faſhion thereof grounded on it. If then e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very following years</hi> Bible <hi>be better then the former,<note place="margin">Recon. p. 38.</note> why may not the next years</hi> Bible <hi>be better then this year, and ſo to the end of the World? and in the mean time the</hi> Sectarian Bible <hi>never be perfect, or better then a yearly Almanack; not ſo good as an Almanack for</hi> Ever; <hi>as is</hi> Erra Pater, <hi>or the</hi> Shepherd's Prognoſtication, <hi>or</hi> Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man<hi>'s</hi> Calendar. <hi>Why then ſhould it be more the Word of God then</hi> Aeſop<hi>'s</hi> Fables, <hi>or the</hi> Turkiſh Alcoran? One would think now that he had done his worſt againſt our <hi>Bible;</hi> but he underſtood his trade better then ſo, &amp; therefore becauſe this calumny needed it very much, he was reſolved to help it with a good ſhare of that confidence, which I obſerved before, was peculiar to theſe men. For as if he had been yet <hi>over cold, ſweet,</hi> and <hi>mild,</hi> he mends the matter by ſaying, that our <hi>Bible</hi> is <hi>worſe then</hi> Aeſop<hi>'s Fables; it is Diabolical In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventions, and Heretical labors, and a Sacrilegious Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to deceive and damn all ſuch poor Souls as believe it,<note place="margin">P. 41.</note> and therefore worthy to be burnt with Fire in the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle of the Market at noon, and let all the people ſay Amen, ſo be it.</hi> This was a good hearty man I warrant him, and would not willingly loſe his buſineſs by doing it by halves.</p>
               <pb n="116" facs="tcp:60861:60"/>
               <p>I ſhould now have done with him, but that I find him afterwards impoſing upon his Reader with as ſhameful a <hi>Down-right</hi> Miſ-repreſentation of us, as ever was invented:<note place="margin">P. 50.</note> For ſays he of our Clergy, <hi>All their Miſſion was either the inſpiration of a Spirit they know not what, or the Commiſſion of a Child, or the Letters Pattents of a Woman, or the illicit and invalid ordination or miſſion of or by one</hi> Scory <hi>an Apoſtate Monk, who ordained the first Biſhops at the</hi> Nagg's-head <hi>in</hi> Cheapſide, <hi>in Queen</hi> Elizabeth<hi>'s time.</hi> Now I would deſire the Repreſenter to conſider with himſelf how he would have ſet us forth to the World, if we had invented the ſtory of Pope <hi>Joan,</hi> as they have done this of the <hi>Naggs-head</hi> Ordination: Why, ſurely he would have muſtered up all his Figures to repreſent us as the lewdeſt Varlets up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the face of the Earth? But though we have recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved that ſtory from their own Authors, and know what advantages to make of it, if we needed them; yet we are very willing to hear what any learned man can ſay to diſprove it, and to allow all reaſonable preſumptions againſt it. Of our Adverſaries we beg none of this candor, and deſire no more of them then not to tell tales of us of their own invention. As to this <hi>Nagg's-head</hi> buſineſs, I ask the Repreſenter two things, one is, Whether himſelf believes it? the other, Whether they have not commonly and boldly reported it up and down amongſt us? Let him then remember how he declaimed againſt us for creating in the people ſuch an averſion to Popery, which he did not wonder at, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he <hi>conſidered that ten thouſand Pulpits have been for many years declaiming againſt them, <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Reply </seg>
                     </label> 
                     <note place="margin">p. 43.</note> where every man has had a liberty of expoſing them as he pleaſed,</hi> &amp;c. Well, but what muſt we have expected by this time, if the <hi>Ten thouſand Pulpits</hi> had been all this while at
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:60861:60"/>their Service, when they have not been afraid to pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh ſuch ſcandalous untruths againſst us, even whilſst they had not all the liberty of doing <hi>as they pleaſe,</hi> which he imagines we have taken: If they take this freedom of telling of Tales, even here amongſt us, without any colour of proof, and againſt the Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of unqueſtionable Recods; we may, I think, without Uncharitableneſs gueſs that where they are under no reſtraint, they <hi>repreſent</hi> our <hi>Doctrines, as they pleaſe,</hi> and <hi>charge them with what Conſequence and Interpretations they pleaſe, and expoſe our Practices as they pleaſe,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>And make Narratives of</hi> us <hi>as they pleaſe,</hi> and <hi>make</hi> us <hi>as guilty as they pleaſe,</hi> and <hi>have made Truth and Goſpel of any thing against</hi> us <hi>as they pleaſe.</hi> And when I conſider theſe things, I cannot wonder that in ſome parts of <hi>Spain</hi> (where the Miſ-repreſenting Trade has gone rarely forward) they are made to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that we <hi>Engliſh,</hi> ſince we turn'd <hi>Heretics,</hi> are grown <hi>Satyrs,</hi> and have gotten <hi>Horns</hi> and <hi>Tails.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I am now ſomething weary of this unprofitable La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, and ſhall therefore add but one thing more, which is, That ſome of them are wont to Reproach their Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries only by their Faults, when they pretend to give them their whole Character, and to add what they have any Colour for, out of their own Heads, and ſometimes without any Colour at all; but eſpecially when the manner and circumſtances of their dying are to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated, for here the Attention and Paſſions of the Reader are commonly raiſed very high. <hi>Of</hi> all which <hi>Bolſec</hi>'s Life of <hi>Calvin,</hi> is a memorable Inſtance: Thus when he brings him to his declining Age, he tells us the <hi>ſeveral Diſeaſes which afflïcted him for many years to the laſt Gaſp,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Bolſec.</hi> Vit. <hi>Calv.</hi> c. 22.</note> were a certain and expreſs Token and Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of God's anger againſt him;</hi> and anſwers that Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:60861:61"/>againſt it, from the Calamities that befel <hi>Job,</hi> by the deliverance God ſent him at laſt: Which kind of reaſoning gives every man to the Devil that dyes of painful and tormenting Diſeaſes. But not content to argue from thoſe Diſeaſes by which <hi>Beza</hi> ſaid that he ended his Life, <hi>viz. Conſumption, Cholic, Stone,</hi> &amp;c. incident all of them to Old Age, and eſpecially to Men of a Sedentary Life: <hi>Bolſec</hi> adds one out of his own Brain, <hi>With which,</hi> as he ſays, <hi>God's open Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies by his juſt Judgment have been puniſhed,</hi> viz. That he had <hi>a most filthy and poyſonous <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lcer about his lower parts, which were corroded by Vermin. Thus,</hi> ſays he, <hi>Honorius</hi> the Second King of the <hi>Vandals,</hi> Dyed, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter he had <hi>perſecuted the Orthodox Church eight years;</hi> thus <hi>Maximianus, the moſt cruel Enemy of the</hi> Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans; and thus <hi>Antiochus;</hi> and thus <hi>Herod,</hi> who <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped the Honour of God;</hi> thus <hi>many more Hypocrites and Enemies of God periſhed, who under pretence and colour of Sanctity and Zeal, had fought against the Truth, and after a miſerable death in this World, have been thrown headlong into the Everlasſting Torments of Hell.</hi> And in this manner, as he ſays, was <hi>Calvin</hi> marked out; nay, he affirms it to be <hi>most true,</hi> that <hi>the Wretch not being able to bear his horrible Tortures, called upon the Devil, and expir'd with Oaths, Curſes, and Blaſphemies.</hi> Well, but one would expect now a very notable proof of ſo wonderful a matter as this was, and of all the reſt that he ſays upon this occaſion: Why, ſays <hi>Bolſec,</hi> they <hi>have given Teſtimony to this, who were about him in his Sickneſs to the last: And therefore let</hi> Beza <hi>and others deny it as they pleaſe, the thing is ſufficiently plain.</hi> Was ever malitious Story ſupported by more feeble Teſtimony then this? It ſeems we muſt take <hi>Bolſec</hi>'s word, that <hi>Calvin</hi>'s Friends and Servants reported theſe
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:60861:61"/>things: But can any man be ſo ſilly as to think that if <hi>Bolſec</hi> had come to the knowledge of this by any certain or probable means of Intelligence, that he, I ſay, would have ſuffered us to go without it? But then if he had pretended particular Proofs, he had laid him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf open to be particularly baffed: for which reaſon the ſafeſt way, was to ſay in general, The Servants ſaid ſo, and the thing is plain, and there's an end.</p>
               <p>Thus alſo <hi>Cochles</hi> repreſents <hi>Luther</hi>'s Death, <hi>viz.</hi> That he went to Bed merry and drunk, and was next morning found deal in his Bed; his Body being black, and his Tongue lolling out, as if he had been ſtrangled, which ſome think was done by the Devil, ſome by his Wife; and as they carried him to the Church to bury him, his Body ſtank ſo that they were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained to throw it into a Ditch, and ſo they depart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. Which is a very pleaſant ſtory, but that another tells it ſo croſly, that 'tis impoſſible but one of them muſt be guilty of Leeſing. The truth is, they were ſo impatient, that theſe kind of Tales were told and ſent up and down before the Man himſelf was dead, as I ſhall further acquaint the Repreſenter when he deſires it.</p>
               <p>In the mean time I <hi>forbear,</hi> as he ſays, and wiſh there may be no occaſion given, to carry on the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſy in this manner. This very little that I have ſaid of a great deal more that remains, being deſigned only to ſhew them what may be done, if the think fit to leave the Queſtion, and to fall upon us for Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>repreſenting them, inſtead of maintaining their Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trines like Scholars and Diſputants.</p>
               <p>There remains now but one thing more to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered, and that is, What Reaſon the Repreſenter had to tax the Author of the <hi>Expoſition</hi> of our Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine,
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:60861:62"/>with <hi>wiſhing for Moderation in the deepeſt Satyr, condemning the want of Civility in others, with the moſt exaſperating Reflections of his own,</hi> and a great deal more to this purpoſe; which according to the moſt impar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial Judgment that I can make, is all ſaid without Cauſe given. And the declamation of the Repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter here upon, ſhews only that if he had lighted upon a fit Subject, the man does not want words to ſet it out to the Life. <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Reply, </seg>
                  </label> 
                  <note place="margin">p. 45.</note> But what has that Author done? He charges them with <hi>their Art of Palliating, with want of Fairneſs and Civility, with laying aſide Moderation, and falling into a vein of Lightneſs and Scurrility, forget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting that Religion is the Subject, and Chriſtians and Scho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars their Antageniſts,</hi> &amp;c. Theſe things I confeſs he lays to their charge: But where's the <hi>Satyr?</hi> Where are the <hi>Exaſperating Expreſſions?</hi> The <hi>Pen ſteep'd in Gall,</hi> and the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncharitable Expoſing,</hi> for which <hi>he ſeems,</hi> to the Repreſenter, <hi>but to make a ſerious Droll?</hi> 'Tis true enough, that to accuſe men of <hi>Palliating</hi> their Religion, <hi>of want of Fairneſs,</hi> of <hi>falling into Lightneſs,</hi> of <hi>trivial Jeſtings,</hi> and <hi>accomodating their writings to the Genius of Scepticks, who divert them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves at the expence of all Religion.</hi> This I do acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge to be <hi>Satyrical,</hi> and as the Perſons may be up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on whom it falls, <hi>Exaſperating.</hi> But then the <hi>Satyr</hi> and the <hi>Sharpneſs</hi> lyes not here in the <hi>Manner</hi> of ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, but in the <hi>Truth</hi> of what is ſaid: And I hope that Author does not deſerve ill of theſe men, for ſpeaking the plain Truth of them in Expreſſions ſo ſoft and inoffenſive, as if he had taken time to chooſe the gentleſt: If they do not now repreſent their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion with that Sincerity which one would expect from <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> I know a great many ſharper words whereby one might juſtly expreſs that Fault, but
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:60861:62"/>ſcarce one that has leſs keenneſs, then that they <hi>Pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liate.</hi> If they bring in a <hi>Zealous Brother Ridicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling</hi> our Church, inſtead of Defending their own; could any thing be more cool, then to complain of <hi>want of Fairneſs and Civility,</hi> then to reſent their <hi>Fall<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing into a Vein of Lightneſs and Scurrility;</hi> and to put them in mind that <hi>Religion is the Subject, and Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans and Scholars their Antagoniſts.</hi> If this be turned in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to matter of Accuſation too, we have an ill time of it, who muſt have to do with men that can well enough endure to do all theſe things, but cannot endure to hear of it again, though in the mildeſt way of Repreſenting it: Had that Author, whoſe Books the Repreſenter may be aſhamed to acknowledge that he has read; had he, I ſay, written in the Repreſenter's ſtrain, had he ſaid any thing like making the King's Capital City a <hi>Proteſtant Sodom,</hi> and the Fires of <hi>Southwark</hi> and the <hi>Temple,</hi> our <hi>Evangelical Proofs</hi> againſt the Papiſts; and the Preachers <hi>Theme</hi> the <hi>alarum to keep the drowſie Flook from nodding;</hi> had he ſet the Repreſenter any example of ſuch unhandſome levities as theſe are; and which, to ſay no more, are hardly tolerable upon the ſtage, then indeed the juſtice of his charge would not have born him out in his management of it: But when that excellent man had charged them with no more then what he has terribly proved, and that is <hi>Palliating,</hi> or with no more then what is flagrant in their laſt pieces, viz. <hi>Want of Fairneſe and Civility,</hi> &amp;c. in a word, with no more then what is true; and this without virulen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy or ſo much as levity of expreſſion, (for which I leave the World to judge by thoſe very phraſes which the Repreſenter has picked out of his laſt Book) and yet for this, <hi>his Pen</hi> muſt be ſaid to be <hi>ſteeped in Gall,</hi> and his <hi>Antagoniſts expoſed under the most odious character
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:60861:63"/>imaginable.</hi> I might well make more, but I cannot make leſs of it, then that ſome men are very much <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſperated</hi> by being ſhewn to themſelves.</p>
               <p>And now, if I had a mind to take every occaſion, he has given no ſmall one by bringing in that Parable in the Scripture, <hi>Of the Trees chuſing a King;</hi> to illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate his own <hi>ſeriouſneſs</hi> in the <hi>Drolling</hi> Sermon he compoſed for the zealous Brother: <hi>But I forbear at preſent,</hi> becauſe he pretends to <hi>forbearance</hi> too.</p>
               <p>For the advice that he has given the forementioned Author, I do acknowledge that it were very good, but that it wants pertinence and occaſion; and for that rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon looks more like an unjuſt Accuſation, then a chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Admonition. But if he thinks good counſel is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways to be received with thanks; I ſay to him what he ſays to our Expoſitor, <hi>Let him turn to ſuch of his own Communion who have given bad examples</hi> in the buſineſs of <hi>Miſ-repreſenting.</hi> And let him too that gives good advice take it alſo; which though it be not ſo eaſie, it will yet be better for him: But above all things, <hi>Let him endeavour that their Arguments and Methods for the defeating of Proteſtants, be not ſuch as any Jew may take to ſtrike at Chriſtianity, and every Athiest to make a ſham of all Religion.</hi> Which advice is ſo good, that 'tis pity it ſhould be loſt upon thoſe that need it not; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I deſire him to recommend it to the Author of the Parallel between the Doctrine of the <hi>Trinity</hi> and the Doctrine of <hi>Tranſubſtantiation.</hi> Let the Repreſenter do his duty well upon this occaſion; and I can hereafter tell him of others wherein his intereſt will prevail more then mine.</p>
               <p>But becauſe the Repreſenter is <hi>ſincerely</hi> of our Expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitor's <hi>mind, That this way of handling Controverſies, doth rather exaſperate then heal our Diviſions.</hi> I will tell him
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:60861:63"/>an effectual way to prevent it, Let them Repreſent their Religion like men that are not afraid to let the people know the bottom of it; and when they offer to defend their Doctrines, let them not pretend to go on with their firſt undertaking, when they leave it, and fall into Invectives againſt their Adverſaries: for if they would honeſtly confeſs that their buſineſs is to make us look as odiouſly as they can, they ſhould, for me, go on in this way till they are weary, without any recrimination. If the Repreſenter deſires alſo that theſe Controverſies may have an end, let him per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade his Friends not to produce teſtimonies out of the Fathers for Popery, without taking notice of the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers that have been ſo often made to them: Which ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, if it had been given and taken, we had not ſeen the <hi>Conſenſus Veterum,</hi> and the <hi>Nubes Teſtium.</hi> Let them not furniſh out Books with Arguments that have been often offered, and as often anſwered; but take the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſie where it was left by their Predeceſſors and ours, and then go on with it if they can; which had been very good advice to Mr. <hi>Clenche.</hi> Let them not begin all over again, to ſpin out the time, and to make our Diſputes endleſs: Let them write and do like men that hope to gain upon the World by Reaſon and Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument. As for our parts we ſhall be careful to follow his laſt Advice, and to prove our ſelves true <hi>Members of the Church of</hi> England, not onely by maintaining the Truth which She hath taught us, but by practiſing thoſe <hi>Principles</hi> and that <hi>Loyalty which we Preach;</hi> that as we are ſenſible to whom we owe the Liberty we en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy, ſo we may approve our ſelves not altogether un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy of it, but be always able to give ſome good ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of our ſelves, with reſpect to theſe Controverſies, both to <hi>God</hi> and the <hi>King.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:60861:64"/>
            <p>THE D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ctrines and Practices of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> truely Repreſented; in Anſwer to a Book inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuled, a Papiſt Miſ-repreſented and Repreſented, &amp;c. Quarto.</p>
            <p>An Anſwer to a Diſcourſe intituled, Papiſts Proteſting againſt Proteſtant Popery <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eing a Vidication of Papiſts not Miſrepreſented by Pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>tants: and containing a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Examination of Monſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>aux,</hi> late Biſhop of <hi>Condom,</hi> his Expoſition of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> in the Articles of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ocation of Saints, and the Worſhip of Images, occaſioned by that Diſcourſe. Quarto.</p>
            <p>An <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nſwer to the Amicable Accomodation of the Difference between the Repreſenter and the Anſwerer. Quarto.</p>
            <p>Biſhop <hi>Wilkin</hi>'s Fifteen Sermons. Octavo.</p>
            <p>Sermmons and Diſcourſes, ſome of which never before printed, the third Volume. By the Reverend Dr. <hi>Til<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lotſon</hi> Dean of <hi>Canterbury.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Manuel for a Chriſtian Souldier. Written by <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raſmus,</hi> and Tranſlated into Engliſh. Twelves.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Printed for</hi> W. Rogers.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:60861:64"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
